Hey welcome back.
So we have a brand new section here on a brand new exciting hopefully exciting data structure trees.
So trees aside from being everyone's favorite perennial plants are also a classic data structure.
They're taught in computer science classes around the world.
They're also very commonly used all around the world.
So they are a bit of a step up from links to lists a little more complicated but also maybe a little
more interesting.
So quickly let's run through our objectives.
We want to define what a tree is.
Compare and contrast trees with length lists and arrays and things like that.
Explain the differences between these different types of trees.
We're going to talk about just plain old trees than binary trees.
And then finally binary search trees and binary search trees is what what this section is really focused
on.
But we're going to talk about these three categories and then most of what we'll be doing is implementing
a bunch of operations on binary search trees.
So we'll define our own BSD binary search tree.
I say BSD from here on out.
Our own BSD class and out a bunch of methods like we did with a singly linked list or doubly linked
list.
But first we have to talk about what a tree is.
So trees are data structures that consist of nodes just like the links listed but they're in a parent
child relationship.
Hopefully consensual we basically end up with branches.
So from one node we can have it connects to one other node or two or three or 10 or 0 nodes but we end
up with these branching structures.
Hence the name tree.
Think of an actual tree.
We follow a branch and it splits at some point and then that branch can split and they can keep splitting
and we end up with all these different little branches off of this main original branch.
Now often when we see diagrams or they look more like this where they're top down rather than a tree
which grows from the ground up.
It doesn't matter right to same exact structure it's just flipped.
But usually you will see them represented like this.
So here is an example of a tree.
Each one of these circles represents a node just like it did on our length list.
But notice this is very different than the length list in that each node can point to more than one
or can have more than one reference to another node.
So this is our top most node will go over the terminology.
This is called the root.
And it points to 9 as another node.
It also references 12 and 8 in ninety nine and 10.
And each of those nodes potentially references one or more other nodes or actually zero.
In this case this is a dead end and nothing comes after 12 has 1 2 three children Nine-Nine has two
children 10 has two children and so on.
So this is an example of a tree but they're not always like this.
You might have a tree that looks like this.
We have a single top most node and it branches off into two nodes and then each of those only branches
off into one node.
So it doesn't have to be this nasty complicated mess.
It could be simple.
This is also another example of a tree and you know it doesn't have to be numbers we can just like a
linked list we can store data in there we can store strings or I mean if you wanted to you could store
anything.
Arrays are.
I don't know what would you want to put there.
Most of the time it's numbers and strings but it could be anything so when we talk about lists lists
are linear.
It's one thing and then the next then the next then the next then the next everything is in a line in
a row.
Trees are non-linear.
They can branch.
We can have more than one pathway through a tree with a length.
There's one path in a double Alicea you could work backwards or forwards but still there is one line
through our data structure in trees there's many different paths we could take just like the journey
of life.
All right you end up here.
This is a decision you have to make.
You could make one choice and go this way.
And if you do make that choice you'll never know what was over here.
And then you make another choice.
This is one path here.
This is another path.
This is another path with a length list.
There's only one pathway through.
So you can think of a singly linked list as a very special case of a tree.
So this could be a tree.
It's not a great use for a tree but if we had this to pointing to 12 which points to its child 11 you
could represent that as a length.
Just to add 12 to 11 but you probably wouldn't do that it would probably just use the length lists.
If this is what your data looks like but I just want to show that this is a special case.
But as soon as we added a second branch here or here it's not it's not a first as soon as it becomes
non-linear.
Now when we're talking about trees there are some rules.
So this is not a tree.
So what we have here are nodes that are referencing other nodes that are not below them.
That makes sense or not children.
So a node can only point to a child and the parent child relationship.
We can't have a child pointing to parents we can't have a node pointing to a sibling.
We can't have what what's going on here.
This is actually what's known as a graph.
Talk about these later a tree every node is moving away from the root node if that makes sense.
All these arrows have to point down if we are trying to represent it.
So this is also not a tree.
It looks like it could be because all the nodes are pointing away from the root but there is no one
root.
We have two beginnings of this tree.
So that's not a tree.
We need to have one entry point.
So as I mentioned there is some terminology.
The root is the top node in a tree.
So if we go back to this tree this is the roots a child is a node directly connected to another node.
When moving away from the root a parent that's the converse notion of a child.
I think those two make sense siblings are nodes that have the same parent.
A leaf is a node with no children on this tree.
This is a leaf.
It has no children.
This is also a child of this node.
This is the parent of this node.
This is the root.
And lastly there's terminology for the connection which we call an edge.
It's the actual arrow between one node and another or at least in my diagrams It's an arrow.
OK.
So we have root.
This is an edge.
This is a child relative to this parent but it's a parent relative to this child.
This is also a leaf.
It has no children.
And I think that's all the terminology right edge.
Yeah.
I covered Bill.
OK.
So that's basic terminology it's just helpful for us to discuss when we're implementing code I'll say
something like.
All right we need to you know add the edge from this parent to this child.
Or I might say Let's check if a node is the root or if it's a leaf and so on.
OK so we'll leave off here.
Next I'm going to talk about some real applications of trees and we'll also introduce binary trees and
binary search trees in the next video.