All right.
Welcome back.
Next what I'd like to do is quickly run through some real world use cases for trees.
These aren't just theoretical things this isn't just about you know interview prep.
Trees are used all the time even if you're not fully conscious of it.
You've interacted with trees both as a javascript developer most likely but then also just as a user
of the Internet.
So the most common example is Tim L and the DOM.
The document object model.
So when we think about age Tim Well it lends itself to a tree like structure.
Right we have elements and inside of elements we can have nested elements that are child that are child
that are children and we can keep having children nested in nested nested further down.
And if a parent child relationship between those aged him elements which are just text but then once
he gets to the browser after a request and get the response the browser then reads through it all parses
it and it creates the DOM.
The document object model and in Chrome we get this nice debugger we can click through sort of an interactive
way of viewing the different nodes.
But behind the scenes there is a corresponding javascript object for each one of these nodes.
So there's a body you know we can access it just by talking typing document dot body and print text
for us here but it's actually an object.
And if we do dot we can see it has a bunch of properties a bunch of methods we can call and we can do
things like look at its children and it gives us a list of children.
So let's take the first thing in there that gives us a node and we can do it children on that and there
are so just one thing in there that looks like there's just one child div instead of that first child.
Anyway if you're not familiar with the Dom I wouldn't worry about it just know that it's a tree structure
very very.
They use one.
So another application has to do with network routing.
Definitely not my expertise.
I'm not even going to try to explain how it works but if you go to the routing page in Wikipedia we
get all sorts of diagrams of trees over here.
So these are different delivery schemes for how basically a message is transmitted to a node or to multiple
nodes and you can see that we've got some tree structures going on here and that's pretty much all of
that because I know nothing about network routing.
But behind the scenes there are some trees being used there's a bunch of you know classic computer science
logic that goes into finding the shortest path.
Anyways Next up we'll talk about abstract syntax trees.
So these are our way of describing the syntax of a programming language using a tree structure.
So without going into too much detail really doesn't matter.
Honestly all that matters is that you see that this is a tree structure.
Whatever language this is for it's from Wikipedia.
If you do want to read more about it we you know we have let's say a while loop instead of a while block.
We have a condition as part of the while and then we also have the body inside of that while And in
that condition we can have a comparison between a variable and a constant and this is a very succinct
shortened version it's missing a lot of logic.
But the point is to show you that this is a way of basically if you were writing code to take in other
code and run that code or to parse that code or to make sure it's valid syntax you could use an abstraction
text tree to help you out next.
Trees are used in artificial intelligence all the time.
There are tons of applications for trees and artificial intelligence and machine learning.
Probably the simplest example is something called a minimax tree.
So let's say we're building a tic tac toe game we want to build an AI that is very good that it isn't
just picking random moves.
We could basically break down the logic of the game into a tree and we basically would say here's a
given state of the board.
And these are all the possible moves that the human player could make with them.
They are so the computer is X and what we see here is OK you know if a human player plays in oh here
the best possible mood to move to make is to put an X right here and in that way X would win.
If an O goes here the best possible move is to put an X in the middle and then it depends what 0 does
next.
You know there's multiple options.
Basically this tree structure just describes a bunch of different possible options for what could happen.
And after a given move by the opponent the best possible next move.
So that's really superficial.
You didn't even scratch the surface of how you actually implement this and what the minimax part is
the logic.
But all that I want to show you is that this is basically called The Decision Tree.
You have different decisions that you make branching points and you follow one and then that splits
and you follow the next decision and you keep going.
And these have applications in very complicated you know classification algorithms for example not just
tic tac toe AI.
And then finally probably the simplest example is the way that your folders are models and an operating
system you know if you see something like this on a Mac or PC your computer is represented as a tree
structure.
There's all these directories it's hierarchical.
There's a root.
There is a top most folder you know on a Mac.
I actually don't know what it is anymore.
On your account it's the root directory.
But you know there's multiple accounts.
You can get a computer anyway so it doesn't matter.
But let's just say we're looking at a given folder this folder inside this is maybe our root.
We have two other folders inside.
And then they have files in.
Yeah.
Technically this has two types of nodes you could say those files and folders but the structure itself
is treelike we have all these branches and those children have children of their own and so on.
So that's just a quick introduction to some of the real world use cases for trees.
Sure you know this is not a purely theoretical thing it's not just an exercise.
This is stuff that comes up all the time in programming.
One example I totally forgot to mention is Jason.
So if you've ever worked with Jaison javascript object notation you'd get it you know I don't know an
AJAX call you're sending in a request and you're getting some data from an API when you parse that response
from a string into javascript or for using Python or whatever language you're using.
There's code that is traversing a tree or creating a tree like structure as you can see here I'm using
a Chrome extension just to view some child nodes and they each have children and this is a tree structure.
You can represent this easily.
Well I shouldn't say easily it suits itself to being represented by a tree it's a lot of work but it
still is a tree structure where we have parent and child nodes but there's at the end of the day a single
root.
All right I'll leave it off there.
There is a lot of different uses for trees.