Welcome back so much like the real world where we have tons and tons of varieties.
Types of trees get different categories of trees got families.
I'm not a botanist.
I do like trees though.
But there are many many types and we can enjoy them all in the world.
Anyway in the world of computer science data structure of the tree there are many varieties as well.
So actually on Wikipedia there is an article that contains a list I don't know if it's complete but
this from here on out I'm going to scroll through.
These are all varieties of trees all different types.
So they all follow the same rule defined by.
They fit the pattern of a tree but they'll add in some special properties some rules basically something
that makes them a bit different and often you know some of them will be much faster at searching or
insertion of a particular thing or they excel at storing data in a particular format or data that is
you know contains a lot of duplicates or data that's all unique and they all.
I mean I haven't heard of the.
The majority is not even a good way of putting it.
I haven't heard of like 95 percent of these.
There's some very nice trees here.
And you can see also there are different categories of trees like keep's Oh dear I don't know if you
hear that my cats hang on
sorry about that.
Where was I.
There are many types of trees and different categories different groupings like heaps which we'll learn
about later.
We're going to talk about this video.
Mainly our binary tree.
So one group sort of like you could think of in geometry.
There's this thing called polygon just any shape.
Well I guess not any shape any cit. shape or there's any number of sides and within that we have quadrate
laterals.
That's one family just like this is a family.
And then we have triangles and other family.
And within that we could have you know within quadrilateral there's rectangles and trapezoids that's
about as far as my geometry goes at this point.
So the trees that we're going to focus on are trees in general we've already kind of laid that out.
But more specifically binary trees and even more specifically binary search trees.
So binary search trees are a special type of a binary tree which is a special type of tree and they
excel as you can imagine from the title at searching.
So we store sorted data in a particular way.
We'll get there in just a moment in a binary search tree which makes it easier to retrieve.
Let's just recap this is just a generic tree.
Each node could have any number of child nodes we've got this one has four children.
One two three four.
This one has zero children.
This one has three.
This one has two this one has one.
There's no real rules about how many binary tree on the other hand has a special condition.
Each node can have at most two children at the binary part.
So it can have zero children can have one children one child and it can have two children.
So our root node usually would have two and then each node could have two or could have one or it could
have zero but it can't have three.
For example this is not a binary tree.
This is a valid tree in general if we're just talking about generic tree but it is not a binary tree
and there are also I've heard of ternary trees where there's three at most each node can have three
children.
I'm sure there are terms for you know Khwaja unary quad.
I don't know five six seven eight but they're just not as commonly talked about because binary trees
have some special properties that make them easier to navigate.
And we'll talk about that when we talk about binary search trees which is actually right now so binary
search trees are a special case of a binary tree which is a type of a tree.
So they are trees they most have two children per node 0 one or two children.
And on top of that binary search trees are sorted in a particular way they are kept in an order.
So B-S tease which is what I'll probably say most of the time because binary search tree gets a little
bit annoying to say beasties are used to store data that can be compared.
That is sortable so often classically we're talking about numbers and that's what we'll be working with.
It could be strings it could be any other piece of data that that you know has some way of there's a
way for you to order it and compare things which one is greater which one is less.
So this is how they work.
This is the special magic property.
If we take any node on the tree it's tried the route all numbers or every item that is less than this
node is located to the left of it every item or number in our case that is greater than is located to
the right.
And you could repeat that on each child node.
So if we look at six to the left are the numbers smaller than 6 to the right are the numbers greater
than 6 like 8 or 15 over here.
We only have one node but 20 is greater than 15 so it's located to the right of it.
So to review that binary search tree is a type of binary tree.
Every parent node has at most two children but on top of that every node to the left of a parent node
is always less than the parent and every node to the right of a parent node is always greater than the
parent.
So here's a slightly larger example.
We take any node like the root all nodes to the left.
All of these should be less than forty one and everything to the right is greater than 41.
And then we could try that again over here at 20.
Everything the left needs to be less than 20 and it is everything to the right is greater than 20.
Same thing down to 11.
Blah blah blah.
Over here it's the same exact property.
So that's what makes a binary search tree a binary search tree rather than just a binary tree.
So the data is kept in a particular order every node every child to the right is greater than a node
A parent node and every piece of data to the left is less than the parent node.