A quick pop quiz here is this a valid binary search tree with these pieces of data.
These numbers take a look.
Posit if you need a little extra time the answer is No.
So what's the problem here.
Well if we look on this node 8 to the left three is indeed smaller than 8 but 6 is larger than 8.
So that is not good.
That's invalid.
How about this one.
Is this valid.
Well hopefully you can tell right off the bat the answer is nope it doesn't matter what the actual numbers
are because this root node has three children.
So it's not a binary tree any more.
So out of the question an forgivable.
Next here's a slightly larger one.
Is this a valid binary search tree.
Take a moment to think about it.
The answer is nope.
Once again And the problem area is right here.
So we have three.
And to the right we have six so six is larger than three.
That's OK.
But to the left we have four.
Four is greater than three and everything to the left has to be smaller than three.
So invalid.
So three invalid trees for different reasons.