The last thing I'd like to do before we actually dive into coding went up in the next video is explain
why these are used.
And really the way that we order them where everything to the right is greater than the parent and everything
to the left is less than the parent makes it much it makes it very easy and makes it fast to look things
up.
Also it makes it easy to insert things to find a place for a node.
So that search part of the binary search tree becomes very quick compared to looking for node in an
unsorted tree.
So let me show you how it works.
Imagine we have this tree and we're looking for the number 72.
Although we have to start is the.
So we don't actually see that our code doesn't know what's lying ahead.
It just sees the root all that we have to do is check.
All right.
1:53 greater than 41 Yes.
So we only care about this half of the tree.
Basically every comparison we do should roughly chop in half the number of values we look at.
If you remember how binary search worked in a list it's the same idea where we have this data sorted
where everything to the right is greater everything to the left is smaller or less than.
And we make a comparison.
Ideally we chop the tree in half.
Now it depends on how the tree is distributed.
We could have way more values over here.
And very few small values but in general on average we cut the number of comparisons with number of
nodes in half.
So we check.
Seventy two is greater than 41.
So we only care about this side.
So then we go to 65 is 72 less than or greater than it's greater than 65.
So we go over here now we get to 91 is 72 less than or greater than 91.
It's less then and we found it.
Now if you compare that to if this was an unsorted tree and 72 was indeed in the tree it could be anywhere
in this tree and we might have to look at every single node and traverse the entire tree.
And we'll talk about how you would do that.
But you know you could pick any order do you go all the way here first and then here and then here and
then down here.
Do you go to the right for you.
There's a million ways if there's not a million.
There's many ways of traversing a tree but with a binary search tree when we're looking for a value
there's a very specific procedure we follow we compare and we go to the right or the left.
We compare again and we cut it in half.
Keep going until you find the value or you don't find it.
But you know because the way a binary search she works the value is not in there if you don't find it.
OK.
So to recap here there's many types of trees.
There are binary trees where each parents or each node can have at most two children.
There are many types of binary trees one of which is the binary search tree a binary search tree works
or sorted data or sortable data where there's an order you can compare things and it's the same rules
a binary tree every parent node has at most two children.
But on top of that every node to the left of a parent is always less than the parent every node to the
right is always greater than the parent.
And that makes it so that we can search we can find things much faster.