Welcome back.
In this video I just want to get us set up with our basic skeleton our two classes.
So we'll have a binary search tree class and then a node class just like we did with a linked list.
We had the link to this class and then a node.
So a binary search tree itself really only has one important property which is the root.
And then each node has a value.
But instead of having a dot next or previous We have a left and a right so I'll quickly code this up
I'll fast forward through some of it.
So our constructor takes a single value in and we just said this value equals value.
And then this dot right.
I like to do the left first.
I don't know why and this dot right doesn't matter at all.
OK.
So that's our single node.
Now we'll just make our binary search tree you could just do B S T if you prefer and instead of that
of a constructor it doesn't take anything.
You could have it take an initial value and create the node if you want it to.
But we won't do that and we'll just do this.
Root equals no.
Now with this we could construct our own basic BSD I could say you know our tree equals binary search
tree.
I need to say new binary search tree and then we could do tree dot root equals new node.
Let's say with the value of 10 and then we could manually say tree root dot right equals new nodes so
it needs to be greater than 10 let's say 15 tree root left it equals new node of something less than
10.
How about 7 and we could keep going.
I'll just do one more level to do tree root dot left dot right.
So this needs to be less than 15 because it's to the left of it.
But it also needs to be greater than 7.
So let's say no and you start to be less than 10 and greater than 7.
So let's go with it actually 9 like odd numbers and this sets up a simple binary search tree.
Although it's a huge pain to insert things like this.
So just like we did with a singly linked list where we're going to add is a method called insert and
it will figure out where something goes.
Based off of comparisons Oh this needs to be new.
Node 9 showed I was doing there let's run it.
Just make sure it works.
If you look at our tree.
OK.
We've got to root out roots.
I mean there's not much for us to really check at this point.
We have some nodes that are connected each node has a value left and a right.
OK.
In the next video I'll explain how Insearch would work.
And then we'll get coding.