Welcome back.
So now let's add a way of inserting into our tree so we have a value.
I should be able to call insert passing the value and the tree will add it to the correct place.
It will make the new node and then put it in the correct spot depending on what that number is.
So for example if you're trying to insert 13 where would that go on this list.
Well we would start and we would check how does 13 compare to 10.
Well it's greater than 10.
So it goes over here somewhere.
How does it compare to 15.
Well it's less than.
So is there a node to the left.
If not that's where 13 goes if there is a node.
Then we go to that one and we check how does it compare to 13.
Do we go to the left or the right.
But there is no node.
So that means this is 13 new home or on a slightly larger scale.
If we did an insert of.
Sure.
Sixty eight.
I'll posit first to check.
Is there a route.
If there's no route then that becomes our route.
But there is so we compare 68 to 41 and it is greater than 41.
So we check.
Well is there a right.
Is there a node over here and there is.
So we compare 65 now to 68.
Well 68 is still greater.
So we're going to go to the right again.
And now we compare 91 and 68.
Well 68 is less than 91.
So we go to the left and we do it again we compare it to 72.
Well 68 is less than 72.
Is there a left.
No there is not.
So that means this is where 68 goes.
That is its new home.
So those are the steps that we follow.
And if you want here's the pseudo code you can do this.
If we are recursively I think it's easiest to do it personally iterative.
But either one will work the rough outline.
You don't have to follow this order exactly you know verbatim.
You don't have to create a new node on line one but at some point you create a new node and then you
start at the root.
You check if there is a root if there is not.
Well that's super easy.
You're lucky the root now becomes that new node that just means we have an empty tree.
The very first time we insert something.
But if there is a root you check if the value of the new node is greater than or less than the value
of the root.
And depending on that if it is greater we check to see if there is a node to the right.
If there is move to that node and repeat the steps so have some sort of loop write a while loop.
I would just do like.
While true have something continue to go.
If you're doing an iterative fli at least and inside of that you're just going to check if it's greater
then move on to the next dot right and then check for greater or less than that and eventually you will
find a place to insert it.
So the process just one more time check if there's a route if not easy.
It's an empty tree.
Just add it to be the root if there is a root.
Compare your new value to see if it's greater than or less than.
And if it's greater then you need to check if there is a node.
If there's nothing there then that is the new home.
Same thing if it's less than you need to check.
Is there a left.
If it's not as if there is no doubt left then that's your new home.
Otherwise you just move on to that right and you repeat the steps or you move onto the left and repeat
the steps just like we saw here.
We tried to insert 13.
We check.
Is there a route.
Yes.
OK so 13 is greater than 10.
That means we need to check.
Is there a dot right.
Yes.
So now this is where we start getting the same process is 13 greater than or less than 15.
It's less then.
So is there a left.
No.
So that is where 13 goes and then we would return at that point.
So I didn't add this in the pseudo code but I think it's best to return the entire tree at the end of
the method.
It's not a deal breaker but that's what I like to do instead of just returning nothing or returning
the node and return the entire tree at the very end.
All right.
So give it a shot in the next video.
I'll have a solution.