All right welcome back.
Let's go ahead and write the code for insert.
So I have a snippet over here with the same classes I showed you two videos to go.
We have our node class value left and right and then we have our binary search tree class with which
just has an empty root to start.
Now I recorded this video once before and I was using this sort of basic binary tree structure because
it's really hard honestly to visualize how this all should look like the links list is easy.
You know you insert something it should go afterwards you end up with this linear list with a tree.
It can be hard to keep track of where things should go.
So I recorded the entire video and then I realized that I had messed up this entire tree.
It just doesn't actually make sense.
The values that I used it's not a valid binary tree.
So we have 10 on the left side.
Every value should be less than 10.
So that's true on the right side every value should be greater than and then 10.
But if we look at five to the left values are less than the right.
Four is not greater than.
So I should have something like 7 there.
Same thing over here.
I don't know what I was thinking.
13 the left of that 14 does not work.
So let's go with 11 for example.
Now we have a valid tree.
OK.
So let's start by defining insert which takes a value and we'll just make that new node to start.
So our new node equals new node and passing the value.
And then let's go with the easy win which is to check.
Is there a route already or is there not a route like if we just did try to answer 10.
That becomes the root.
There's nothing in there so we'll just check if this route is no then we're going to set out roots to
equal the new node and then return this just so that we get out of this.
None of the other code will run because we're returning.
I run the code.
We look at our tree.
We've got 10.
Now if I tried to insert something after this like three nothing happens because well technically we
make a new node but then we never attach it or insert it and nothing is returned because this code doesn't
run.
OK.
So now the bulk of the logic happens in the else portion to remember the process.
If our tree is only 10 right now this doesn't exist.
What we do we check.
Is there a route.
Well if there's not a route then we do this otherwise which is what we have here.
The Otherwise condition we need to check is our value less than or greater than this value right here.
And if it's less then what are we going to do.
We're going to check.
Is there a left.
And if there's not then we put the value right there.
Otherwise same thing on the right side.
Now that's the case if there's only one node in there.
But if our tree looks like this let's say we're inserting the number one.
We would check.
Is there a root.
Yes there is.
All right is one less than 10 or greater than it's less than.
So then we check.
We know it goes on the left side.
We check.
Is there a node on the left if it looks like this.
We should put one right here.
But if it looks like this while there is a note here.
So then we compare again is one less than five.
That's true.
So we're going to insert it on the left somewhere do we insert it right here.
Nope there's already a value there.
So then we move down and repeat.
So the process involves looping just like with a length list.
And I'm going to make a variable called Current and current will start as the root just like in our
linked list examples current started as this started the beginning of the linked list and we're going
to update current as we go.
And I'm just going to add in a while true we're going to continue over and over and over so unlike with
the links where we had a link that we could you could add a length but it wouldn't help you here.
I mean length isn't even really the right measurement.
You could add like a number of nodes or something.
But that still doesn't really help you.
So I'm just going loop while true and I'm going to break out of this loop using a return statement.
If we finish if we insert the node.
So while true basically our process is going to be you know check if the value is less than or greater
than.
So let's do that now.
Well just to if value is less then and then current value if that's the case that means it's going to
go on the left somewhere over here.
But we first need to check is there current data left.
So another conditional if current dot left is equal to know if there is nothing on the left and we found
our spot eventually like if we if we end up here this is current.
If there's no left in the value is less than this value then we insert it to the left.
OK.
So we'll just say current left equals new node and then return we're done.
We don't want this loop to keep going.
Now this code will actually work only if we insert like 10 and then 5.
It's not going to work if we insert something after that because if we insert 10 that's all that we
have then we check if value is less than current value.
If this is current yes 5 is less than 10.
There is no left.
So we've set five right here.
And if we just verified that if I run this code and I look at the tree then we look at the root and
then we look to its left.
We have five.
OK.
But it wouldn't work if we tried to insert two or 13 or any other value to the right or to the left.
So although we need to do if it is less than 10 or whatever the route is but there is already a value
here.
Then we need to move current to now be 5 and then we do the same thing.
And if there's already a value to the left or to the right then we update current two whichever one
it should be.
And then we check again.
So really here all that we need.
Nice and short.
It's just current equals current left.
So we're moving to current left because the value is less than the current value.
So if this is what our tree looks like and we're trying to insert the numbers three we'd start here.
Three is less than 10 so we need we know we need to look to the left but there already is a left.
So this part does not run.
So we update current.
Now we 5 and do the same thing.
This time there is no left so we insert right here.
OK.
So this is just handling the left side and we could verify that it works by inserting like the number
two.
For example if we run this our tree should have root of 10 the left of 10 should be five and the left
of that should be two.
We have no right set up on any of them.
So we just need to basically do the same thing for the right side.
So I'll do LCF value is greater than current value.
If that's the case we're going to check if current right is no.
If it is then we found our spot current outright equals new node return this otherwise.
Keep looking.
Update current so that we traverse further current equals current rates and we should be good to go
here.
See if I have any typos or any issues.
Let's now also insert some other value.
So 10 5 2 but do try to insert 13 to 11 and 16 and also said OK let's run this.
Here we go we've got our tree.
And what should we explore explored first let's go down the right side this time.
So here's our route of 10 and to the right we should have 13 which we do.
To the left we have 11.
And to the right we have 16 that all looks good.
Let's check the left on the left we should have five to the left of that we have to the left that we
have 7 let's just verify it still works let's say we insert what about 3 where should that go.
Well defend the left side and we find two.
It goes to the right of two.
So if we look at tree and we look at the route then we look at the left which is five.
The left has two.
And then the right of that is now three.
So we basically inserted it this diagram is getting ugly but we inserted it right there.
OK.
So it looks like it's working.
Let's see how does it handle or does it handle duplicates.
So if I tried to insert 10 for example what happens.
Well I had to restart my browser.
Or at least this window because we hit an infinite loop and I was trying to illustrate that but I didn't
actually think it through there was nothing to show you looping infinitely all that you wish saw or
would have seen it's just my computer get hung up and me being unable to type.
So we got an infinite loop because if I tried to insert 10 or any of these numbers that are already
in there we have this while true but we're only checking if the value is less than or greater than.
Now how is how we actually handle duplicates is really up to the special case of what we're doing the
specifics.
Some people are just going to ignore them.
Some people some trees just ignore them outright.
That's what we'll do.
We could just add a check in here to see if the value is equal to current value.
Then we will just return false or undefined or something.
The other option though that you might see is if you need to know like if we're inserting certain things
over and over you want to keep track of that.
You could add a frequency or a count to the node and you could increment that.
So next to each node we can have accounts like this.
And you know maybe we have four six teens are in there for some reason and two tens.
So if you needed that you could do that but I'm just going to add an if at the very beginning if value
is equal to current value then let's return undefined or something undefined.
OK let's try running this again.
We look at our tree.
Everything looks good.
Ten five two.
OK.
Let's try inserting 10 again.
We get undefined and if we look at the tree it's still still works.
Not that hopefully nothing should be changed.
Everything still works if we tried to insert something other than 10 that's already in there like 7.
It takes a little bit because it does have to traverse the tree until it finds the right spot and it
realizes oh this is already in there.
OK.
We're done.
Lastly some people get a little up in arms about this.
You can simplify some of this logic.
There's a couple of places that are unnecessary.
For example here if value is less than current value we check if there's currently a left and we return.
And before I had an else here but because there's only two options and four returning here we don't
necessarily have to have the else it's just a stylistic thing so I have both solutions.
This one is a little longer but it's more explicit about things.
So there's else's same thing here.
This else is well we don't have to have We're checking if the route is no return.
If it is we're done elsewhere we don't have to have the else we could just start.
So that's what I did here.
But just tiny changes really ascertain if you prefer the solution.
Yeah you can use this one.
It's really the same logic just slightly less explicit but also less verbose.