All right.
Welcome back.
Next let's add a method called Find or search or whatever you want you know contains node basically
the idea is that you have a binary tree and you can search to see if a value is in that tree.
So he could search to see if 50 is a tree or 100 isn't a tree.
And the process is very similar to inserting in a binary search tree at least because we have those
rules.
The you know greater than to the right less than to the left.
So we can cut about half the tree away each comparison that we make.
So for example when we go to insert a number like let's say we're inserting seven into this list.
Let's do that quickly.
Insert the number seven.
All right we compare it.
It's less then less than this very fast.
We checked once we got to 11.
Was there a left.
Nope.
Well that's where 7 goes.
Now for doing the same thing but searching for 7 I'll go slower this time we do the exact same steps
we check.
All right is this 7.
No.
So it's less than OK.
So we need to look on the left.
Is this 7.
Twenty is not seven.
So seven is less than again.
So we look on the left is this 7.
Nope it's 11 but we know that 7 is less than 11.
So we looked to the left and what do you know we found seven.
So we return true or return the node.
We're just going to do.
True or false.
To see if we found it if it contains that value.
And if we were inserting something that isn't in there or sorry if we're searching for something that's
not in there like let's say we're searching for 75 go.
All right we start here.
Is this equal to 75.
The Root.
Nope.
75 is greater.
So it's going to be over here if it's in here on the right side.
So we get to the next node.
All right is 75 equal to 65.
Nope.
It's greater then.
So it's going to be over here on the right OK.
So we look now we have 91.
Well 75 is less than 91.
So we need to look to the left and we get to 72 and now 75 is greater than 72.
So we know it needs to be on the right but there is no right.
So that means it's not in here.
If we find the point where we basically hit the end of the tree on one branch and there is no dot net
or not next there's no right when we're looking for it right or there's no left and we're looking for
a left that tells us the value is not in there assuming our tree is set up correctly.
I mean if for some reason 75 was overhear incorrectly Of course we're not going to find it because we're
not checking every single node.
That's the point of the binary search tree.
We know the order that things are stored and we know how it's structured.
So we can take advantage of that into a much faster search.
OK so in this case we would return false or return no.
And this is what they're showing.
So the basic steps start at the root check if there's a route.
If not we're done because there's nothing in there.
If there is a route check the value of the new node see if it's equal to what we're looking for.
If you found it then we're done.
If not check to see if the value is greater than or less than if it's greater.
Look to see if there's something to the right.
If there is move to that node and repeat the same steps if there's not that means that we're done.
Same thing on the left.
So I walk through it one more time.
If you feel good to go try an implemented on your own.
It's very similar to what we did in the last video with insert.
It's just actually a little simpler let's say that we're searching for 40.
We're going to start here 41.
Right.
40 is less than 41.
So we look to the left.
We get to 20.
Well 40 is greater than 20.
We check.
Is there something to the right.
Yes.
So then we start the loop over is 40 equal to 29.
No.
So we check it's greater than.
So is there a dot right.
Yes.
So we move down here and start the loop over is 40 equal to 32.
Nope.
So then we check.
Is there something to the right because 40 is greater than 32.
No there is not.
That means we didn't find it.
We return false.
So those are the basic steps.
Go ahead.
You know you don't have to follow the pseudo code to the tee it doesn't contain every bit of information.
For example we want to have probably a while loop and I would make a variable called found in a variable
called Current or start or some sort of variable to keep track of where you are.
And then a variable that you'll set to True or false that will stop the loop.
So when you find it the loop should stop or if you hit the end then you should return OK.
Give it a shot.