Already let's implement find on our B S T class.
So the first thing we'll do is just add the method find which accepts a value and we have a couple of
couple of optimizations we can make at the end.
But I'm just going to start by following this.
We're going to check if there's a route.
So that's simple.
If this route is no then we're just going to return what we want to return undefined false.
Let's just say we want this to be true or false.
So we're going to say that it either returns true or false.
So if there's nothing in there then we can't find the value returned false.
That's nice.
If we run it we make a new a new tree.
Call it the new binary search tree.
We do not find one.
We should get false.
All right so that's out of the way.
Now what I'm going to do is make a variable called Start and I'm going to start equal the roots.
You can also call it current.
I kind of actually prefer current.
So I'm not going to call it start.
OK with current and then let's make another variable and this one is going to be called found and it
starts as false.
So found just keeps track of.
If we've found the item yet.
Then we need to get to the bulk of our logic which involves basically looping.
So I'll do a while loop and we want to loop while not found so while we haven't found the thing.
But also while there is a current so I'll explain why in just a moment.
But we want to keep going because if we let's say we never find it right it's not in there.
Found is always going to be false.
So we also need to make sure this loop doesn't go forever so current is going to be our value that as
soon as there is no current whenever there is you know we've hit the end of the tree we can't update
current at all.
It's no then our loop will stop.
So basically this is while there is something to loop over and we haven't found it what do we do.
Let's start by just checking if the value is less than current dot value.
If it is left less than then we're going to say current is now equal to current left.
We know that it needs to be on the left side.
So for example if this is a tree we have and we're looking for two.
Well if we did a tree up find two we're going to set current to equal this node and then found it's
going to be false.
So we check 2 is less than current value that's true.
So now current is this.
And so we start again.
So let's do the same thing with an LCF value is greater than current value.
If that's the case current equals current right now we're missing the most important part which is the
else.
If we found it we're going to set found equals true.
So this is if it's less than this is if it's greater than the only other option is that it's equal to.
So we'll set found true.
And then the loop should be done because this is now false.
Not found not true is false.
So we're done here.
Then after this while loop we'd need to return the node.
Well that was pretty unclear about this honestly in instructions.
I regret that if you should return the note itself or return true or false to see if it contains it
let's return the node.
So that's going to be current.
I apologize if you implemented one solution and I did the opposite here but the logic is the same either
way we could return true right here if we found it we can return current.
Okay.
So I'm going to return current at the end and then we also want to check if it's never found we should
return something because right now ups did not mean to do that.
If we run this code we've got our tree values that have all of these.
So if I look for.
You know try to find 5 for example.
Okay.
It was in their tree up find 10 that's in there.
It Out find this time to that's also in there.
OK.
But what about 100.
That's not in there.
So we're getting no instead of No.
I think it would be better to return false.
So to do that we could just add an if statement here.
If it's not found not found return false or actually I think undefined might be better but doesn't really
matter.
But just some value here to indicate it's not in there.
And if we wanted to so just to be fair if we wanted to do that.
True or false version.
So it doesn't actually return the node it just returns true or false so maybe I'll call it contains
value.
It's a little simpler because if we find it we can return true.
And we don't need this here.
We can just return false OK.
So if we find it if it's equal we return true.
And then the only way we get here is if it's not in there.
So we return false.
So if I run this one would you treat dot contains one that's false but 10 is in there so it's two and
16 I think.
But 18 is not in there.
OK.
So sort of out of left field but I just had to do two implementations one true or false only returned
values called contains the other one is called Find and it actually returns the value the node itself.
If it's in there.
OK.