All right.
Welcome back.
So we're still talking about binary search trees but we're not going to implement any new methods.
We're going to do right now is review the two methods we've already added.
And in particular focus on their performance their time complexity.
So as a binary search tree grows whether it's let's say it starts at 10 nodes and it goes up to a million
nodes.
How much more time on average but we'll also talk about best and worst cases.
How much more time does it take to insert a value or to search.
I've actually given it away already.
This is best and average case of log.
And I'm going explain why that is in just a moment.
But if you don't remember what the log is what logarithms are.
If you didn't watch the well if you don't remember from math class.
Totally understandable.
It's not that useful in everyday life but if you didn't watch the video in the beginning of this course
in the Big O section you might want to go check that out.
It explains in some more detail basically what this means.
And just as a refresher this actually means a log based to of and which is really it's so lazy the way
that big-O works we just simplify simplify simplify.
We get rid of the base too and you just say log in.
OK.
So let's talk about how we arrived here.
The first thing to get out of the way is that Logan is good.
That is a solid time complexity that if we look at the chart which we will in a moment you'll see that
it grows pretty slowly.
All right.
So here we have two trees two binary search trees.
I just want to reiterate what I'm talking about in this video is only for binary search trees.
They have to be sorted because they give us this nice nice shortcut.
So here's this first tree.
It's what seven nodes.
Something like that.
As we look for a value let's say that we're searching or inserting it doesn't matter because we're basically
doing the same thing.
We're finding the correct spot for it.
So let's say I'm trying to insert 15:9 into this top tree.
Well we're going to have to start here and we're gonna have to make a comparison go here another comparison
go here another comparison and then insert the value.
Now if we doubled the size of the tree.
So this has double the nodes as the one above it only has one more level down one more step.
Its height grows by 1.
So in this tree even though it has double the nodes as the one from above we only have to look one more
time we have to only take one more step.
So if I was trying to insert 61 this time I just have to go one step two steps three steps four steps.
This one that has half the nodes was three steps.
So this relationship here because the way we keep it sorted and again that only works in a search tree
a binary search tree as the tree doubles as a number of nodes doubles.
We only increase the number of steps by 1.
So that relationship is log based 2.
So here's the actual chart from Wikipedia of log 2 of X..
If you look at it just the positive side as we double the value from 1 to 2 we only take one step up
as we double it again to 4 two steps up.
So we double it again to eight 3 steps up.
If we go back to this big O complexity chart where we just see all of the different notations charted
next to one another you can see that log in is really solid.
It grows very very slowly compared to something like I don't know and squared quadratic time.
I mean that's not good or analog in or even linear time.
The only thing that's better on this chart at least is constant time.
So log in is good.
It takes a while takes a long time for it to start to grow.
And this is the same for insertion and for searching.
Just to reiterate that they're the same idea because the way that the tree is set up we follow the same
steps we compare do we go right or left compare.
Do we go right or left.
And whether we find the value or we insert.
It's the same sort of number of steps.
OK so now let's talk about why I said not guaranteed.
So of log in is it time complexity for the average case of a tree but also for the best case there's
no faster possible way.
But when we talk about worst case it's not guaranteed.
And that's because there are some binary search tree configurations that are very slow at least compared
to the ones we've been looking at.
For example this very sad floppy mopy binary search tree.
This tree which really just looks like a linked list or something there is very it's entirely one sided
but it's still a valid binary search tree because if we take a value every node to the right is greater
than its parent and we keep going into valid the entire way.
So if we're talking about inserting into this tree if we have a tree like this let's say how many items
is this 8 or something.
If we had it grow to a million items and it was still a one sided tree which is not a good use for binary
search tree but if that's what you had and it kept growing and growing and growing then the number of
steps it's going to take to insert or to search is going to grow as the number of nodes grow.
So that would be 0.
And if you had a completely one sided tree like this.
Now there's a really easy solution to this which is just don't store a binary tree or binary search
tree like this.
If you needed this as a tree and you wanted it to be sortable you could rewrite this binary search tree
where you pick a different route pick.
I don't know 34 is the root and then restructure the entire tree and have these values to write these
values to the left.
That would make your searching and insertion much faster already.
So I just want to point out though this is a valid BSD.
So this is why I said not guaranteed to be overflow again.
But on average insertion and searching in a binary search tree are 0 of log and for time complexity.
And that is pretty good.
Pretty good.
All right.
Moving on.