Hey welcome back.
So we're moving on to our second data structure another length list first this time it's a doubly linked
list instead of a singly linked list and basically spoiler alert.
All that we do is add a pointer to the previous node and the next node.
So each node points in two directions that seems like a very tiny change and it is to the actual structure
but it has some large ramifications for the code that we write the methods.
But first let's talk about our objectives.
We're going to construct a doubly linked list.
We'll compare and contrast doublin singly length lists and will also implement basic operations like
we did in the last section push pop shift shift insert get set.
All those things.
But first let's start by just describing how it works.
So it's a property mentioned.
It's almost identical to a singly linked list.
We have a bunch of nodes.
There's no indexing.
So it's still a blink first.
It's not like an array.
We don't have random access using numbers or an index.
We start we have a head and we have a tail but every node in the list points to the next node ahead
of it.
But also the previous node behind it.
So that's where the doubly linked part comes from instead of just pointing to the next next next.
It looks more like this.
So we have a head pointing to the next item and then also has a previous pointer but there's nothing
because it's the beginning.
So then our second item points to the next item but also to the previous item and all the way down to
our tail the last item.
It has no next but it has a previous.
So as you mentioned it's a tiny change structurally to each node just one pointer pointing to the previous
node in each node but it has a large impact on some of the code we write and the efficiency of certain
operations.
For example when we're talking about popping off the last item of a lengthy list a singly linked lists
like we have here there's just one way this Duret the arrows are pointing one direction.
There you go.
If you want to pop this last item off and I go to remove from the tail we have to iterate the entire
list and we have to find the the second to last item.
Remember if you watched the video on pop in the last section we had to find the second to last item
and make that the new tail.
We can't just go to the tail like if we go on to remove 16 we can just go to 16 and remove it.
We have to go to the item before it and make that the new tail.
So we can't work backwards when we're talking about a double length.
First however if I want to remove the last item I can just go to the tail and work backwards with previous.
I can move this direction instead of having to go from the beginning until the end of the second to
last item.
I can just work backwards.
Or another thing that is much much easier.
Imagine that you wanted to print out a length list in reverse or you wanted to iterate it in reverse.
If you had a singly link first and you try to go backwards.
It is a huge pain.
It's horribly inefficient.
You basically start at the beginning go all the way to the end and you can't work backwards.
So you could start over and go to the second the last thing or I mean you could make an array and just
add things to that array one the time as you go through and then reverse that array.
But there's no easy way to just start at the beginning and go or start at the end and go at the beginning
with the doubling length first.
You can start here and we can just do up previous previous previous.
It's just as easy as going from the beginning.
Next up next up next.
And as we go through the section Oh definitely spend time comparing the two singly and doubling for
us and how they perform on certain operations and you'll see that some of the code we write is a little
bit more complicated because at the bare minimum we have to now account for two pointers we have to
update a next and previous every time we add something in or remove something or delete some well remove
and delete that exact same thing.
So we have some more work to do but it's not that much harder.
The real drawback is that it takes up more memory.
So it's kind of always a tradeoff in programming more flexibility using a doubling length list but it
also means more memory.
That's a huge step because now we're storing our previous and next instead of just next.
OK.
So this will be something we come back to but we will leave this off for now.
At this singly linked lists and a doubling First they are very very similar in a lot of ways for length.
There's no there there is no indices.
There is an order to them and they just consist of a bunch of nodes connected by pointers singly link
this is one directional just that next or I mean theoretically just previous but a doubly linked list
has both directions it points to the next item and the item behind it the previous item in the next
video will implement our own doubling length list and we'll get working on push and pop and some of
the other methods.