All right.
And this quick video I just want to set up our two classes we're going to have node just like before
and we're going to have doubly linked list and the basics of both are very very similar to what we had
before.
The only difference is that a node now has a value it has a next and it has a previous R.W. length list.
Class is just going to have a head a tail and a length.
Just like before.
So this is unchanged now but logic the code we add to this will change a lot all the different methods
we add compared to singly think for us.
That's why we have a whole section on it.
But the actual constructors COME UP look the same.
So let's start class Node class Node here at our constructor.
Each node has a value.
So we set this dot Val equals Val and then we have this next and we'll set that to know the beginning
and stop previous equals nil.
So this is really this is the only difference in the node class.
Otherwise it's identical and then are doubly linked list class will just do class double the length
list as a constructor.
Just leave it empty.
And we just need to set this head equals no this dot tail equals no.
And this length starts at zero and that's it.
That's our skeleton.
So I'll get rid of this now.
You don't need that.
This is what we'll be using and adding on to our node class is done when we don't touch that anymore.
We had everything to this class.
So we'll be adding you know push just like before or pop or whatever else we do if we want to just test
it out though just to make sure it works.
Let's run this code let's just work with the Node class.
Let's do.
I don't know first equals new node.
Give it a value just give the value of 12.
All right.
We are first and I can do first duck next equals new node.
This time it's going to be 13 and so far we're just working with this as a single length for us because
I said first dot next to be that new node.
Now the crazy thing is I also need to take 13 which is the next item and I need to link it backwards.
So I want to say first dot next which should give me 13.
Yup that node Next Previous.
It's very bizarre right.
Were saying first thing next.
It's reference to the previous thing should be the first thing.
And now if we look at first it connects to this next node but that next node has a reference to the
previous node.
And actually we could just keep pushing this and going back and forth between the two.
Anyway that's the skeleton for our doubly linked list class.
In the next video we're going to start adding methods.
First up is going to be push so we can get some data in there.