All right.
Welcome back.
So our first challenge is to write a push method.
So are doubly linked list class doesn't do anything right now.
Let's add a method called Push that takes a node or takes a value and add a new node to the end of the
doubly linked list.
So if we visualize that here found a push something in at the end I'll do creates and oh no not create
insert after tale is how we specify at the end.
Let's do all that we have to do is find the tail and we make a new node eighty.
We connect the dots next of the tail to our new tail and then we also need to go the other direction
we need to take the new tail and connect it backwards to the old tail.
And then finally we make this the tail we move that over.
So if we wanted to write the pseudo code the steps that we need to follow the first thing is to create
the new node that you're going to add in so create a new node with the value passed in.
We need to check if the head is no.
Or you can also just check if the length is zero.
Basically check if the list is empty.
If it is the head and the tail are both the newly created node and you don't actually have to do anything
else.
If that's the case because there's no previous or next to connect.
We just make the head and the tail the same.
Otherwise if there is something in there already we take the current.
And we set the next property on it to be the new node that we just made but then we also need to take
the previous property of the new node and set it to be the old tail.
So we need to point the arrow backwards.
If this is making the forward arrow the next we need to do the previous from the new node back to the
old tail and then we just need to update the tail property to be the new node that is now at the end
just like we did here where we inserted we step back here we make the new node we connect the old tale
to the new node then we connect the new node to the old tail and then we just say all right this thing
is the tail that's the last step.
And then lastly increment the length and then return the entire list.
All right.
So in the next video we'll have a solution.