Welcome back let's get writing our solution to push.
OK.
So the very first thing we'll do after actually writing the method is create the new node with the value
passed in.
So let's start there.
So are doubly linked to this class going to add push which accepts a value because I want to be able
to say list push 50 or push hello or whatever.
So let's make that new node new node equals new node with that value that's passed in.
So we have that new node next we want to check if the list has anything in it.
So if the head is empty if the head is empty empty head I have the empty head right now.
If the head property is no or if the list is empty meaning that the length is zero.
We could do this.
However we want.
Actually just to show that it doesn't matter.
I'm going to do something that I didn't specify when I say if this length equals zero which is another
way of just checking if the list is empty.
We can also do if this starred head is no.
Or if this tale is nil it doesn't really matter.
OK so I'm going to do this.
If that's the case what did we need to do.
We need to make the head and tail be the newly created node.
This dot head equals new node.
This tail equals new node.
Otherwise set the next property on the tail to be the new node.
OK.
So let's do else.
So this means that there's something in there already.
So let's say that the list already has the number 99.
And what we need to do is add in 100 at the end.
So if this is the current tail I'm going to say this tail which would give me 99 dot next equals the
new node.
So that gives me the arrow going this way.
But then I need to also set this the new tail or it's not the tail yet but it will be previous to be
the old tail.
So to do that all I need to do is say new node datt previous equals this tail.
So that's giving me I'm going to basically say 100 previous.
See if I can do this arrow backwards.
There we go.
Is the old tail this tail.
Still the current tail actually.
And then finally we need to update the tail to be the newly created node.
So I'd just say this tail is now new node which is now moving.
If this was the tail before this if I can tab over it now.
Finally we need to add one to the length.
OK.
So that's going to be this length plus plus or plus equals 1 and then return the entire list return
this.
Let's test it out.
I just executed my code.
Let's make a new list.
So I'll just call it a list equals new length list and then I'll say list dot push let's push in a number
like ninety nine.
Let's look at the list expand this.
It should have head ninety nine and tells 99 and like this one.
All right let's stop push for more time.
Stu one hundred This time we should have had just 99 and tail 100.
This has a next.
The head is pointing to one hundred that's good.
And the tail 100 should be pointing back to 99 in the previous perfect.
Last check lets you push out your last list push last item and if we look at our list length 3 that's
all correct.
Everything looks good.
Our tail has lost item points.
Previous to this node and this node with 100 has both a next and a previous.
All right.
So that works.
It's pretty similar to what we did with a singly linked list.
The main difference is that we have to do a double connection.
We have to do a little more work connect to the next and the previous.
Next up is pop which is a little bit different much simpler in a doubly linked list.