All right.
Next up we'll implement Pop on a double length list.
So pop should work the same way as before on a singly linked list or any array or list for for that
matter.
It should just remove the last item and return it.
The difference on a doubly linked list.
I'm actually looking at a singly linked list here well which was more complicated.
It's annoying honestly to pop something from the end because it's not a matter of just finding the tail
and removing it.
Well that actually is the problem because to actually remove the tail we have to find the item before
the tail and set the next property to nil in order to chop that to sever the bond.
But we can't work backwards so we have to go at the beginning and you know I'll fast forward through
this.
Actually it's going to be very short.
There we go.
Just keep going.
We have to go all the way until we find the second to last item.
Here we go.
And for that tie a W link first is much easier.
We just start at the tail and we can just access daat previous.
So if I want to remove the last item we just start there and work backwards.
So the pseudocode looks like this.
If there is no tail so we need to first check.
You know we're trying to pop off something that's empty.
If there's no head or No-Tail or if the length is zero.
Just pick one.
Return undefined.
So if it's an invalid pop if there's nothing to pop off return undefined.
Otherwise take the current tail stored in a variable so that we can return it later.
So we're going to chop off the connections the lifeline between the second the last item in the tail
but we need to first store the tail so we can return it.
There is a special case if the length is one set.
The head and the tail both to be null.
Because the list is now empty update the tail to be the previous node.
So this means we had the old tail at the end.
We want to now say the tail is actually the old tail that previous.
Then we want to now take the current the new tail that we just updated.
We moved it back when item we want to take it next and make it null.
So that's what was happening here.
I stepped back.
All right.
So we find the tail we move the tail to this item.
Now we want to say this next is null so that should sever the bond and actually be extra precise we
want to take the last thing that we're returning and said it's previous to be no as well just to clean
up any extra ends any extra references.
Then we subtract one from the length because we pop something off and then we return the value that
we removed and that's it.
So the sides don't make this very clear.
Actually they don't say it at all.
It's not even that it's not clear when you sever this bond.
You need to remove both connections so it's not enough just to say this next is NO TO GET RID OF ONE
DIRECTION.
We should also remove the other reference.
Technically it may not be a problem because if we're moving this to be the tail and we set the next
to be No it's not yes an issue in must somebody somehow starts from this node and they go down previous.
And then that gives them the entire list.
So would you want to chop that off so that it's on its own it's just the node that were returning were
not returning any linkages to the list.
OK so give it a shot and the next video will have an implementation.