OK so let's implement pop.
So I'm going to head over and just write the skeleton I've got pop no arguments and the first thing
we want to do is check if there's anything in the list or rather we want to check if it's empty.
So instead if it's the last time I did if this top length is zero this time I'll do if there's no head
of a head this list return undefined.
So that's just like the singly first pop.
Next one I'm going to do is store the current tail in a variable.
So I'll call this pops node.
This is the thing that we're popping off.
It's going to be this duct tape.
Then we have our special case that we talked about if the length is one make the head and tail.
No.
So if this length equals one what are we going to do.
We want to set this head equals no this tail to be no perfect.
Otherwise we need to update the tail.
And what that entails what that means if this is our current list let's say we do have one to find three
and seven and we're popping seven off.
Well there's two connections there.
We have this connection and you have to pardon this hideous diagram.
Oh my gosh this is terrible.
There we go.
We have this connection.
OK.
So if this is currently the tail that's what the letter means we have this in a variable.
We're going to say this is the new tail.
So that's easy to move that reference there all that all although we have to write is this tail equals
Pop's node dot previous.
Right.
That's just going to say take this thing up previous.
That's the new Tell.
All right.
Next we're going to set the new tails next to be no.
So that's going to be severing this bond here.
So that's just this tale next equals no.
Now there's one thing that we have to do remember is we remove this linkage.
We update the tail.
We need to remove this linkage too.
And that just means.
So actually I'm not going to do that right away just to show you.
So I'll come back to that.
This is a better way of teaching it.
I hope so.
We need to Lastly Inc.
Or Dickerman the length and return the value so this tellt length minus minus or minus equals one and
return the value so popped node.
OK.
So let's run the code.
Here is our list.
What we don't have one yet let's do new W-why first let's push one stop push to.
OK.
So if I do list up pop right now it gives me back the node and you'll see that it's next is no but it's
previous is still there it's still pointing to the old tail or to the new tail.
Excuse me this used to be the tail and it has that linkage still.
So the list itself doesn't it's not connected.
If you look at the list the tail has no next and no previous Because it's only one item.
So there is no connection to this old node going one way going next.
But if we have the old node if I saved it to a variable let me actually do a couple more pushes.
Let's just add on.
I don't know 50 and 100.
If I look at the list it's three items long and the last item right now is 100.
If I do var old tail equals list of pop and I look at the old tail I can do that previous.
And then previous again.
And I can walk through the entire list.
So I didn't just return.
Well I did just return the node node has lingering connections.
So we want to sever those ties remove that entirely and to do that.
It's not that bad.
We're just going to take pops node dot previous equals no.
So to summarize the steps we create a new node we set the new tail to be the one right before the new
node that's much easier than the singly link for us.
We don't have to loop through that or navigate the entire list.
We don't traverse it.
We just start at the end and do our previous.
Then we just set this up tailboard next.
This is the new tail next.
Now nothing is empty.
So we chop that one line and then we take the old tail previous and set it to be no as well.
So we chop the second connection then we subtract one from length and return the pop node.
So let's just verify it works.
So let's verify it works.
List equals new lengths list double the length list that is.
Let's push let's just make sure if I do a pop right now by the way it shouldn't work.
Whoops.
Let's see if we have one small issue which is this shouldn't be giving me an error and it's because
it can't read previous.
No.
So it's getting to this line and it shouldn't be because it's empty.
This is why we want to check this dumbhead not head because there is nothing called ahead.
So if we do if not head that's always going to be true or false.
Now this is a situation let's rerun it.
Just double check if I do list equals new double length list.
Let's stop pop.
OK.
It doesn't let us pop anymore.
Now if we push one and then two and then three if I do a list of pop they give me three.
And the next is no.
And the previous says no.
It's totally isolated.
And if we look at the list and we look at the tail the tail has a previous but it has no next and we're
all good let's just make sure Fred you pop again.
We look at the list.
It's one item long list of pop.
One more time.
Give us a last item.
If we look at the list it's now empty.
Everything is working OK.
So that is pop again.
It's easier if you compare it to the code from the singly linked list.
We don't have to navigate the entire thing we don't have to have a loop we just start at the end and
work backwards.
The only annoying thing as with everything we do in the length list we have two linkages to account
for it but otherwise it's much faster and much easier.