Welcome back.
Next up we'll add shift to our doubly linked list.
So shift hopefully you know by now removes a node from the beginning.
No shame if you don't.
I always mix them up shift and shift and push well push and pop or shift and shift.
I always manage to think that shift is shift and shift his shift.
I should know that by now but shift removes the node from the beginning of a list and if we go back
to our singly linked list example to remove from the beginning it's pretty easy we just take the current
head we find its next and make that the new head.
And then we take this next in and make it all make it.
We set it to null and then we return that old head and we're done with it doubly linked list.
It's pretty much the same except we have an extra linkage.
If we remove from the beginning he paused.
This is all that we do is find the current head and then we find the next and we make that the new head.
Then we have to set this previous to no and this old head next to no.
So two connections that we have to sever and we return the old head.
So they are very similar.
Double dealing first we just have to also update the previous.
But there's no real benefit that we get from a double length post in this example.
It's just as easy or difficult or annoying or whatever it is in a single post.
It's the same and it doesn't do anything.
Except for previous.
OK so here's the pseudocode.
You can start by just checking if the length is zero or if there is no head return undefined just edge
case that we've been returning to.
Otherwise store the current head property in a variable.
I'll call mine old head just so that we have something to return at the end.
We need to store it.
We can't just remove it.
We have another special case.
If the length this one and you've removed the last item we need to set the head to be no and the tail
to be null otherwise update the head to be the next of the old head.
So that's what we did at the very beginning here.
So we have this is the old head.
We're going to move it.
The head reference to be old head next which it's just moving a little reference to point or like that.
So do that and then set the heads previous property to know meaning the new heads previous property
to No and then set the old heads next to no.
So that severing these bonds right here and then finally decrement the length and return the old head.
So give that a shot.
Like I said it's basically the same as doing it on a singly linked list.
Except you have to pay attention to previous.
So there's no real benefit for doubling length list.
In this scenario.
OK.
Next up I'll have a solution.