All right.
So let's get working on shift.
OK so the very first thing we'll do.
Aside from defining it it's adding that edge case.
Again we can check if the list is empty by checking if that head is no or if it doesn't exist or by
checking if the length is zero.
So I'll do length this time we did this dumbhead last time I'll do if this data length equals zero return
undefined.
All right.
Now the next thing we need to do is store the current head in a variable.
So I'll call it old head or shifted node or whatever you want to call it is right now the current head
of head but that's about to change.
First we have this edge case like this one and we remove the last item we need to make sure the head
and the tail are no.
So if this length is equal to one we're going to set this dud head equal to no.
I could've just copied this from above.
This tail equals nil.
OK so that's that edge case.
Now we need to update the head to be the next of the old.
Going back to this diagram.
I think I'll put in comments because it's getting an error if we have ninety nine and one hundred two
items in our list we have two connections to the next and the previous.
What we want to do.
We also have a reference to the head first.
This is the current head and I've stored it in a variable.
I'm moving the head to be 100.
So I'm just going to say this head equals old head next.
So ninety nine dot next meaning.
This is the new head.
Now we just need to sever these bonds so it doesn't matter which one we do first.
I can say this head meaning the new head dot previous equals no.
So that's going to remove that connection and then I can say old head dot next equals nil.
This is the old red dot next there's no old heard dot next no.
And now that removes this entirely they're not connected at all.
This is called the head now and this is it.
So I can return old head.
We have one more thing which is to decrement the length so this dot length minus minus and then return
old.
And that should be it.
So I just added in some code here.
So I don't have to type push over and over.
You have to watch me do that.
So we have our list that has three items.
Harry Ron and Hermione in there and let's do a list.
Shift.
So it looks like that works.
We got Harry back there next and previous is not totally isolated.
And if we look at the list now the head is rotten.
It has no previous.
That's correct.
It's at the beginning and the tail is her mind.
Let's do this double shift again.
OK we've got Ron on it's own.
And we look at the list.
It's one item now her mind the no next no previous.
It's just head and tail or her mind.
One more shift.
So we have a problem here which is that in this use case this use case scenario where length is one
we're sitting head and tail to be No.
We don't want to do any of this other stuff so I'm going to add an else here on these three lines and
close it up there.
And this is the same thing we did appear for pop we checked if there's one said the head and tail to
be no.
Otherwise do this.
So we had we set the head and tail to be no because there is nothing else to do.
And then we subtract one from length and returned the old head.
So just make sure it works rerun the code so I'll do that shift one time two times three times four
times.
And now the list is empty but we don't get an error if I keep trying to shift like we were doing or
where we were getting before.
OK.
So shift is pretty much the same or very similar to writing shift for a singly linked list.
We just have to pay attention to previous and next rather than only next.
Next up we're working on surprise surprise on shift.