All right.
Next up is an shift.
So upshift will add a note to the beginning of our doubly linked list.
So it's about the same as what we did with a singly we.
First we just have that extra connection.
So if we come over here and read you insert the beginning we'll add the number eighty five.
All that we do is find the current head.
We make a new node.
We point the new node at the current head.
Then we point the head of the current head at the new node and then we make this the head.
That's the final step and we're done.
So it's pretty short all that we have to look out for is if the list is empty.
And in that case we make the head and the tail the same thing.
All right.
So here's the pseudocode.
Create a new node with the value that's passed in.
If the length is 0 if it's empty set the head and the tail to be that new node.
Otherwise we'll set the previous property on the head to be the new node.
Then we set the next property on the new node to be the current head.
And then finally we move the head label.
We make the head the new node we shifted over or shifted over.
And then we increment the length and then return the list.
All right.
So just to reiterate that we take the current head.
Well first we make the new node.
Then we take the current head and we have a new node point next to the current head.
Then we have the current previous set to the new node.
There is that other arrow and then finally we say this isn't the head anymore.
This is the head.
And we're done.
We just have to look out for the edge case when it's empty the head and the tail are the same thing.
All right.