All right so let's implement an shift.
First thing we'll do is create a new node with the value passed in.
OK.
So we have an shift which takes a value and we just make new node equals new node with that value.
All right then what we're going to do is check if the list is empty.
If the length is zero or that's just one way of doing it if this link equals equals zero we can also
do this.
If not this knothead.
If that's the case we're going to set this damn head.
Equal equals new node and this dovetail equals new node.
OK.
Next up I have four equals.
There you go.
Otherwise set the previous property on the head of the list to be the new node.
So it will do.
Else the previous property on the heads of this head previous equals new node.
Then we need to go the other direction set the next property on the new node to be the current head
so new node next equals this head.
The current head not for long though because we're now going to update the head to be the new node this
head equals new node.
And then finally increment the length and return the list.
So that's going to be this stuff length plus plus return.
This we return the entire list.
Let's make sure it works.
So I'm going to execute the code and what we have here a list of three things in it.
Do lists dot on shift.
I think this is Harry Potter themed.
Let's do.
I don't know Hagrid.
OK.
If we look at list the head now is Hagrid.
Perfect.
And it should be pointing to Harry which it is.
And there's no previous perfect Let's just pop them all off or shift.
Let's do pop a couple of times.
OK.
Now we just have what we have is it's empty.
It's empty now.
Let's do this.
On shift and make sure it works
when it's empty and it looks like it does.
Yep.
Head and tail are both set properly.
OK.