Hey welcome back.
Next we'll implement.
Get on a doubly linked list so get.
Takes an index number and it returns the node at that index at that position.
And we could implement it the same way that we did with our singly linked list.
But there's actually a nice optimization that's a pretty significant change if we can make that we can
only do with a doubly linked list.
But just to recap or recall how we did it with a singly linked list.
Let's say we're looking for a get and we pass in five years let's say six.
So we're looking for the item an index of 6.
We started at the head.
That's our only option.
And then we had a counter variable.
We set it equal to zero.
This is index zero.
And then we just did in a loop.
Next we add one to counter.
It's now one next counters to the next counters.
Three four five.
Next counter is now six.
So we return this node ninety five and that works.
And if we wanted to do I don't know index of eight for example we still have to start at the beginning
and just go all the way down.
Now if we have 1000 items in the list and we're looking for the second to last item in a singly linked
list we have to go through all the items before it in a totally lengthy list.
We could do the same thing.
We could start at the beginning and work down to the tail or the element but we could also start at
the end and do Dopp previous previous previous.
So you could just do working from the end if you wanted to or you could only work in the beginning.
But the optimal solution is to work from one or the other depending on the index that is provided.
So if I did let's make a new list that's a little larger I think tennis a larger size can do if this
is the list.
We know that there's 10 items in here.
The highest index is nine.
If somebody is looking for the index of 7 if someone did this list get seven.
We could just start with the beginning and just add add add until we get to index 7.
But 7 is closer to the end of the list.
So we could and we should start at the end and work backwards.
So we know this is index of nine.
It's one of the highest index is one less than the length.
So we can start at 9 and work back to 8 back to 7.
So that's what we're going to do.
We're going to write code that checks is the index that's provided closer to 0 or closer to the last
index the length minus 1 and that would make a very significant difference if we're talking about I
don't know a million items in the list and we're looking for the $900 thousand.
Item for example.
No need to start at the very beginning.
So here's the pseudo code.
First thing we need to do is just check if it's a valid index.
So if it's negative or greater or equal to the length return.
No.
Remember it can't be equal to the length.
If there's 10 items there's nothing in index 10 the highest is nine.
Otherwise we're now going to check if the index is less than or equal to half the length of the list.
If that's the case we're going to start from the beginning and move to the right.
Next up next until we find the correct note.
Otherwise that means that the index is greater than the half of the length of the length of the list
meaning that it's closer to the right side or closer to the tail.
So we'll start here.
And instead of adding one each time we do it next we will subtract one from a counter every time we
do a previous.
So our counter is going to start as the last index.
Our position will be in this case 9 because there's 10 items 10 months one gives us 9 or if we had five
items in the list we would start at index 4 and subtract one each time we did.
Previous.
So hopefully this makes sense this idea.
All you have to do take the length divide by two and compare the index to that result and it's up to
you if you're looking for the exact middle of the list the middle index if you would rather group that
in with the head or with the two doesn't matter.
OK so give that a shot.
One more time.
Here is the pseudo code.
Return the node once it's founded and specify that.
And that's pretty much it.
So try tried out in the next video I'll have a solution.