All right let's implement it.
So first things first let's define get except an index and we're going to check for edge case or the
error.
If if index is negative not good.
We can't find that or index is greater than or equal to this length.
So we can't have it be out of bounds on either side.
And again we can't have it equal to the length because the highest index just like an array is always
one less than the length.
If that's the case return and what I say no undefined false it doesn't really matter to me.
Just returned something bad to the negative.
OK.
Otherwise what we need to do now is let's just start by implementing the left part.
So we start at the head just like we did with single wheeling first and just do.
Next up next we're going to have to do that at some point.
So let's just start there.
So I'll make a variable called Count and started at zero and then I'm going to make another variable
called Current and set that to be the head.
OK.
And then I'm just going to do while count is not equal to indexed.
So we're going to start with counting zero and we're going to add 1.
What we're going to do current equals current up next to traverse the list.
Hopefully this sort of approach is review at this point and then we'll add one to count count plus plus.
So we start to say we're looking for index of to count starts at zero current is head.
And this started then we check his count equal to index it's not so current now is equal to the head
next.
And we add one to count and we keep going until we hit whatever is an index to her mind.
And then once we found that item we just need to return current at the end.
So this is an optimized version.
Well let's just make sure it works.
So if I have any errors in this make this a little bit larger.
Let's push on a couple of other things.
Let's just push on last and then I'll do actually last.
OK so if we look at list it has five things I shouldn't be able to do do get of negative 1 or of 10
or even five.
But if I did get of say three index of three it gives me last if I do index of four gives me actually
last index of zero.
Harry one is ran into is her my any.
Once I get I have to yell at my cat.
They're destroying my furniture.
OK.
So that's great.
That works.
We're going to use a lot of this logic.
But now we also want to do the same thing.
We want to start at the end and work towards the middle and we're going to do it based off of where
the index is in that list.
How high or low that indexes will go back to the pseudo code now and check if the index is less than
or equal to half the length of the list.
So we're going to do this approach right here.
If index.
So I'm going to write this out.
If index is less than or equal to the equals part doesn't.
You could do it on the other one.
Whichever way you'd prefer to do it doesn't matter.
But I'm going to say if the index is less than or equal to this length divide by two.
If that's the case we're going to do all of this and we'll refactor this in a bit.
There's going to be a little duplication otherwise that means we're going to start at the end of the
list.
So we're going to start with a count variable equal to this length minus one.
For example if our list looks like this our length is 10.
Our last item is index of nine so we're going to start with count at nine and subtract one each time.
So we're actually going to write the same sort of loop.
We're just going to do what I need to do.
Current as well var current equals this tale.
We're starting at the end.
Well counting is not equal to index.
What are we going to do.
We're going to say current equals current dot previous.
We're going to step backwards and then we're going to do count minus minus subtract one from Count and
then at the end return current.
Ok ok I'm back.
So let's add a little test.
Let's just do a counted out log to say working from beginning.
I don't I hate typing the word beginning say working from start and then the else will do working from
end and let's see which one runs and then we'll read reduce some of the duplication.
OK.
So we have a list that has three things in it.
Let's push in 300 400 500 and 600.
OK.
So length is seven.
If I do it this does get zero.
It says working from start to a list get of let's say 5 it does working from end.
And if I do with a six that's our last thing in there right.
There's no index of seven right.
So it looks like it's working.
It says that it's working from and we could you know you could create a variable to count how many times
the loop actually runs.
If you wanted to really test it out but we can just trust that this works.
We've added a little bit of logic to check if we're closer to the beginning of the end.
And that changes where we're working from now a tiny change.
First of all we can return current afterwards.
So we don't need to duplicate that.
So let's move that outside of the conditional and just put it afterwards it happens for either one.
Either one of you say that we also have.
See you can get rid of those logs.
Now we have count and current are both being declared.
This is fine.
I would probably do this personally to our count and current and then just update them but it doesn't
really matter.
Honestly we still have to have these lines that are duplicated here.
But overall I'm happy with how this looks how it's working.
If you have a better refactor absolutely there are other ways of doing this or freeriding this where
we don't have so much.
This logic is very very similar except for the actual operation that we're doing inside of there but
this loop is the same.
Right we're sitting current We're sitting count.
There are ways slightly more complicated of Slimming this down but this is fine.
Absolutely it works.
Let's just verify it one more time that it works.
So we've got our list.
Let's do this don't get negative one shouldn't work.
Let's do this.
I get 0.
It works 1 2.
No I didn't type a number and then three shouldn't work.
Looks good.
It's working.
I think that's all that there is.