All right.
Next up we have set on our doubly linked list so set takes an index like get.
But it also takes in a piece of data or a value to update the node at that index with.
So we can say set the item at index 3 to now be hallelujah.
So if you implement it get from the last video set.
It's really really easy because we don't have to do any of the logic to find the node that's what does
it we can call get and all we have to do is actually update the node.
So the pseudo code is pretty short.
Create a variable which is the result of the get method at the index that was passed to the function.
So we don't actually even have to check if the index is valid or invalid because we did that in get
get started checking if the index is negative or greater than or equal to the length.
So we just use get pass in the index and what ever comes back if it returns a valid node set the value
of that node to be the value that was passed in to set and return true.
Otherwise just return false.
So you can do this one in just a couple of lines.
It's four or five lines.
It's just the same as what we did is I think it's identical actually to what we did with a singly length
list.
So if you want to practice rewrite it put it super short.
All right solution coming up.