Welcome back.
Let's right set.
So we're going to go below.
Get in at our set which takes an index and a new value and the first thing we do is just call get with
that index.
So we'll do this get passed and that index and save it to a variable let's call it found Noad or no
call that everyone.
I'm going to go with found a..
And then we're just going to check if found Noad or we could do it the other way and say if not found
Noad.
So if there was a found node we could also be more specific and check if it's not.
No it's probably better.
So if found notice not equal to nil we're going to take a found Noad dot Vau equals the new valve that
comes in and then we return to otherwise return false.
And we don't need to do an else we can just return false check our suit or pseudo code or anything else.
I think that was it.
And let's test it out.
All right.
So we have our list and it has three items.
Harry Ron and Hermione let's just test it out first.
Doing this does set a negative one negative for 100 or 10 apparently because I didn't type in next year.
And just make sure it doesn't work OK.
It's false.
Our list is unchanged.
Same thing if we tried to do with index of 10.
Same thing unchanged.
Now let's try and set let's say the first item instead of harry.
That's the all caps.
Harry you get true.
And if we look at the list it's still three items but the first notice Harry and everything looks good.
Otherwise it's still pointing to Ron which is still pointing to Hermione which is pointing to nothing.
Let's try and update her mind each index of two and we'll do all caps again.
And if you look at a list or look at the tail it's all caps.
Cool.
So that's working.
That's all there is to set nice and easy if we write get that is without get it's a pain but we have
to get.
So it's nice and short.