All right.
Welcome back.
Next we're going to implement insert on a doubly linked list.
So this works in a very similar way to how it does in a single length list.
You pass in an index position and a value.
And it creates a new node with that value and adds it at that position to the length list.
The main difference is that we can optimize it rather than starting at the beginning and always going.
Next up next up next we can also start at the end and go up previous and it's up to our code to decide
which is more appropriate depending on what the index is.
But we don't really have to worry about that because we already wrote a get method so we can use the
get method to retrieve the appropriate place to insert it and get method already has the logic to check
you know length divide by two is the index less than if so start from the head and move towards the
middle.
Or is the index greater than half of the half of the length.
If that's the case start from the tail and move towards the middle.
Anyway what we want to do the same inserting an index of four the the number 77.
Oh I can't do that because our list is 10 things.
OK let's make a new list that has 9 items.
Do this one more time.
Insert index of six.
Sure.
Sixty five.
All right.
So we traverse the list until we find the item right before what we're going to insert.
So we found it.
And now the annoying part about double length list is that we have a lot of connections to make.
So we need to remove this connection both connections there.
And instead we need to have sixty six point sixty five sixty five points back at 66.
Then we have twelve point sixty five previous and sixty five.
Next point at 12.
So if we step through that and see all these lines that we're drawing and we're done.
So there are four different little patches that we have to make.
So here's a pseudo code.
First we're going to check if it's a valid index just like before.
If the index is too small or if it's negative or is greater than or equal to the length return false
if the index is ZERO use unshipped we already wrote that if the index is the same as the length meaning.
So if we have 8 items the length is 8.
If the insert is at 8 that's actually valid remember because even though it's currently not a valid
index it's OK for us to insert at the end which would make it a valid index.
So if that's the case call push or otherwise use our Get method to access the item right before where
we're trying to insert.
So index minus one.
And then you need to do all the patching the next and previous properties on the correct nodes to link
everything together.
Incremental length by one and return TRUE TO tried out in the next video will have a solution.