All right so let's write our Insearch solution for a doubly linked list.
So I'll define insert which takes an index and a value and the first thing we'll do is check if the
index is negative.
So if it's less than zero or if the index is greater than the length then will return false or whatever
value you want to return to indicate that it doesn't work.
Then we had our special case if index exactly zero.
What we want to do.
We're going to return this dot not push this and shift to the beginning.
And if index is exactly equal to the stop length that means we're adding to the very end.
We're going to do ever turn this dot push though.
OK.
And let's just test that part out for now.
Just make sure we didn't miss anything up.
So we have our list.
If i do list that inserts index of.
First so because the list is our new Head correct it looks like it's correct and it's pointing to.
Yep.
Let's try the same thing our length this force for try and do list at insert at 4 and but say I do last
is what I try and insert it looks like it works.
If you look at our table it's set to last.
OK.
And also if we tried to do something invalid like 40 shouldn't work we should get false.
And we do.
OK.
So otherwise the rest of our logic was use the get method to access the index minus one.
So we can do which we call this new found note again equals this don't get in we're going to do index
minus 1 because from trying to insert right here I need to first find the item before it.
So that's what we're doing right now.
So we're finding that one before we also need to make the new node so we can call new node or inserted
node equals new node and pass in the value just like that.
Now all we have to do is patch everything correctly and to make it a little easier.
I'm going to make another variable.
So this is called Found node.
I think I might actually relabel this to previous node and then I'm going to have let's do those called
Before I like that more and then I'm going to have after node equals before node next.
So I just have two references now so far a list looks like I don't know.
A B C D E F.
And if we're trying to insert an index of 3 0 1 to 3 what we did is we found before node is right here
and then I said after Node 2 before node next which is right here.
So I now have a reference to here in reference to here and it's just going to make it a little cleaner
or easier to understand what's happening.
So we want to set the before node dot next to be our new node.
So before node next equals new node then we want to set new node previous.
So we just inserted something right here and say we're inserting hello we did this connection.
Now we need to go from hello back to before node so new no previous equals before node.
Now it needs to go.
Connect this to the after node.
So we'll do new node dot next equals after node after node previous equals new node.
It's kind of a pain but I prefer to make a separate variable to do this.
You don't have to.
You could just right before node next instead of after node.
It's just I don't like chaining that together and having your next stop previous.
And other than that what else do you need to do this at length goes up by 1 and will return TRUE AT
THE END.
Let's test it out see if it works.
So we have our list right now has three things.
If I try and insert this insert at index of 1 we're going with Harry Potter's let's do Tunks under-rated
character and let's look at the list.
So it's now four things.
That's correct.
The head should still be hairy but the head now points to Tunks and Tunks has a next reference and a
previous.
If we look at the previous It said to Harry so that's correct.
And if we look at the next set to run and if we look at Ron and we look at its previous set to Tunks.
So everything is connected correctly which is probably the most annoying part of verifying or making
sure something works in a doubly linked list is making sure that you have all the connections because
you need to make sure you have the next and the previous.
For every single thing that you're changing a couple of small changes.
First of all if we might want everything to return true or false right now everything does unless we
are on shifting or pushing these two scenarios.
This is the same thing in our singly linked list example just to refresh your memory.
If i do list this dot insert anywhere in the middle it returns True.
But if I do it at the beginning it returns to the node or at the end.
For that matter at least it returns true.
What is the last index.
6.
Now there we go.
It's giving me the node.
So if I want to coerce it to a boolean we can do the same thing we did the double bang bang bang which
is now going to turn it into a billion.
Another thing I'll do a little return here just to separate out these edge cases in our conditionals.
I'll also add in I would say opinion I guess but I kind of like separating out a variable declarations
and then I'm actually going to put these on the same line because they're paired together.
We're swopped we're adding the before no next equal to a new node and new no previous equals 4 node.
So I like to group those together to show that they are sort of doing you know one set a pair of connections
at a time.
Same thing here.
Definitely not necessary to do that at all.
But I like that change.
And now just double check everything still works in sort of the beginning that works.
Insert in the middle that works and insert at the end.
Now it was at the end.
What is the last thing.
No that was not the end.
If I answered at six it should work.
Now that the length is seven so if answered at 8 it shouldn't work.
OK.
So that's answer.