All right next we have for move for a doubly linked list.
So remove just takes in an index or position.
And we're going to remove the item at that position just like before we can take advantage of get me
restart this here we can take advantage of get which we already built in the functionality to check
if something is closer to the head or the tail.
So we don't have to write the logic to work from the from the end or from the beginning.
We can take advantage of get but we still want that logic to be running because if we have a million
items in here and we're trying to remove the second to last item or the fifth to last item it makes
no sense to start at the beginning and go NEXT NEXT NEXT NEXT.
All the way almost a million items down when we could start at the end and just go.
Previous previous or however many times.
So that's what we're going to do here.
But of course we're not going to have to write most of the logic although we really have to do is first
check if the index is invalid if it's less than zero or greater than or equal to the length return undefined
or some false value.
If the index is zero shift just take advantage of shift remove from the beginning.
If the index is the same as the length minus one or if it's equal to the length minus one I don't know
why I said it is the same as just use pop.
Otherwise use the get method to retrieve the item to be removed so that retrieves the item then you
have to update the next and previous properties to remove it correctly.
We have to patch the hole.
And then what I like to do is set the next and previous on the found note itself on the thing that you're
removing.
Just wipe those out so that when you return it it's just the value and next and previous on the returned
item are no.
And then subtract one from the length and returned return the removed node.
So for example if we remove something from the middle let's say index of four we find it first using
get.
OK we found it.
So we have to patch the thing before it and the thing after it to connections and then we remove the
connections from here from the deleted item and then we return the deleted item.
OK.
So give this one a shot remove take advantage of the get method that we already wrote and you solution
coming up.