All right let's implement remove on our doubly linked list.
We're almost there.
So we need to specify the index that we're removing at.
And we first check if that index is invalid.
I'm actually just going to copy this from insert.
So if index is less than zero or if it's greater then except this time or equal to the length because
we unlike insert where we could insert right at the very very end if there's eight items we can insert
it index 8.
If we're removing the length is 8 items there's nothing at index 8.
So we need to check if it's greater than or equal to return false or undefined.
Otherwise our next thing is to check if it's at the very beginning.
So for trying to remove from the very very beginning let's just do a return this dot shift which should
remove the thing at the very beginning.
If we're trying to remove at the end which we could check if the index is equal to the length minus
one we're going to turn this pop and let's just make sure that that works in our code.
Let's do this list dot remove zero and they give me the first node if we look at the list.
It's only 2 things.
So I could do a remove at index of one which now is the last index and we get her my any.
And we look at the list.
It's only one thing.
So if I try and do it let's remove one it's invalid.
If I do zero it works.
And our list is empty now.
Looks good.
Now the rest of our logic we're going to use the get method to retrieve the item to be removed.
So let's do that now.
We'll make a variable called removed node equals.
This gets and just pass in the index.
So that gives us the thing that we're removing.
Now we just need to remove it by setting the next and previous properties to the correct things.
So I'm going to set the the note before it.
So here let's go do a b c d e f again if we're trying to remove this node This is removed node.
We need to set this nodes next to be this nodes dot next.
So we leapfrog over it which now sets B's next to B D.
So that removed node previous gives us the next the next of B should be equal to removed node next.
Now I don't really like doing this but previous doesn't act so we could also do what we did earlier
and make a before node in an afternoon.
But I'm going to start with this.
So that gets 1 connection from B to D.
Now we need to go from D to be so removed node dot next dot previous equals removed node previous so
removed node next the DOB previous is now going to point to remove node previous which is B.
I know it's kind of crazy.
Otherwise all that may have left is to set next and previous to no on the found node.
So that's just cleaning up some loose ends so removed node out next equals no removed node previous
equals no.
Then we subtract 1 from the length and then we just return removed node.
Let's see if it works.
I'm going to test it out.
We have our list let's do list.
Remove index of 1 which is wrong.
So our list should now have hairy connected to my any.
So the head is hairy and it's next is her mind.
And if we look at her my previous is hairy and there is no next because it's the tail.
If we try to do this don't remove an invalid index negative for one we get undefined or 100 or 10 undefined.
Let's do a couple of pushes.
OK I pushed in a couple of values LLNL by and ha ha ha.
So if we look at our list now it's five items.
If I try and remove from the very end I do list out remove five.
It doesn't work but if I do start four it works and notice that what we get back has no next and no
no.
That's correct.
We don't want it to have the lingering references so we get list.
Let's look at the tail now.
Which is by next is correct it should be known at the end and previous is pointing to some other node
which is what I'm saying by.
OK.
This all looks good.
Let's just remove from the beginning.
Let's do just remove a couple of times.
How many things are last left.
OK.
What should be done now right.
Totally empty.
Everything looked good.
You could clean this up a bit and it's up to you if you think this is cleaner but you could do var before
node equals removed Snoad previous.
The bar after node equals removed no debt next.
And then we could do the same thing that we had before so we just said before Noad next equals after
Noad and then say after Noad previous equals before Noad.
If you don't like this syntax here and if we refresh it I run the code again.
It should still work just fine.
We have our list Nope list but the t.
If we do list out remove an index of 1 and we look at the list should be correctly patched.
So we have Hary which is pointing next to her mind and her mind he is pointing previous to Harry.
So up to you which you prefer.
This is a little more verbose but then you have this nice clean easy to understand syntax here what
you're actually doing versus before is a little longer and you have this removed.
No everything is in reference to removed node.
Honestly I don't know which one I prefer for insert.
When we had to change more properties I like doing this.
Removed either one.
I think I'll leave both in here and just leave it commented out.
OK so let's remove.