All right.
Welcome back.
Last video on doubly linked lists but I'd like to do here is just run down and recap the Big O notation
for the common operations insertion removal.
Searching and access.
Same thing that we did for singly linked lists and then a lot of cases it's very similar.
But there's a couple of exceptions.
So insertion is constant time which is the same.
It's what it was for singly linked first.
That's really where length lists Excel.
Inserting data is very very easy.
Does it matter where.
It's very easy.
It doesn't matter how long the list is unlike an array removal.
For a doubly linked list is always constant which is not the case for a singly linked list.
Remember that if we are removing from the end of a singly linked list we have to iterate over the entire
thing until we get to the second to last item to make that the new tail on a doubly length list.
It's constant time.
It doesn't matter if you're at the millionth item.
You don't have to traverse the entire list to get to the nine hundred ninety nine thousand nine hundred
ninety nine node.
You just do previous snow removal.
It's faster or it can be at least.
Searching is still alive and but I have a note down here because the way we implemented searching is
optimized where we either start in the left side from the head and move towards the middle or we start
on the right side from the tail and move towards the middle.
Depending on what the indexes.
If it's closer to the end or to the beginning.
But even though that is 0 of and divided by two that still simplifies to 0 of an overall as and grows
it still insignificant for dividing it by 2.
When we talk about things like squared or constant time the differences are so large that dividing by
two doesn't matter so we simplify it to 0.
But keep in mind it is faster still and it's worth knowing that because we use that divide and conquer
approach where we either start at the beginning or the end and move towards the middle.
All right so that's a big O Really what it comes down to is that doubly linked lists are basically the
same except there's an extra pointer pointing to the previous node.
So we have two connections and that does make certain things much easier.
For example if we didn't talk about this really in this big video.
But if you need to start at the end and work backwards.
Often if you need to access your data in a reverse manner let's say that you're representing your browser
history.
This is actually often done with a doubly linked list because every page that you're on has a next Or
a preview and the previous Actually both are set.
So you know if I hit back which I won't do.
Who knows what's what I was looking at before this but if I hit back.
There's a web page and if I was on that web page I could hit forward or back.
That is a doubly linked list.
And a double link for us allows us to easily move backwards using daat previous or forwards using.
Next a singly linked list would not work.
Also double linked lists are better for finding things because it can be done in half the time.
However that extra pointer comes at a cost because it does take up more memory.
So if that's something you're worried about or you want to keep in mind even if you don't care it's
just something you should know.
If you need to talk about the length first.
If it comes up in an interview that's really the key distinction.
So double the linked list can be much better in certain ways and they're certainly easier to navigate
but it comes at a cost of more memory.
All right.
So I said this at the last video of the last section that the most recent recap for singling for lists.
This is very heavy stuff.
There's a lot here.
It's a lot to digest.
It's also not the most captivating content potentially for a lot of people in my experience teaching
this in person.
Some students love the problem solving aspects they didn't care that it wasn't really building any sort
of final product.
We're not making a game or an app or a Web site.
Some people love that or didn't care.
Other people though had a really hard time staying motivated.
So I said this in the last video in the last section.
Do whatever makes you happy.
If you're going to come back to the next section I wouldn't just add these all together and try and
do some power session.
Cram all of this into a night or two.
I would spread this out a lot.
Go pet a dog or cat or llama or get a foot rub.
If you're if you can do that.
Make some coffee.
Do whatever you need to do.
All right.
That is doubly linked lists were done with singly linked lists and double which means we are done with
little bursts.
Hopefully by now you feel pretty comfortable with at the very least explaining what they are and how
they compare to each other and also to array's.