All right.
So we talked about objectives.
We did a little story with Martin and the dragon.
Now let's actually get a formal definition of what recursion is and secondly let's talk about why you
should care.
I did a little bit of well I wasn't trying to scare anyone but I did a little bit of talking at the
beginning about how recursion can be tricky.
So let's talk about why it's worth it why you should care and why you should push through it.
If you do have a hard time getting it right away.
But first definition what is recursion.
It's just a process that calls itself.
And in our case in everything we do in javascript or in code when we say recursion we're referring to
a function that calls itself.
So we've seen many a function that calls other functions that's very very common.
We can have a function called laugh and inside of it we would call cancel out log.
Potentially that's a function call instead of a function.
What's different about recursive functions is they call them self.
So our life function inside would call laugh and you can imagine first of all that and that might make
your head hurt already.
But then imagine that it's happening over and over and over again.
And there has to be some endpoint or if we go back to this slide here.
Here we have imagine that we have a function called check for odd.
We would call it here and then in check for odd it would call itself again on a smaller list and then
that would call check for odds over and over and over again there has to be an endpoint of course or
else we just keep going like an infinite loop.
But it's slightly different than an infinite loop.
But we'll get there.
So let's leave it at that.
It's a function that calls itself.
Now why should you care.
Why do you need to know this.
There's a bunch of reasons.
First of all it's everywhere.
It's used all the time.
We're going to use it a lot in the course for a lot of the solutions we write later on.
But even before that if you've been writing javascript you've probably been using recursive function
without knowing things like J sound parser based on that string of phi if you've ever made an AJAX call
and gotten Jaison back and turned that into javascript then you may have called a recursive function.
Now Jason Jason that string of phi are up to the javascript engine to implement.
So Mozilla has their own.
What's it called Rhino.
I think their own implementation.
Where are they right Jason and parse how they want to and it doesn't have to be written recursively
but it often is.
So the point that I want to make is not that it's guaranteed that you've called a recursive function
but that Jason that parse is often written recursively.
And actually I have the source code open for Rhyno and this is here.
So this is the engine that Mozilla uses and it is it's written in Java.
So don't worry about the syntax.
But if we look it's not as simple as Jaisalmer up parts calling JS that parse immediately instead.
There is a function called Read value.
This method here and read value calls things like read object.
So let's just focus on those two read value.
You call that it calls read object will we look at read object in the middle of read object if we scroll
down a bit it calls read value again.
So then read value is called and that could call read object and we end up with this cycle where even
the spread across two different methods.
They are calling each other so read value is calling read object which is calling read value which calls
read object and it's a cycle that goes over and over and over.
So that's an example of recursion.
But let me show you a simpler implementation.
Here's a simpler implementation written in Javascript.
So this is not actually what's used in any of the browsers because browsers aren't written Javascript
isn't written in Javascript.
But here's an implementation to show what it would look like.
So I'm going to take a look.
There's this method called a walk which is here's something up here so it's called Walk and instead
of walk it's calling walk.
I don't know if you can see that oh no i lost it.
There we are.
So walk is called instead of walk it calls itself over and over.
I'm getting tired of saying the word walk.
It starts to sound very bizarre when I repeat it that much.
But what it's doing if you think of a on a string.
It's all nested when it says walk.
It's going to move down to the next line or to the next thing to parse over and over and over until
it hits the end.
OK so a bit of a tangent but maybe somewhat interesting that there are two examples Jason to parse that
string ify document get element by ID.
And DOM traversal algorithms so remember that the Dahmus is tree structure where we have all these nested
things.
Could be a hundred layers nested full of you know a div instead of a div instead of a div.
And if we're trying to search through all of them one popular approach is to write code that does it
recursively object traversal which is just like traversing Jaison.
Now aside from these functions like Jason to parse and get element by id query selector things that
we've used before probably we're also going to be writing a lot of our own recursive functions later
on.
So when we write our own data structures when we create trees or graphs for example when we want to
traverse them we want to search for something across them.
Often the solutions involve recursion.
Now remember you don't have to do anything recursively but it's a nice.
Sometimes it's easier let's put it that way.
It's cleaner and simpler to understand rather than doing it without recursion and it just got ahead
of my bullet point here.
And sometimes a cleaner alternative to iteration.
So we'll see some examples.
We're going to write a couple of functions both ways with and without recursion.
And I think we'll make it a little clearer that sometimes it's nicer.
So why you should care.
1 it's everywhere.
You've been using it.
That's that doesn't really matter I guess because it doesn't impact how you use things like Jason that
parse but it really is important once you get into these more advanced data structures.
And we're writing our own parts functions on our own get element by id traversing a tree for example.
All right.
So we leave this video off here.