You'll get.
So we're almost to the point where we're kind of write our own recursive functions.
But first we have to talk about one important thing which is what happens behind the scenes when functions
are called in javascript.
If a recursive function is calling itself over and over and over again what happens behind the scenes.
And this is important for us to understand in order to write effective recursive code that doesn't break.
So in almost all programming languages there is some data structure behind the scenes that's managing
function calls functions when they're invoked often are waiting on other functions to return.
There's there's a special order that happens right functions don't just happen randomly like if you
have a function called first and then instead of that function it calls a second function.
You need them to go in the correct order.
And so there's a thing a data structure in charge of that in javascript called the call stack.
So you can think of it as a stack of papers or something.
It's actually a data structure called a stack that we'll learn about later.
You might have heard of stacks and Qs before but all that we're going to say for now is that when a
function is invoked it's placed on the top of the call stack.
So just like we have a stack of papers on our desk the first the newest one that we put on goes on top
and then when javascript's sees the return key word or when a function and there's no more code to run
the compiler will remove the top item from the stack.
So the idea of a stack.
The reason I'm saying a stack of papers on a desk is that you put something on top when you remove something
you also remove from the top you don't remove from the bottom of a stack of papers.
You take whatever's on top.
So that's the idea of the call stack.
What I'm going to show you now is what it looks like in the chrome dev tools.
When we have a couple of function calls what the stack actually looks like how it reflects those functions.
Ok so I have a snippet here that I've made it's very silly but it has four different functions.
There's a function called Wake Up And wakeup calls take a shower eat breakfast and then it prints at
the very end when everything's done ok ready to go to work.
So wake up is invoked down here and then wake up calls take a shower and take shower is simple just
returned showering.
Then we have eat breakfast and eat breakfast is called and it's a little more complicated because it
sets a variable meal equal to cook food which is another function.
So cook food is going to then be called and that returns.
Well there's a list of items and it picks one at random.
So it's going to pick one of these three things.
That's what this code does and just return it.
So cook food might return eggs then eat breakfast was waiting on that meal is now eggs it returns.
Eating eggs and then wake up was waiting on that.
And it's because of the breakfast it was that was holding things up.
Then we move on finally to costa adult vogue.
OK.
Ready to go to work.
So I'm going to show you I'm going to step through this one at a time.
One function call at a time.
And the way I'm going to do that over here I have this call stack window open and I'm going to add a
breakpoint here.
So as I hit this little button to run it or command enter on a Mac what's going to happen is that over
here we'll see things added to the call stack.
So I just hit command enter and I'm going to step through it with this this little thing here this arrow.
So first thing that happens is that we get to wake up and you can see Wake up is on the call stack.
Now it's the first piece of paper put down.
But wake up isn't resolved it hasn't returned something it's not done.
In fact the very first thing it does is called Take shower.
So take a shower is added onto the call stack so now half the stack with two function calls on it.
So take a shower.
It's simple.
Just returned showering and you actually see that right here.
So we're on take shower now return value is showering and then it's removed from the call stack because
it returned a value.
Then we move on back to wake up the next part of wake up.
We already did this.
Now it's on to eat breakfast.
So breakfast is added to the top of the stack and you can see if breakfast isn't as simple.
Eat breakfast is going to call cook food and cook food is added to the top of the stack.
So now we have wake up which is still waiting for the breakfast.
Eat breakfast is waiting on cook food.
So cook food is first it makes this array of items you can see that in the local scope items is created
now.
Next line is going to pick a random item and return it which is what happened to be returned.
Protein shake.
So now cook food is done because it returned and we return back to her I shouldn't say return.
We go back to eat breakfast which was waiting on cook food.
So now you can see an eat breakfast meal in the local scope is equal to protein shake.
So we're going to return.
Eating meal your turn eating protein shake it returns.
Which means that eat breakfast next is removed from the stack it's done.
And finally we go back to wake up which has been waiting patiently this whole time and we are able to
cancel that log.
OK ready to go to work.
You'll see a pier down here.
And now we're done with Wake up and we finish now.
We're at the end.
There we go.
So there's a lot going on there.
But the idea behind it is that as functions are invoked they're added to the top of the stack and then
they are popped off one at a time from the top as well.
So the reason that we're going over this first hope with all was clear what was what's happening there
these dev tools are useful if you've never seen the call stack tool over here it's very nice to be able
to step through and understand the order things are happening in and what's waiting on what.
But the reason I'm showing it to you now when we're discussing recursion is that when we're writing
recursive functions we're going to be working with the call stack a lot.
So you may be you're probably used to functions being pushed on the stack and popped off right when
they're done.
But with recursive functions it's different.
They keep pushing new functions over and over and over onto the call stack.
In fact the same function over and over and over and it's waiting to be called.
So if we take this idea of some parts calling some parts and it keeps calling itself over and over and
over at the call stack is going to look like data on the up parts and up parts based on the parts that
it has to end somewhere.
And that's what we're going to talk about in the next video when we actually write our first bit of
recursive code is where it ends.
We've established that the recursive function calls itself.
But how do we know when it stops.
Because otherwise it's in the call stack just going to continue to go forever.
And we'll talk about that as well.
So hopefully this made it a little bit clearer.
But the call stack is it's the thing behind the scenes in javascript that it's a stack data structure
which all that means is that things are added to the top and remove first from the top and functions
when they're invoked are added to this structure.
So next up we're finally going to write some recursive code.