All right we'll come back.
So in this video we're finally going to write our first recursive function.
So big moment.
And the first thing we should do is just talk about the game plan for any recursive function.
There's two things that must be present.
So the idea is that we're invoking the same function over and over having one function call itself recursively.
But there has to be a stopping point and that's the second piece which is called the base case.
So the base case is where the recursion stops.
There has to be an end of the line.
It doesn't just continue to call itself over and over and over and over forever.
That would be a huge problem just like a wild pass to have some place to stop.
Otherwise it just goes forever and makes your computer angry.
So if we go back to this example with Martin and the dragon every time let's say that this is this represents
a single function call let's call it check for odd numbers and it's called over and over on a smaller
piece of data each time.
But that doesn't just go forever.
There's a clear stopping point.
The code if we were to write this and we can do it in a bit the code would basically have a conditional
to check is the list empty is an empty array for numbers.
If that's the case then stop.
So the two essential parts of any recursive function the base case that has to be there that's the end
of the line.
That's where the recursion stops and then different input.
I can't really think of a good name for this but basically the recursive call you're going to call the
same function over and over but each time you want to call it with a different piece of data you don't
want to just use the same list of numbers and check for the first item in that list to see if it's odd
over and over and over because you would never get anywhere what you would want to do.
And that's with that Martin the dragging solution.
We change the list.
We basically chop off one number at the beginning and then pass the list through again and try to do
the same thing until we hit an empty list.
So there's the different input and then there's the base case.
So let's take a look at a real example now.
Our first simple recursive function it's called Countdown.
It doesn't do much to just print numbers starting from whatever number we pass in it.
Let's say 5 it will print 5 4 3 2 1 and then all done.
So I have it in a snippet here.
If I execute this you'll see the output is 5 4 3 2 1.
All done.
So we could easily write this without recursion.
Do iterative fully.
I went ahead and typed it up.
I could do something like this to make a comment that one out function count down takes a number would
just loop start I at the number like 5 while I.
Is greater than zero.
Subtract one from each time and let's verify that it works.
Let me clear this just so we can double check there we go.
So we go five four three two one.
All done.
OK.
So I just wanted to show that you can easily do this without recursion and that's not the point.
This is something that we all are familiar with just looping and printing numbers.
But to do it recursively is a bit different.
So let's walk through how it works.
When I call count down let's do something simpler let's do three count down with three.
Well let's just walk through line by line.
Is number less than or equal to zero.
No it's three.
So none of this happens.
So all we do is print three.
Then we subtract one from them and then we Cocq count down with none which is now 2.
So we print 3 so we can if we step through basically print 3 then the next line is now 2.
So we call count down with two.
So then let's start over is to less than or equal to zero.
No.
So we skip this.
We constantly log nothing.
So that's going to be print to again we subtract one from now I'm turning it into one and we call count
down with one
then start over a count down of 1.
If Nahm is less than or equal to zero that's still false council about LAGNADO.
So then we print one.
I cannot spell print.
Print 1.
And then countdown of 1 or excuse me content of zero because we subtract 1 from them giving us zero.
Start over.
Count down of zero.
Now this is our base case.
This is the endpoint.
Otherwise if we didn't have this we'd keep going into negative numbers and just forever.
So what does our base case is less than or equal to zero.
Yes.
Now it is.
Number is zero.
So numbers less than or equal to zero.
So we cancel that log all done.
And then this is important we return and we're not returning anything.
We have to have this here because if we didn't if we just printed all done then we'd keep going right
to that LOEG zero.
Now mind minus minus would be numbers negative 1 and be called Count down with negative 1.
So we have to have this return in order to stop it or I guess if we wanted to we could wrap this all
in and else.
So hopefully that's clear what happens.
We just add our final print all done here.
So you can see when we call it with three.
It calls itself count down with two calls and self-content of one with zero.
And then we hit the base case and we stop.