OK.
So hopefully you survive that first recursive function example.
Now we're moving on to our second example.
So this is what it looks like.
It's called Some range and first try and identify two pieces can you identify the base case.
So a key hint for that.
There's only two lines here but a base case almost always involves a conditional to check for something
and then it returns something that's the end it's the bottom of the well you hit the the water hit the
rock.
I don't know that's a terrible way of putting it.
There's an endpoint.
Then there's the different input which is still not happy with that term but there's the recursive call
which we're calling with a smaller piece each time.
So in the last video we were subtracting one from knowm and calling count down again NUMP keeps shrinking
towards eventually the base case here we're doing the same thing.
So the base case to start is this line.
If numbers equal to 1 return 1 and that makes sense.
I mean first of all if we tried to just do some range of 1 if we're going to add all the numbers between
1 and 1 we should just return 1.
So that's a base case.
And then here is our recursive call return income plus some range number minus one.
So this gets a little bit crazy.
I know because we have more than one return in here.
We're going to step through this one little piece at a time.
But think of it this way if I plug in three we're going to start.
This is not true so we skipped that and this is going to return three plus some range of two and some
range of two will return to plus some range of one and some range if one returns one and then all those
things are added back up waiting on the call stack and we end up with six.
So I have it over here let's just test it out quickly.
I do some range of let's do four.
That's going to give us 10 as you can see there.
OK.
And three should give us six and it does.
So let's actually walk through what happens if you feel good about this.
Just move on and skip this because I am going to do a detailed walkthrough just because it really helps
I think and my experience helps if anyone is struggling to understand what's happening.
This is a bit different.
We're not just printing we're returning and returning or returning and returning over and over and over.
So let's let's walk through this.
I call some range of three.
So that's the first thing I do.
This is not true.
So that doesn't matter right now.
Numbers 3.
But then that's going to return.
So if we just write that.
I don't know why I'm doing caps.
There we go.
Return numb which is three plus some range of two.
Right.
OK.
So some range of three.
Is this right here.
And it's waiting for some range of two some range of two if I tab over here.
It's going to be called is number one.
No it's not so we skip so that returns numb which is so I'll try and do this in the middle here.
Return to plus some range of minus 1 which is 1 like that.
OK.
So we have some range of three.
The first thing we called it's waiting.
It's basically trying to add three to some value but it doesn't know what yet.
Some range of 2 has to be computed but that's waiting because some range of two is going to return to
plus whatever some range of one is.
And then finally some range of one when Gnome is equal to 1.
This is true.
So we return 1.
That's our base case.
It stops us from Feel free falling forever to a rapid descent.
We're returning one that's the end.
There is no further recursive call.
So when we return 1 what happens.
Well this this was waiting to see what some range of one was.
So that gets simplified that turns into one.
Right so this returns 1.
So then this turns into one.
So then returns some range of two is going to return to plus one.
This now has a value which is three.
So then some range of two returns three which is to lead it and put it back up here which some range
of 3 was waiting.
Some range of three basically knew it was going to be three plus whatever came back from some range
of two.
Well finally there's a value that came back it's three.
So it returns three plus three which finally returned six.
And that's our answer.
So it's kind of complicated to draw out.
I picked a small number like three.
But as we go higher and higher there's many more function calls on the stack that we have to worry about.
So we can we can view this let's do the same thing.
Let's do for this time and I'll put my breakpoint in here.
If you grasp this already skip it.
But let's do it now.
So we step through.
First thing that happens will I have to execute it command enter.
OK.
So first off some range of four is called that added to the call stack.
This is waiting now for not waiting yet.
It's being executed right now.
This is not true.
Move to the next line and it's going to return four plus some range of three.
So it's going to wait because it has to have an answer from it from some range of three.
So you can see in this this some range right here is three down here.
Number four.
So it's going to do four plus whatever this answers are returns this can't return anything just yet
because it's return value is three plus some range of to none.
And this one is too.
So if you watch over here as I go to the next step we get another some range added to the call stack
and this and this one local variable numb is two.
So this first part's not true.
Move on.
It's going to return to plus some range of 1.
So finally our call or call gets added up here.
So now we have another function call added for some range this time though knowm is one.
In this context so numbers one means this which means this is true.
So we finally return one.
So remember this is waiting here.
This is waiting on the return value of this is waiting in the return value of that.
This one is waiting on the return value of this one.
This is going to return 1 so when that happens right here we go return value one and then watch as he
gets popped off.
There we go.
This function now which was waiting it was adding to plus the return value of some range one.
Well that has a value it's two plus one.
So it returns three and this one when it returns three fills in the blank for this second call which
was waiting to see what some range of three was.
So then we get that enter returns 6.
And then finally this sum range which was waiting the whole time patiently to add four plus the sum
range of three which came back at 6 so we get four plus six which is 10 and a returned 10 and we're
done.
So I know that there's a lot there but I hope that explanation helped out a little bit.
It's always nice to walk through the deck but this one is different than the last video where we just
were printing things out and this in this case whatever is returned from the base case matters it's
added on to what the previous function call was waiting for.
And then that added on and it has this reverse cascade going back up okay.
Hopefully that makes a little sense.
We have a couple of more examples.