All right.
Welcome back.
So we have one more basic recursion example here and it's probably the most classic example of the most
classic intro to recursion function that's used which is factorial.
So if you're not familiar with factorial B It looks something like this as a mathematical expression.
Exclamation point.
You don't read that as for that's just four factorial which is equal to 4 times three times two times
one.
And you know 10 factorial is 10.
I'm not going to type the whole thing out but ten times nine times eight.
All the way down until 1.
So you could easily do this without recursion just like all the other things I've shown you so far.
How would you do that.
Well hopefully you can visualize it now but use a for loop and like here.
Let's define our function.
Just call it function.
Factorial takes in a number and then let's make a total variable but total equal one.
And then we'll do a fourth.
So for let's do i equals numb keep going all I is greater than zero and then do I minus minus and then
we'll just multiply totals total times equals.
And then at the end return total should work.
So total starts that one if numbers three we're going to loop for I equals three.
So the first time through we multiply total by three.
So we get three then we subtract 1 from it's two we multiply by two.
Next time we get six then I is 1.
So we multiply by 1 which technically we don't.
Well let's just make sure it works around this.
So let's just do factorial of three K we get 6 ex-Royal of 4.
We get 24.
OK.
So it's working.
There's one small change you can make just to eliminate some redundancy if total is 31.
There is no reason to multiply by 1.
At the end because we're multiplying by 3 times 2 times 1.
So we can just do this is greater than 1.
You multiply by 1 and it still works OK.
So that's the non-recursive solution the iterative solution.
Next let's do the same thing but recursively.