Welcome back.
Let's do the same thing right factorial.
But do it the recursive way.
OK.
So what we need to do the first thing aside from just defining our function.
The first thing is going to be to understand both the base case and the smaller chunk the recursive
call the different whatever you want to call it.
Basically the two different components.
So I mean just to find it here takes in a number like this.
And what we're going to do factorial of three is equal to three times the factorial of two factorial
of two is equal to two times a factorial of 1.
So what we're going to do at the end of the day we're going to return here numb times factorial of numb
minus one.
So hopefully this part makes sense but if we just had this this would be problematic because there's
no stopping point.
If numb starts at 10:00 then we're going to return 10 times factorial of nine.
But then factorial of nine returns nine times sectorial of eight.
But it keeps going he goes past zero goes to negatives and it will go forever.
So that's not good.
So we need to have the endpoint.
Well what is our End Point.
Well we kind of can take what we did in the interim version iterative version we multiply by 1.
That's the end of the road.
We don't want to keep going to zero because if we do if we multiply by zero it eliminates all of our
hard work because it wipes everything out.
The magical power of zero.
So we'll just do something like if numb is equal to one return one factorial of one should be one right
if we plug one in here we should get one right away one time to one.
There's nothing below it to multiply by.
And this is it.
This is the solution.
So it's short.
And if we step through it let's do it with three again.
We're going to it's the same idea behind the last one we did with some range.
Right it looks identical except for multiplying instead of adding So factorial of three is going to
return three times factorial of two factorial of two.
It's going to return to times factor of 1 factorial of 1 returned 1.
So then we work back up.
So if we just really quickly do this factorial of three actually that manufacturable of 5 a little bit
larger.
Just to show you and I'm not going to go through it step by step.
We're just going to very quickly look at what happens to our stack over there as it continues to grow.
OK so now Gnome is one.
So we have one two three four five calls here.
Naam is one which is returned.
So then we work backwards you can see the return value growing from one that is multiplied by two then
by three.
Now we're going to multiply it by four.
We get 24.
Then you multiply it by five and we get 120 and that's the return value of 120 and you can see the console
shows us it displays the return value of 120.
All right so that is recursive factorial a very very common intro to recursion exercise and it's a pattern
as I already explained it's basically the same thing here except we're multiplying now instead of adding.