Welcome back.
So what I want to do now and this video is talk about some of the pitfalls the common problems that
arise when you're writing recursive solutions.
So one thing that happens more often than you might think is that you don't have a base case or your
base case is wrong.
So what I mean by that is that if you go back to factorial here without this base case right here this
code just keeps going and going and adding function calls to the stack over and over.
So if we just plug into the factorial of two it's going to do return two times factorial of one factorial
of one is going to return 1 times factorial of zero factorial of zero overturn zero times factorial
of negative 1 and it just keeps going forever.
There's no end in sight.
And if I do run this right now you'll see what we get maximum call stack size exceeded.
So this means that actually I don't exactly know what will happen if we do try and step through this
but if I if I try it out you'll see that our stack just continues to grow over and over and over.
So I could keep clicking forever and stepping through this.
We're at 100 something calls in the stack right now but there is a maximum size it does differ depending
on Node what engine you're using.
I think that it's somewhere around 10000 calls.
Not positive though.
But there's a maximum and we're going to exceed it.
So if I just resume the script execution you'll see if we get that error maximum call stack size exceeded.
OK so that's a big problem.
Another thing that we could run into is returning the wrong thing or forgetting to return in the first
place.
So what I mean by that is if instead of returning So let's say we have a base case the correct space
case so it should stop.
But what if we are just returning numb times factorial of no.
And this is a simple example it's easy to identify the problem but sometimes the code is a lot longer
and sometimes it's harder to walk through each individual step.
If you don't take the time to pay attention to what you're actually returning because even though we
have a base case it doesn't help we're never going to hit it because we're returning.
In the case of factorial to returning to times factorial of two which is going to return to time sectorial
to unspin forever.
Well not quite forever.
As you'll see.
We hit a problem there we go maximum call stack size exceeded one more potential pitfall is if instead
of a return here if we had a constant log one for example.
So we still if the base case let's change this back to number minus 1.
So everything looks good except that we're constantly logging one when numbers are equal to 1.
And what do we get.
Same thing maximum call stack size exceeded because we printed out one here for we to refresh and do
the same thing step through this.
If we look at the call stack.
OK.
So factorial of 2 is called.
So we returned two times factorial of 1 factorial of 1 isn't returning anything.
So it doesn't stop execution here.
Remember that's the way that we we pop this thing off the stack is by returning.
But we're not returning one.
So instead this is just a nice little extra thing.
Oh by the way if Gnome is equal to 1 print out one but then keep going return 1 times factorial of 0.
So you'll see that's what happens now.
Now one we return one time check or local hero.
Now name is zero.
And we keep going and if I keep clicking you'll see nothing keeps going down negative 7.
Now we're at and we'll keep going until we hit the maximum call stack size if we exceed it.
So I'm going to fix that and put it back as return 1.
So the importance of returning is.
I mean that's what recursion is built on the idea of this call stack where all these things are dependent
on one another waiting they're kind of primed in a chain.
But we still have to return some value at the end to then send back and then to add or multiply or do
something with to send back to the previous one to keep going until we get to the original function
call effect.
Tauriel too.
All right.
So let's just make sure it still works and do factorial at 5 but if we get one 20 Okay it's working.
Now one note in Chrome the message it's giving me is what is the maximum call stack size exceeded.
This is generally what's known as a stack overflow.
Think of the stack.
It's overflowing.
Right.
Too many frames on that stack.
Too many functions trying to be called.
So you might have and you've probably come across that term before.
And the name of a popular Web site stack overflow that's where it comes from.
When you have usually it's a recursive call if you see that message just keep that in mind.
This means that your recursion is not stopping.
There's never a rock bottom.
OK.
That wraps up but I want to say about common problems.
You don't have a base case or you're forgetting to return the value or returning the wrong thing.
All of those can result in a stack overflow which is not good.