Welcome back.
Next I'd like to introduce a design pattern that's commonly used with recursion called hoper method
recursion.
So far all the recursive functions we've written are single standalone functions like factorial.
It is recursive itself we call factorial from outside the function and factorial itself calls factorial
inside its own code.
That's been the case with all the functions we've written so far with helper method recursion.
It's a little bit different.
So this code doesn't actually do anything.
This is sort of just a pattern that I'm laying out but with helper method recursion we have two functions.
We have the outer function here and then inside we have our recursive function.
So this recursive function calls itself as you can see here.
Again this is just the pattern I'm going to show you a concrete example that does something in just
a moment.
That's what's called a helper function or a helper method recursion.
We have our main outer function that we would call like a developer from outside here we would call
outer and pass something in and then inside the code of outer.
There is another function defined and it is called and it calls itself recursively.
So this is commonly done when we need to compile something like an array or a list of data.
We're not simply tabulating we're not multiplying one value over and over and over like we work with
factorial or something different something range.
That was another one we did.
If we're doing something like this collecting all the odd values in an array it's very easy to do helper
method recursion.
We create an empty array where we will then store our data in and then we call our helper function.
So the reason we do this.
If I just tried to define a function called collect odds which accepts a list of names.
If I tried to make a variable called result and I set it to be an empty array.
This is where we're going to put the odd numbers.
Well if we're doing a recursive function no matter what I put after this every time it is called result
will be reset to be an empty array.
So how are we going to collect our data.
How are we going to have this piece that persists throughout.
And one easy solution is to define result outside of collect odds like this and then add two results
in here and rather than having a result float around in the middle of nowhere like this.
We use helper method recursion which really just means defining a function around it.
So here's my solution for a solution to this problem.
Looks like I'm missing a bracket update that slide it is ok zoomed in too much.
So what we have here is collect odd values which is what we would actually call down here.
Will pass in like I don't know.
Let's do a simple one something like this and it takes that array in it makes our result array that's
empty.
Then here is our recursive logic and ignoring that for just a moment we call the helper function which
you defined here with the array and then we return results.
That was to find a peer.
So this is going to manipulate results who will be adding to result.
And again the reason we do this is that if we tried to define result inside of here it would be reset
to an empty array every time through.
So with the help or method recursion we can get around that.
And this is a common pattern when we are trying to compile some sort of result usually an array or some
other sort of data structure along those lines.
So the actual logic here if we do want to walk through this if we look at helper it's executed at the
bottom with array.
So this is array.
This is passed in and we have a base case where if the helper input is empty if the length this year
row we just return.
Otherwise we check if the first input or the first element mod 2 is not equal to zero.
That means that it's odd.
So if it's not divisible by 2 cleanly it's odd.
So we push helper and input 0 into Brazil.
Then the next thing that we do is call helper.
But this time we call it on everything else in the array.
Excluding that first element.
So we make a submarine like this a smaller array and we pass that in to helper and we run it again.
And it's not empty.
So we don't return.
And then we take the first element which is this and we check if it's even or odd.
Well it's even this time.
So this doesn't run.
So then we call a helper again helper and put that slice 1.
So this time instead of this subarray we look at this one.
So we're always looking at the first element and we're shrinking that array shrinking and shrinking
it until it's empty and we return OK.
So that's the logic behind it.
But this pattern whether it's odd values or we're doing something else.
So later in the course this is a flash forward.
Do not worry about understanding any of this but this is from the graph section of the course.
We did find a method called depth first recursive which has a result variable.
And this actually is it's an example of helper method recursion.
Here is the helper method defined inside of our other function and we call it down here and it's updating
the result variable.
Anyway we'll come back to this.
Not the focus.
I just wanted to show you that this is a real thing.
I'm not just making it up or showing it to you for no reason.
This is an actual traversal of a graph data structure something a little more complex.
OK.
So this is one way of doing this solution but this is not the only way of writing collect odd values
recursively.
You can do it without a helper function you can do it without having to define result outside in a different
scope and then updating results.
It's just that this is simplistic it's easier to understand in the next video.
I'm going to show you how to do this.
The pure recursion way which is not necessarily better.
It's a little more confusing but it is all recursion.
There is no helper method.
It's a little shorter but we'll get there.
That's coming up next.
So Hulver method recursion is just a pattern where we have an outer function that's not recursive which
calls an inner function which is recursive.
OK.
I'll be quite.