Hey welcome back.
So the first thing I should say is that this video is paired here it goes along with the previous video.
We're going to solve the same problem in two different ways.
So in the last video if you didn't watch it I recommend you at least skim it.
We talked about helper method recursion one strategy one approach to solving this problem collect odd
values so recursively doing this is easy.
Can use a loop and it's not difficult but to do it recursively is a little bit more difficult.
So collect old values takes an array of numbers even and odd and it should return only the odd numbers
extracted from that array without actually changing the original array.
So helper method recursion was one strategy but that's not the only way we can do it with what's called
Pure recursion meaning the function itself is totally self-contained in its recursive.
We don't have some external data structure like we had here this external result today.
We're not doing a nested function helper method recursion.
We're not doing any of that.
We can do it with pure recursion.
It's just a little more challenging.
So here's the code.
It is shorter but it's a little harder to wrap your head around at first.
So I'm going to copy this over and show you that it works.
Here we go.
If I execute the code collect our values on 1 2 3 4 5.
It works we get 1 3 and 5.
Now if we walk through how it works it's a little bit different.
So we are defining this variable new array each time through.
And if you remember in the last video what I said was if you were if you define this new array each
time through it's going to be reset to be empty.
And that's true.
This is going to be an empty array every time the function is called recursively down here.
What's different is that we don't care we want it to work that way.
And what we actually do is concatenate all the arrays at the very very end into one array and return
that.
Let me just walk you through what happens.
It accepts an array.
One two three four or five.
That's what we'll start with.
Then we define a new array to be empty.
We check if the array that input is empty.
It's not in our case it's 1 2 3 4 5.
Then we check if the first number in our array is odd.
And in our case it is.
So we push that number one on to new array.
So at this point our new array looks like this.
Just one.
Then we assign new array to equal new array that current value dot concat the result of collect odd
values on the rest of the array.
So array slice 1 if we take this array for example 2 3 4 5 slice 1 it gives me everything from the first
element onwards so ignoring the zero element or the index of zero element we get three four or five.
So a rate of slice 1 is going to take this array
like that.
Collect odd values of two three four five.
So of course we're waiting here's the recursive part we're waiting for this to come back and return
a value.
And that can take a moment.
So when we call that we diagram this out collect our values 2 three four or 5 we make a new empty array
new array array at length is not zero.
It still has values in it for them.
So we skip this.
The first number is not odd.
It's 2.
So we skip it we don't add it in.
Then we get to this line new array equals new array concat collect odd values array slice 1 so new array
this time is actually empty.
This is what new array is.
New array.
Doc concat the same thing.
Collect odd values of the array.
Three four five Sorry if you can hear that car honking outside.
It's a bit ridiculous.
Three four five.
This array slice 1.
So speeding through the rest of this when we call it next time we're waiting on this collect our values.
Three four five.
Well what does that return.
Well it's going to concatenate on a non-empty array this time new array contains three because it's
the first value is odd.
And so then we call that concat on collect odd values on for Khama 5.
And then this repeats I'm just going to copy this down
so this time it's an empty array because the first value is even and then next time through.
We're almost there it contains five and we try on an empty array.
And then finally when we call collect our values with an empty array if it's empty we return new array
or new array is just empty.
So this finally returns this value.
So we get an empty array.
So then what happens.
Well this was waiting to concatenate this with whatever this returned and this happened to return an
empty array.
OK.
So when we concatenate five with an empty array it's just 5.
Then we return new array at the end.
So we return this so we can replace this right here with that.
So now we can once again we concatenate an empty array with this array.
And that's going to give us this array and we return it.
So then here collect odd values return this and we concatenated with this the array containing 3.
So we end up with this array.
Then we take this and that's returned and we filled in there and we concatenate it with an empty array.
Which just leaves us the same thing.
We return that here which is concatenated with this which gives us our final return value.
One comma three comma five.
So along the way we use concat to help build up the result.
If we just tried to push into new array over and over.
It would be reassigned instead.
New array is just going to allow us to either concatenate nothing as you saw five rebuild this.
I won't let me go back.
Well a lot of the time with even numbers we were returning an empty array or concatenating an empty
array with another return value that wasn't empty that contained an odd value.
So we use concat to help us out here.
And this is the pure recursion way of accomplishing the same problem.
I think personally that helper method recursion is more straightforward.
Yes it does involve you know a little more code to make that separate second method but I don't think
that it's a big deal and when you get to more complex logic you're working with more difficult logic
and data structures rather than just pulling out the odd numbers.
You can always do it using pure recursion you can.
You know you can make that work but often I prefer to go with helper recursion.
But in this case I kind of like this solution.
It's kind of cute.
Doing all this concat over and over and over just to show you a couple of tips when you're using arrays
and you're trying to do a pure recursive solution without a helper method.
You can use methods like slice the spread operator and Concat that will make copies of arrays so you
don't mutate them.
And this will allow you also to accumulate some sort of result.
Strings are immutable so you'll need to use methods like slice or substring to make copies and with
objects.
It's helpful to use object as a sign or the spread operator.
So we will come back to this later in the course we will be writing quite a few recursive solutions.