Hey welcome back.
It's a new section here.
It's a brand new morning at least for me.
Recording this and most importantly a brand new data structure that graph so I love graphs personally
they're fun to teach They're fun to implement but most importantly they're really really useful in today's
world.
Graphs are used in basically any social network any time we're modeling users and recommendation engines
for example.
When Netflix recommends another movie or something to you or advertisers target you based off of something.
Graphs are usually in play.
And when I say graph we're not talking about a chart which in English often we also call that graph.
Now talking about this sort of two dimensional looking chart it's a data structure very different than
this.
So what it is we'll get to just a moment but first our objectives.
So explain what a graph is.
Obviously get to start there.
Compare and contrast different types of graphs and also will compare and contrast graphs to other structures
we've seen like trees which are actually a sort of a special type of a graph.
And then also talk about their utility their applications in the real world.
Then we'll implement a graph using something called an adjacency list.
So there are multiple ways to implement graphs.
I'm just going to show you one the adjacency list and we'll talk about why then we'll traverse through
a graph using our good old B if s and DFS breadth first in depth first search compare and contrast graph
traversal algorithms we'll talk about big-O along the way.
Talk about some fun algorithms but let's get started by just talking about what a graph is.
Take it away Wikipedia a graph data structure consists of a finite and possibly mutable set of vertices
or nodes or points together with a set of ordered pairs of these vertices for an undirected graph or
a set of ordered pairs for a directed graph.
OK you get that.
Yeah.
That doesn't really make much sense or probably doesn't make a lot of sense.
It's kind of clunky really what it comes down to is a graph is a collection of nodes and connections
between those notes.
So if we go back and read that definition again let's just sort of skim through it a finite set of vertices
or note.
So let's just say a set of nodes together with a set of pairs of these vertices.
So those are the connections.
So we have a bunch of dots a bunch of nodes and then connections between them.
So this is a valid graph.
These are the nodes and these are the connections.
Here's another valid graph.
The same nodes just different connections.
So the placement of them in this diagram doesn't matter.
We can have this same structure.
It's just the connections that are important.
But you know if these are if this be was way over here or this F was way over here doesn't matter as
long as we have the same lines going the same connections.
It's really just about those lines.
OK.
So this is a valid graph.
Here's another one.
We have some nodes with connections between them.
Do I have one more.
Here we go.
A very different looking one the same number of nodes the same letters for each one but different connections
different lines.
So if we go back to something like a linked list and we talked about linked lists we had nodes that
are connected in a linear fashion.
When we had no trees we had nodes that there was one parent.
One top most node.
And then from there there were a bunch of children that descended from that one node and each parent
could have its own children and so on.
So a tree is a type of a graph but in these graphs that we're looking at here.
There is no parent no there is no starting place.
There is no you know entry point.
These are all just notes are treated equally and they're connected in different ways and those connections
can mean different things.
Let's actually talk about a few examples.
First of all of where you would use this.