So now I want to talk about some real world applications.
Where does this stuff come up a bunch of nodes connected by lions.
Well all over the place.
Social networking I'll talk about we'll also talk about things like mapping Google maps directions location
pathfinding routing when you request a web page.
The actual response itself comes back in a bunch of different little packets all over the place across
this massive network.
Really they're just used all over the place.
But let's start by talking about social networking or just the internet in general.
So this is a visualization I found on Flickr.
There's many of these out there but this was one of the only ones they found that had a license that
allowed me to use it.
And I think this is somebody who can see I think with their name models I don't know if you use Facebook
or what social network their connections between their friends.
I think it was Facebook and so each dot on here each node is a person like Kim the L and then you can
see all the connections that you know Kimmer has two other friends.
And what's interesting here is that we can see there are these clusters.
There are some people that this person knows who maybe don't know any of his other friends or her other
friends like this Susan maybe they met on a cruise somewhere.
He was traveling.
But then there's this giant cluster maybe they went to school together all these people or maybe they
live in the same city and they went to college years you know different groups here.
But this is a way of representing a social network.
So Facebook Instagram Twitter all of these they're storing your friendships your relationships and much
much more than just a name like we have here.
But that's the bare minimum really to represent the structure of a friend network of an actual real
world social network or think of storing actors and their relationships in movies.
And you know the different actors that have been in each movie you could store it this way.
Here is a visualization of part of Wikipedia.
These are pages that link to one another.
And this is just a small subset of it there are way more Wikipedia pages than the nodes that you see
here.
But we can see there are certain clusters and like this one here or whatever this is it links to a ton
of different pages that themselves don't really link to other pages.
And this is just Wikipedia but the web itself the Internet in its entirety we could model as a graph
where we have web pages that link to another page.
So anytime that one web page links to another that would be a connection from one node to another Here's
another application.
When we talk about mapping this is a really really common one.
When we think of how Google Maps for example or Mapquest if you were back in you remember that printing
out directions I used to have to do that from my parents.
When you think about how you would store that map itself in roads it's just only talk about roads not
hiking trails not bike lanes.
There's a bunch of nodes different cities different locations waypoints restaurant whatever we're talking
about.
And then roads that connect them and those roads are basically the connections that we talked about
between the nodes.
And in this example this is in Guatemala to go from this one city beautiful city Antigua to get to Lake
added land which is a beautiful lake.
There are many many options.
This is only showing kind of the two fastest but of course we could go some ridiculous route like go
through here and then go over here then go up the ice and there's a bunch of ways to get there.
And Google Maps is basically calculating the fastest way to get there.
Along this graph there are many different options and there's many algorithms that talk about finding
that shortest path and what's the easiest way to do that.
And it's much more complicated than just the length of the road.
There's things like the speed limit of the road for example you might have a much shorter road but it's
windier or it's a dirt road.
You might have traffic that Google obviously takes that into account.
Things might be close.
It's a lot more complicated than just calculating the shortest path.
But my point is more that we can store this data using a graph.
It's a bunch of nodes connected by roads.
So recommendation engines that's another one.
When we talk about any time you see something on a Web site people also watch like on Netflix or who
you might also like X when you're listening to something on Spotify for example people you might know
Facebook or Instagram or Twitter they all suggest those.
This thing was frequently bought with on Amazon for example and many other web pages.
Those are all recommendations that are made to you and often the way that they're made the way these
all this data is stored is in some sort of graph relationship.
So here's a super simple example I made with two video games.
Imagine that we had this for every single video game ever made.
And I didn't actually write out all the data points but here's a graphic for the game Halo and for Borderlands.
If you're not familiar with the games it doesn't matter.
But what you can see here the ones in green I didn't actually write Tex for all of them but the things
in green they are nodes that both these games have in common.
So these are like genre elements maybe space future sci fi guns.
First person shooters.
But now imagine that you have this expanded not only to include every game in Amazon for example or
in steam or whatever app you use to buy a game but also other things besides just genres.
How about user reviews and clicks people who clicked on Borderlands also looked and browsed what else
or trailer reviews.
There's so many different things that you would take into account and then to suggest something let's
say about Borderlands and I finished it to have a little box pop up and say People also looked at X
you might just look you write code to figure out what games have the most in common.
Which ones share the most nodes.
OK.
Well in our graphics only halo will suggest Halo.
So the datasets get way more complicated but anytime we're talking about this sort of X also did this
or you might like this or you should buy this.
I guess that's a little more forceful.
You should buy but you might want this.
Those are recommendations pretty much always stored with some sort of graph structure.
I forgot I had a little diagram there.
The thing things in common in that box here's a cool graph structure that models all the different genres.
Most of the genres in music around the world.
So if we zoom in you actually see all of these connections appear it's pretty crazy.
So this purple Let's see.
Which one are you.
Purple is Jamaican slash and reggae.
And if we go and unfortunately the zoom is kind of annoying but if I had zoom in you can see.
All right.
So there's dub and then we hover over dub and you can see all of its connections to other nodes.
For example it connects to old school rap pioneers or if we look at deep funk and new funk it has some
connections over to freestyle and break dance on the right in red.
Or too early funk and funk.
Anyway this is a fun Web site to check out but this is a graph structure at its core storing modeling
the relationships between genres.
This one also has an added dimension though of time I believe as things developed.
You can see that down here are the more recent trend up top are the older types of music so you can
see like classical it's over here and what is this folk music is here anyway.
So graphs are really commonly used.
They're sort of exciting I think to know about and the next thing we need to do now that we have established
the base definition it's a bunch of nodes with connections between them and there's not a pattern like
there is for a tree or for a linked list.
There's sort of freeform and just nodes with connections.
What we need to do next is talk about different types of graphs and also a little terminology so that
we understand the type that we're going to implement which we're going to get to very shortly.
That's coming up.