Welcome back.
So we've talked about what a graph is generally some nodes with connections between them.
Now let's talk about some particular types of graphs.
First of all there's some terminology.
These are the basic terms you have to talk about vertex and edge.
So a vertex is what we the fancy term for a node.
So when a graph when we say vertex it's just in our diagram one of the circles an edge is the connection
between the nodes.
Then there are two pieces will come back to weighted slash unweighted and directed slash undirected.
But first let's look at this graph on this graph.
Any of those circles are vertices.
This is a vertex see.
This is a vertex B.
So I might use node and Vertex interchangeably but that the technical term like on Wikipedia you'll
see Virtex although it does say Notice well in the introduction vertex is like the technical term.
And then these connections are edges.
So this is an edge from Ada.
This is an edge from A to B from B to D and so on.
So from one vertex to another that's what an edge is.
So there are many many types of graphs different distinctions and sort of how they're built and rules
they follow.
Just like with trees and actually already hinted at this a tree.
We actually click on them page for a tree.
The definition is that it's a graph in which any two vertices are connected by exactly one path meaning
that to go from six to two for example there is only one path to get there to go from three to five.
There's one path.
Contrast that with some of our graphs here to go from B to D.
We could go here here to here or we could go here to A to B to F D.
And this is not even a great example some of the other ones we've seen there are way more edges with
more connections.
So for a tree to be a tree it's just a bunch of nodes with a bunch of connections so it's a graph.
However there's only one path from a given node to another.
OK.
Now let's talk about directed versus undirected graphs.
So this has to do with the edges the connections between the vertices.
So in an undirected graph there is no direction to or polarity.
You could say to the edges.
So they are two way connections is another way of thinking about it a and b are a connection.
So is B to say if we are traversing this we could go this way but we could also go this way there is
no direction associated with an edge and that's useful oftentimes depends on what you're modeling.
But let's talk about like Facebook how Facebook model's friends if you don't have a Facebook Facebook
account you probably know how it works.
You have to request someone and then they will accept your request or reject it but hopefully accept
it unless you're a stock or something.
In that case you are both friends.
So you see that friends stuff on your web page or on your home page they see your content.
It's not a one way relationship.
So this is an example of what you know a couple of friends could look like on Facebook where if Maria
and Tim are connected that means Maria sees Tim's content and tim sees Maria's content.
Now let's contrast that with a directed graph.
So a directed graph is often represented with arrows which indicates the direction the polarity of that
edge.
So for example from B we can go to see we could traverse to see if we could traverse to a from E..
We cannot traverse to B we cannot traverse to D or to f.
So e is sort of like a dead end here.
So on on directed graph there is a direction assigned to the edge the connection between vertices to
vote for Texas disease.
Yes.
So that's how you would model a social network like Instagram or Twitter where our friendships are the
following relationship is not a two way thing by default.
For example on this chart let's say it's Instagram we have Maria who follows Tim and Tim also follows
Maria so they see each other's content.
But Maria follows Justin Bieber so she sees his content.
Justin Bieber does not follow Maria back much to her chagrin.
That would really make her day.
If Justin Bieber would follow her but he doesn't.
Same thing with tim.
Tim follows Justin Bieber Justin Bieber does not follow Tim but if you look over here Justin Bieber
does follow Kanye and Kanye follow Justin Bieber so you can see this sort of information in a situ in
a social network like Instagram is important because if you are a celebrity you probably don't want
to just see every single person's content who follows you.
You want to be able to pick and choose what you see unlike on Facebook where we modeled it with an undirected
graph because all connections are two way.
Although that does ignore the whole like Facebook celebrity pages where you can you know create a special
marketing account.
But if we're just talking about the basic typical user account on Facebook versus Instagram this is
how we'd model Instagram with a directed graph.
Facebook is an undirected graph.
OK.
So there's one other piece of terminology which is a weighted graph versus unweighted.
So right now this graph is actually unweighted because each connection between the vertices the nodes
each edge has no value associated with it.
But now get this.
There we go.
Magically it is a weighted graph.
So when we assign a value to the edges it becomes a weighted graph.
There's information about the connection itself.
So unweighted versus weighted.
Everything we've seen so far has been an unweighted graph.
This is an unweighted directed graph.
This is an unweighted undirected graph and this is a weighted but undirected graph.
So for example if we're talking about maps here's our same Google Maps example in Guatemala.
I'll get rid of the map.
Let's say these are all cities or I don't know gas stations or any sort of points of interest.
There's connections or edges between them but they are weighted.
We need to know these values.
So if we're trying to calculate the shortest path we can add these it's not to scale by the way I just
picked random numbers but we would add up.
You know if we're trying to go from here to here we could add 40 plus 20 plus three or add 13 plus 120.
And you know figure out which is shortest.
Now this currently the way it's displayed is an undirected graph.
It's two way connections but maybe some of these roads are actually one way roads in which case like
if we were really modeling Google Maps we would have a directed and weighted graph where you know certain
roads like in San Francisco or Manhattan for example but really all over the world are one way road.
You can't just go any sort of way that you want.
You have to follow the rules and there is an actual value assigned to those edges.
So if we go back to something like Instagram this could easily be represented as a weighted graph because
you might like if you're a marketer if we're talking about Instagram's like advertising team internally
they care about these relationships not just who follows Who but also what their appetite is for that
person's content.
That makes sense.
So there would be some sort of value assigned to this relationship or more than one value so that Maria's
connection to Justin Bieber might be superstrong because she loves Justin Bieber.
But Jones maybe isn't as strong.
And you could easily store that using a graph data structure.
Keep track of you know how many times this person did X or Y or assign a value for how much they love
a certain person they follow.
So just because I'm displaying this part just to explain what a directed graph is I'm not saying that
it couldn't be a weighted graph.
All right so let's wrap up the terminology.
Let's go back here.
We have undirected graphs.
So what I first showed you in the last video there is two way connections or you could say that there
is no direction to the connections the edges between the vertices.
And even before that we talked about the term edge is the connection between two notes which technically
each node is called a vertex.
So then there's a directed graph where there is a direction assigned to an edge and edge could be bi
directional.
I could could point both ways but it also could point one way.
Then we talked about unweighted versus weighted so an unweighted graph has no value associated no magnitude
with each edge a weighted graph does have a value associated with an edge.
And so when we're traversing or when we're computing the shortest path for example we would use these
values.
All right.
I know those a lot.
Next we're going to talk about different ways different strategies for actually storing the information
in a graph.
How do we model it.
That's next.