Welcome back.
Now that we know a little more about grafs we know the fancy terminology around them.
Let's dive into the nitty gritty details of actually implementing graphs storing them or representing
them using code.
So going back to this image from Wikipedia it's a graph of a small subset of Wikipedia pages we have
each vertex here is a page or an article on Wikipedia.
And each edge each connection represents I believe a link or a reference a cross-reference.
So if we have this chart here and somebody asks you to store it using code how the heck would you go
about doing that.
What data structures would you use to help you create your own classes What would you do.
It's not easy but if we break it down what we really need to store a graph the important information
are the nodes the actual vertices and then a way of storing the connections.
So with like with a linked list for example we did next and previous If it was a doubly linked list
with a binary search tree we had left and right.
In our classes that's not going to work for a graph really because there's any number of nodes and the
number of edges connections between a note.
So what do we do.
Well you could come up with any number of solutions.
Just like with the linked list you could store lengthiest using an array just doesn't really make sense
because why not just use an array.
Same thing with graphs you could come up with sort of heavy handed approaches but there are two standard
approaches that we're going to talk about that most articles blog posts deck overflow the two common
ideas for how to do this and they're called the adjacency matrix and the adjacency list.
So before we dive into that this is the graph that we're going to work with here try and represent this
using code.
It's a little slimmed down from this one but it's the same idea.
We have vertices a vertex and then edges between A and B or A and F and we need to store that information.
So we go into the adjacency matrix A matrix if you're not familiar with it is just a two dimensional
structure usually implemented with nested arrays but not always.
And basically we store information in rows and columns.
So we could represent the connections here using a matrix something like this.
So the way you would read this sort of a boolean matrix yes or no zero or 1.
So between any two vertices and two nodes let's say a n d.
So if we look at a and we go over to D.
There is no edge zero false there's nothing there.
But if we look at a and b go to a we look at B there is a connection there.
If you look at a an F A over to F where there's a one right there which is how we store true.
So this is the way of representing all the edges.
Notice that it works the same way if we start here.
So if we're looking at the connection between C and D for example we could start at c on this left axis
and go over to D and we see there's a connection or we get started on C appear at the top and go down
to D.
And that's because it's an undirected graph meaning that it's a two way connection but we can also store
directed graphs where only one way is stored that makes sense.
So what we have here is a matrix you could do nested arrays to store this information.
Zeros and ones is probably the most common but you could you could do.
True or false you could do.
I mean if you wanted you could do yes or no.
But all that you're storing are the edges.
So every time that we add a new node A new vertex we have to add an entire new row down here an entire
new column and we'll compare and contrast the approaches and just a bit.
Explain what these are good at what a matrix works well doing it and what it sucks at quickly.
Here's the Wikipedia page just wanted to show some diagrams.
Here's a representation of an undirected graph here.
This is the graph Here's a matrix storing it.
Here is a directed graph you can see the arrows and you can see the the matrix that we're doing or that
we're using is no longer symmetrical.