The other approach we'll discuss is called an adjacency list.
So I actually change these nodes.
The verdict seems to be numeric and you'll see why in just a second it's easier to show how you could
store this.
So instead of A and B C D.
So on we have 0 1 2 3 4 5.
So the way that this works is we use an array or list to store the edges.
So if we wanted to figure out what edges what connections there were between 3 and its other nodes the
other vertices we would go to index three of our array 0 1 2 3 right here.
And then there's a list there that contains that connection.
So there is a connection between three and two and three and four as you can see here those are the
edges.
If we wanted to know is there an edge between 5 and 1.
Well we would either look at index 1 and look 4 or 5.
It's not there or we'd look at index 5 and look for one.
It's also not there and this is an undirected graph.
So we have things stored both ways.
For example zero has a edge to one.
One has an edge to zero.
So this is another way of storing it.
However if we're talking about letters we're going back to this where we have a B C D E F and letters
is arbitrary.
But let's say it's a name a string or something else that isn't just a number.
Right.
This one hinges on using the positions of an array to find the connections the edges from zero.
We go to this zero with item and that works.
But what if our nodes aren't numeric.
What if they're not in order like this.
What if their strengths are what if there's huge gaps between the numbers.
So we don't want to just use an array.
What else could we do.
Well we could use a hash table use a key value pair data structure so a dictionary a javascript object
a map.
There's many ways of doing this depending on the language.
But here's the exact same information where we store for a given key instead of a key being a number
like zero in an array.
It's now in a hash table or hash map to look at the connections the edges from a we look up a inside
of this structure and then we look at the list and we see right there something from a to b and a TO
F..
As you can see here a to b A to F. same thing.
Let's do.
So we'd ask for e from this hash map and we get this.
So that tells us there's a connection between Ian D and F..
OK.
So this is an adjacency list.