Just like an adjacency matrix there are two different ways of expressing the edges the relationships
between our vertices.
OK.
Now let's compare them.
So here's kind of an intimidating slide that talks about the Big O notation between adjacent to us and
adjacency matrices for various operations.
So first a couple of things I should explain the N E.
So v is a number of vertices is the number of edges.
So if we think about the storage how much space they take up compared to one another.
If we look at an adjacency matrix you can see we're looking at big-O of V squared where v is a number
of vertices and that makes sense because it's a two dimensional structure.
If we add a new vertex it means not only just adding one slot in it means actually adding an entire
row in an entire column to our matrix.
Compare that with an adjacency list.
It really only grows at the rate of number of vertices and edges.
So I think that makes sense right.
All we have to store here really the size is governed.
Or if we go back to this example same thing in the adjacency of list the size of it the amount of storage
is determined by how many edges how many connections we have.
But if we go to our matrix it doesn't matter how many connections there are.
It matters how many vertices.
So we could have 100 more vertices or let's be more conservative let's say nine more vertices and they
might not have very many connections they could only have one each one edge each.
Well we're still going to have to add nine rows down here or appear and nine columns and that's a lot
of space.
So if your data is sparse if you don't have a lot of connections a lot of edges maybe don't use a matrix.
So you can use this slide as a reference.
But here's a breakdown of some of the key points.
So an adjacency list as we've already talked about can take up less space in sparse graphs where you
don't have as many edges compared to an adjacency matrix which takes up more space.
V squared or V is a number of vertices an adjacency list.
If all you want is to know the edges just iterate.
For example search over all of the edges and you need to access all of them.
It's easier to do with an adjacency list because I think that makes sense if we have this structure
we can just start.
All right here's edge Here's all the edges all the edges.
If we go to a matrix we're going to have to iterate over a bunch of things that aren't edges.
We're going to you know there are things that are stored here that don't exist that makes sense we're
leaving empty spaces versus in an adjacency bust.
We're only storing the actual connections it so fast to iterate over alleges lower to iterate over all
the edges in a matrix.
However with an adjacency list looking up a specific edge to see if it exists for example can be slow
in a matrix.
It's very fast.
You can see that on our Big O here to queery something.
OLF one constant time for an adjacency matrix.
So if I wanted to know we go back here is there an edge between a and D.
All I have to do is go find that slot A and D.
No there is not.
Is there an edge between B and C A B C.
Yes there is.
It's constant time.
If we compare that to an adjacent CBEST actually let's go to letters if I want to know is there a connection
between A and D.
Well I'm going to have to ask for a first then I'm going to have to iterate over this.
So depending on how many connections there are how many edges to A.
There could be a ton and I might have to iterate over the entire thing depending on the number of edges.
So I can't know instantly like I did with a matrix.
So that's where we get oh a V plus E V is number of vertices is number of edges.
So the big O itself doesn't matter that much right now just know that in general a matrix takes up more
space.
When we're talking about sparse data sets it's not great.
It's slower to iterate over every edge but it is faster to look up a specific edge.
Also some people think the implementation of a matrix can be a little easier and adjacency list takes
up less space.
It's faster to iterate over all edges but it's slower to queery for the existence or to check if something
if an edge is in there.
So which one are we going to use them.
Are going to go with this rainbow.
Beautiful text and adjacency list.
So excited about it.
There three times.
Why are we going with an adjacency list.
Well mainly because of the space that it takes up and the fact that most of the data in the real world
whether we're talking about social network data friends modeling actors who are in movies together Wikipedia
pages whatever it is real world data tends to be sparse.
So we can have a ton of nodes lots of vertices but usually they're not all connected and that lends
itself more to adjacency lists.
Remember this chart look at any given node on here.
It doesn't really have many connections.
Some of them do.
Definitely but there's a lot of nodes that only have one edge one connection.
So for each one of these whatever the number of nodes is here the number of vertices seem to make a
massive matrix versus if we're only storing the actual connections using a list it's a lot easier.
It's a little and it takes up less space.
So because most real world data looks something like this even though there's a ton of data here.
The large set there aren't very many connections compared to how many there could be.
So in a matrix it works well if your data is jam packed.
If your matrix could be almost full then you might want to use a matrix but otherwise I prefer to use
an adjacency list.
So that's where we're going.
And finally in the next video we've all set up our code and get started.