Welcome back.
Let's get to work implementing our graph class.
So I mentioned in the last video we're going to use an adjacency list to do this.
And our basic class for our graph is super basic a Tibet way of explaining that it's very simple.
Let's put it that way.
All we need is a single property called adjacency list or something similar to store the actual edges
the relationships the connections between our vertexes or vertices.
So it will start empty and we'll add things in one at a time.
But first we need a way just to add a vertex before we can add edges before we can draw the connections.
We have to just add the dots the nodes so that's where we're going to start I should mention we're going
to do an undirected graph.
For now it's very simple to change it to be a directed graph where the relationships that the edges
are one way there's a direction from A to B.
For us we're going from A to B and at the same time bita.
So when we add an edge and we'll talk about how we how we handle that.
Well let's start with the basics.
Adding in a vertex.
So here's our first method.
We'll use this as our skeleton add a vertex is basically a one liner.
It takes the name of a vertex whether it's 10 or pineapple or Hawai whatever it is.
We add that in to our adjacency of us.
So write a method called add Virtex which accepts a name of a vertex.
It should add a key to the adjacency list with the name of the vertex and its value should be an empty
array.
So we add a vertex first before we can add an edge.
So there's no connection at this point.
We're just adding in a simple vertex.
So if we had a graph called G and it was empty and we called add vertex Tokyo the result is that our
adjacency list looks like this.
Tokyo is now a key a value for Tokyo is an empty list an empty array and that's it.
So it's really really simple this one all that we do right the method you need to just make sure that
it accepts the vertex.
You add that vertex has a key with the corresponding value of an empty array to the adjacent to list
and that's all.
So give it a shot in the next video there'll be like a 10 second solution.