All right.
So let's give it a shot.
I'll head over here and the first thing we need to do is define our graph class.
We need to add our constructor doesn't take anything and we set this adjacency.
That's the hardest part is spelling adjacency list is going to equal an object.
OK.
Then we add our method called add Virtex which accepts a new vertex key and then all we have to do is
do this dot adjacency list of Vertex whatever that vertex is instead of equal to an empty array.
Now I didn't specify how this should handle duplicate.
So if there's already a key in there we're one thing we're going to do with this graph class is keep
it simple.
We're not going to you know add in a bunch of error handling.
So if somebody tries to add a new vertex it's already in there.
It's fine if we overwrite it obviously in the real world you would want to add some sort of protection
in there.
You know return or throw an error that says there's already a vertex in there or ignore it because our
code is just going to overwrite it and set it to be empty but it be super simple to fix out right.
We were just check if this adjacency list of Virtex if that exists.
Or let's say if it's not there then let's just do it on the one line and see how long that line is.
I think that's OK with me.
So we'll just do this just to keep it really simple.
If there's nothing there already then make it an empty array and that's it doesn't even need to return
something.
Let's run our code.
Let's make a new graph.
Just call it g equals new graph.
OK.
And we do not add vertex of Tokyo for example.
We look at g at the adjacency list and now has Tokyo set to an empty array.
Do one more with what else should we do.
San Francisco Okay.
And basically that's all there is to it.
But let's just make sure that little tiny bit of error checking worked.
So I'm going to manually change this is not how you should interact with it but we don't have any methods
to do anything.
So I'm just going to change it.
Tokyo from an empty array to just have something in there so if we look at the adjacency of us now Tokyo
is not an empty array.
Pretend that that's an actual relationship that's data we care about.
So if I now did not add vertex of Tokyo again we don't want it to overwrite it.
And if we look we still have Tokyo set to its initial data.
OK.
So this is fine.
That's about as much error handling as we need.
Looks good that at Vertex really simple.
You didn't even need to do this first part.
Just set the adjacency list of that key to be an empty array.
Next we'll add relationships between vertices will add edges.