Welcome back.
Next up we'll focus on adding edges on drawing those connections between two vertices.
So if we are adding cities in Tokyo in Dallas and Los Angeles and Hong Kong and that sort of thing let's
say that we are working for an airline we're representing like all the flights that an airline has and
the connections you know at the back of those airline magazines.
If you ever read those anymore there's those maps that have all those lines from cities will do the
same thing sort of.
We're going to model that data structure.
OK.
So an edge will represent a flight from one city to another that our airline offers so of actually at
an edge we need to specify the two cities the two vertices.
We will just call them Virtex one and two.
So the function called add edge needs to accept two arguments V1 V2 vertex 1 v vertex to whatever you
want and it should find in the adjacency list the key of Vertex 1 and then push vertex 2 into that array
and then do the same thing for Virtex 2.
So it should find in that adjacency list the key of vertex to push vertex 1 into that array.
And don't worry about handling errors.
If somebody enters an invalid vertex if that edge already exists don't worry about that for now.
Let's just get the basics.
This is really more about fundamentally how this all works.
So let me just show you roughly how it work.
If this is what we have at the beginning like we can do this right now just add a new vertex added vertex
add a new vertex Tokyo Dallas and Aspen.
There's nothing connecting them there's no edges.
Then if we did add edge Tokyo and Dallas remember that this is an undirected graph.
So it doesn't matter if we do Tokyo and then Dallas or Dallas than Tokyo but our end result would look
like this.
Tokyo.
The key of Tokyo now has now has Dallas in its array.
And the key of Dallas now has Tokyo in its array.
Or if we did an edge from Dallas to Aspen which is really the same thing is Aspen to Dallas.
We end up with Dallas now has Aspen and they're in Aspen.
Now has Dallas.
OK.
So this is pretty short as well.
It's really just two lines that you need to do if if we're not doing any of the air checking as I mentioned
all that we're doing is accepting to write a method called an edge it accepts two arguments.
You take that first one and you find it in the adjacency list using it as is key and then you push the
second one into that array.
And then you do the same thing for Virtex 2 you push the first vertex into its array.
OK.
Let's see how it goes.