All right.
So let's implement an edge on our graph class.
So let's just define an edge and it takes two vertices.
I'll just go with V-1 and V-2 and then in here we just need to access this adjacency list of V-1.
It's now equal not equal to excuse me.
We're going to push into that V-2 and then do the same thing.
This adjacency list of the two we will push in not we want and that's all according to the specs that
I've laid out that's all you have to do.
Now if you did want to add error handling and to make sure that this is a valid key and this is a valid
key you could do that just a couple of conditional statements but I mean I'll leave mine super simple.
Let's just make sure it works.
So I'm going to define down here.
Let's do the new graph.
I'll fast forward through this.
OK.
So I have three vertices in there.
They should all be empty at this point.
Great.
Now let's try doing g.
Add edge from let's go from Dallas and Tokyo.
Which direction doesn't matter because it's going to go both ways.
And if we look at our adjacency list we now have Tokyo is in the Dallas array and Dallas is in the Tokyo
array.
So if we wanted to make this a directed graph we just wouldn't do both of these.
Right we would take the first one.
So the order would matter.
We would go from V1 to V-2 and only do this we wouldn't go from V-2 to V-1 but we're assuming that our
flight to go both directions which I think most airlines do.
I mean I don't know it's possible that they only have flights in one direction from one city to another
and they fly back a different route.
We're ignoring that.
OK so let's just make sure it works again.
Just double check.
Let's also add one from Dallas to Aspen.
And if you look at our Jason to us now we have Aspen has Dallas and Dallas also has Aspen.
OK.
So that's all there is to adding an edge.