Welcome back.
Next up we'll add two different methods to remove nodes.
Excuse me vertices and edges.
So first let's remove an edge so we'll need to provide two different arguments.
What's the actual edge we're trying to remove from Dallas to Tokyo.
OK.
And then what that actually means is removing two different pieces of data because our connection is
stored in two places.
So write a method called remove edge that accepts to two vertices the names of two vertices two keys
in our list.
Then it should reassign the key of Vertex one to be an array that contains everything that was there
before.
Minus vertex 2 and do the same thing for vertex to reassign the key of vertex to to be an array that
does not contain vertex 1 and don't worry about handling errors in invalid vertices things that aren't
there just assume that we're calling these methods with valid names for all of vertices.
So here's an example.
If this is the state of our current adjacency list if we called remove edge Tokyo in Dallas we are going
to need to remove Dallas from the Tokyo list and remove Tokyo from the Dallas list.
But that doesn't mean just setting it to be empty of course.
We can't delete the entire thing.
We need to maintain Aspen in there.
So really it just means re-assigning this list Dallas to be equal to this whole thing minus Tokyo.
There's many ways of doing it but give it a shot.
Here's what our end result would look like.
Tokyo is empty.
Dallas still contains Aspen.
But that connection has been severed.
Dallas and Tokyo no longer are on edge.
All right.
So give it a shot.