All right let's get to work on removing an edge.
So let's define our method over here.
Call it shocker.
Remove edge and it accepts two vertices and then all that we need to do is let's start with the first
one.
We're going to need to reassign this adjacency list the one to be everything it already is minus V-2.
So I'm just going to use the built in filter and Javascript adjacency list of the one dot filter and
then I'll just call this V.
Doesn't matter and will filter where v is not equal to V-2 which now I'm looking at v v v to maybe to
make it clearer I'll call this vertex one vertex to just moment update this.
OK so we're just saying take the current adjacency list of Vertex 1.
Filter it.
Keep everything where it is not equal to Virtex 2.
OK.
And then I'm just going to duplicate this
and alter it slightly so it's Virtex 2 that we're updating and we're comparing it to vertex 1.
There's other ways of doing this of course but let's let's test this out.
So I will quickly update this.
OK so now I added two edges in but just look at the adjacency list.
Here's what we have.
Aspen connected to Dallas Dallas connected to Aspen and then the Tokyo and Dulles connection.
OK.
So let's do a G dot remove edge from let's say we're getting rid of the flight from Dallas to Aspen
or from Aspen to Dallas.
Let's look at our adjacency list now and we can see there's no connection now between Aspen.
There's nothing in that array.
And in Dallas there's no trace of Aspen.
Let's do it one more time for Dallas in Tokyo.
And we will get G.
Everything is empty now.
Like most of these methods we could break it pretty easily if I tried to do it to do a remove edge from
L.A. to S.F. for example.
There is no Virtex called L.A. or SFO so we get an error because filter doesn't work on undefined.
That's OK.
I said you know pretty explicitly that we're not going to care about that for these videos we're just
working on the fundamentals of our graph.
And that's all there is to removing an edge.
Next up our last sort of basic piece is removing a vertex and then we'll get to traversal and searching
and that sort of thing.