Welcome back.
So our final basic component around adding edges and vertices and removing them is removing a vertex.
So let's say that you know we're modeling this airline and we used to fly out of I don't know Hong Kong
a lot but now something happened.
We are it's I don't know why it seems like a place you would never pull out of fear an airline but let's
just say we were removing it from our map we don't want to fly to Hong Kong anymore.
That means removing all edges and also removing the Virtex itself.
So it's a little bit more complicated.
So we'll write a function called remove Virtex and accept a single argument just the name of the Virtex
we're trying to remove.
It should loop as long as there are any other vertices in the adjacency list for that vertex.
So meaning if we have Hong Kong in our adjacency list and there are ten edges it's just 10 other cities
we need to loop through that and remove each connection.
It's not enough just to delete Hong Kong from the list.
We also need to remove all of the edges.
Otherwise we were left with these broken edges.
So inside the loop we'll just use our remove edge function.
We already defined so we'll call remove edge for each edge in the vertex or trying to remove.
And then lastly will I actually delete the key in the adjacent to the list.
So let me show you what that looks like.
If this is our initial state it's a little more complicated.
Let's say we're going to delete Hong Kong the entire vertex.
So what that actually means deleting is this entire line of course.
But if we only got rid of this then we would have Tokyo still's a reference to Hong Kong.
Even if Hong Kong is gone and that's broken that's not good.
So we also need to remove that we need to remove.
Los Angeles has a connection to Hong Kong and so does Dallas.
So we need to remove all of that.
So our logic is really take Hong Kong.
That's what we're removing.
Loop over its array and for each one called remove edge which he already defined which will delete Tokyo
from Hong Kong and remove Hong Kong from Tokyo remove edge on Dallas in Hong Kong and so on.
And then finally we still need to actually delete Hong Kong.
The key so that there's no reference to Hong Kong in here.
And that's something you may not do very often.
I don't do it very often.
Usually you just leave it empty or set it to be undefined or something.
But let's just remove it entirely from our adjacency list.
But in Javascript you can do that with just delete and then the thing you're trying to delete.
So this is what we'd end up with at the end of the day.
All trace of Hong Kong gun.