All right.
So let's get to work on our final method around the very basics at least after this we get to go on
to traversal and searching and some of the more challenging stuff.
And we have to worry about recursion and stuff like that.
But for now removing a vertex.
So let's define our method come up here we'll call remove Virtex and it takes in the name of a Virtex
like Hong Kong and I've written a couple other method calls to build out a little bit larger graph so
that we actually have some data to remove to make sure it all works.
So if we remove Virtex What do we need to start with.
Well as always we're going to need to do this dot adjacency list of that vertex and that's going to
give us you know for example if you go back here.
Can you give us this.
If we're trying to remove Hong Kong we need to loop over that and for each item in there we are then
going to pass it in to remove edge.
So let's do a loop right now.
Let's just do we could do while this data adjacent to Virtex and I'm going to do length which seems
weird to do while this adjacency list length but I'm going to actually pop off items from this list
as we go.
So eventually we'll get to 0 and then our loop will stop.
You could do a for loop.
You don't have to do it this way.
So we're going to grab.
Let's just call it adjacent vertex.
You don't even have to make a variable to do this but to make it a bit easier to read I'm going to do
this here so we're going to take each item and pop it.
So here if I run this right now if we look at adjacency list let's say we're looking at Hong Kong.
We're looping over this while this whole thing has a length.
If we're trying to remove the Hong Kong vertex first time through pop this item Los Angeles off and
then we're going to call this dot remove edge and what's the edge where we're removing.
Well it's between Los Angeles and Hong Kong.
The Virtex itself.
So the order doesn't matter.
We can do Virtex and then adjacent Virtex or we could do the other way round because this is an undirected
graph.
There is no direction.
The order doesn't matter.
We're removing both parts.
OK.
So that will do that takes care of that.
And then if we actually run this now and we look at g g dot adjacency let's just check on it one more
time.
All right here's Hong Kong.
Let's now remove Virtex Hong Kong and if we look at the adjacency list again you'll see what do we have.
Well we got rid of all the references to Hong Kong.
If we look up here this has gone.
And for example there used to be Hong Kong in Dallas and in Los Angeles and Tokyo.
And if we look at those Tokyo there's no Hong Kong Los Angeles no Hong Kong Dallas no Hong Kong.
However we still have this empty array.
So this is where we need to delete that entire key.
So down here said You may not do this very often.
Delete this adjacency list of that vertex so delete Hong Kong entirely.
So if I rerun this we look at the adjacency list again.
It's back to Hong Kong.
Now let's remove Hong Kong and look at the adjacent to the.
Again there there's no trace of it.
Hopefully yes it's gone.
Again I don't know why we'd remove a flight or all flights to Hong Kong.
Seems like that wouldn't happen.
But you can see it's gone.
Let's try removing Aspen now and if we look at the adjacency list no trace of Aspen either.
OK.
So that's one way of writing removed Virtex.
There are other ways you could do.
You could write that would be a little more efficient.
Also you could pretty easily add in some air handling just added conditional to make sure that the Virtex
is valid.
But again I'm keeping this very bare minimal just to focus on the logic.
So next now that we have a basic skeleton we can add and remove vertices edges.
Now we're going to actually build out a little more complex graph and then talk about traversing and
recursion and depth first and breadth first and yeah get your aspirin or Advil ready or alcohol or whatever
you need.
It's going to be quite the ride.
It's fun stuff.
OK.
That's next.