Hey everyone welcome to a new section.
This one is a little special.
A little different because it's not about a new data structure we're not learning a structure and implementing
it.
Unlike you I guess the past 10 plus sections where it was all right this is a tree that's right one
this is a graph of the right one instead we're learning and implementing a single very famous algorithm
called Dijkstra's algorithm.
It's shortened from Dykstra.
Shortest path algorithm.
Most people if you just say Dykstra they know what you're talking about.
Well not most people in the real world but most computer science people it's very very famous.
It's one of if not the most famous algorithms out there.
We'll talk about why why it's named Dykstra is who he was what he did and most importantly what the
algorithm does.
In just a bit.
But the first thing I want to say is that even though this is not about implementing a new data structure
there are two sort of prerequisite data structures.
One is the graph because Dykstra is algorithm X upon a graph.
It searches across a graph.
So if you didn't watch the graphic graphic content you definitely want to do that.
And then the second thing is that it actually uses a priority queue as part of its implementation.
So in this section we're not going to write a priority queue from scratch because in the binary heap
section we did that we used a binary heap to implement a priority queue.
Now if you skip that.
I understand there's a lot of content in this coarsen and you don't necessarily have to go you know
video by video but I am telling you now you definitely want to go and just watch the priority queue
section or the binary heap section.
And in particular the Prior to cube videos at the end because that code will come up here.
So I'm just going to copy and paste it over.
So just as a warning those two things Graf's binary keep's I would be I would try to familiarize yourself
with them first.
All right.
Next let's talk about our objectives.
So first we're going to understand the importance of Dykstra.
That's happening in this video.
The history that sort of thing then as a sidebar we have to implement a weighted graph because Dexters
algorithm works on a weighted graph and so far we've only done unweighted graphs.
After then we'll begin sort of digesting and understanding the algorithm.
Now it's not terribly complicated but it gets long enough that me giving you a single slide of pseudo
code probably wouldn't be enough.
So I'm going to have some animations some videos or some slides and made to walk through it some diagrams
so we're going to just go step by step how it works and a sample graph then we'll implement it using
a naive party priority queue and then we'll upgrade it a bit using our binary heap priority queue.
All right.
So a lot of stuff for a single algorithm.
Let's start by talking about what it even is.