All right.
So if you happen to skip the last video we're talking about Dexter's algorithm here and the two important
things you need to know before you begin this are graphs and priority queues with a binary heap both
of which I have a lot of content on in this course.
So what is the algorithm.
It's one of the most famous and widely used algorithms around.
Pretty much every computer science classroom in the world learned that at some point and more than that
it's not just an academic thing it's not just you know interview challenge although it often is.
It does come up in interviews.
Most importantly it's used all the time often.
Big tech companies will base a lot of their more proprietary sort of special secret algorithms on top
of Dykstra.
And in some of their own special flavor I guess so.
So we'll talk about what that would look like.
And a lot of the use cases but what it does primarily is it finds the shortest path between two vertices
on a graph.
So if you have a graph with you know 10000 different vertex vertices how do we get from point A to Point
B.
What's the fastest way there could be a million a billion options and a really large graph how do we
calculate the shortest one.
So that's a problem that digesters our themselves.
Hence the term or the name Dykstra is shortest path algorithm.
First let's talk about who dextro was just a sidebar here.
So Edgar Dykstra butchering it.
I know he was a Dutch programmer.
He actually died relatively recently.
Well not that recently but 2002 or 2003 I believe but he was working in the very in the early 20th century
when computer science was sort of a new field.
And he was a bit of a polymath.
He was I think he started out as a physicist theoretical physicist.
He wrote a bunch of essays not to mention tons and tons of academic papers on programming mathematics
problem solving.
Really smart guy and more than just smart very influential.
So he helped to advance the field of computer science from at the time was more of a burgeoning art
to the crazy academic discipline that it is now.
He really established a lot of the academic rigor that's present in computer science.
He came up with a bunch of papers most of which are still cited today.
I read some facts that out of the 30 most influential papers he wrote six of them I think something
like that.
I don't know how you you know how you determine most influential.
But anyway the other thing is that he actually created new fields in within computer science single
papers that he wrote spawned off these new disciplines.
So very very influential.
And unlike some other pioneers whose work sort of at the time was very important and led the way for
other breakthroughs a lot of the stuff that he talked about and wrote about is still in practice today
are commonly used like nature's outgrew them.
So here's a little screenshot from Wikipedia on the right side of his Wikipedia page.
Like any sort of academic figure or really any person there's a little bar that says no one for you
can see he's known for a lot of top.
His main achievement that people recognize today.
It's like saurus algorithm but there are many other algorithms that you can see but also things like
self stabilizing distributed systems shunting yard algorithm smooth sword separation of concerns early
software architecture.
He did a lot and contributed a lot.
So really cool guy and very very important person.
Now the algorithm itself it is listed up top.
It's widely used widely taught as I mentioned and we've we've kind of explored the main idea behind
it finding the shortest path between one point and another but the story of how he came up with it and
why he even tackled this problem is kind of interesting.
I don't know if this is 100 percent true but it's on Wikipedia which doesn't always mean much but apparently
that the impetus for him actually doing this for coming up with his shortest path algorithm is that
he wanted a problem that he could come up with to demonstrate to the general public why computers are
awesome why they were powerful.
He wanted to show something that was difficult for humans to do and how easily computers could do it.
So he came up with this travel problem of finding the shortest path along the massive train network
in the Netherlands figuring out the fastest is the shortest way.
This is his quote.
What is the shortest way to travel from Rotterdam to granite again.
Not much.
Sorry about that.
From any given city to city it's the algorithm for the shortest path.
And then here's his little humble brag which I designed in about 20 minutes.
Apparently he was shopping and then over coffee and he was tired.
He designed it like a little cafe table in 20 minutes.
And eventually that algorithm became to my great amazement.
One of the cornerstones of my fame.
So it's kind of fascinating.
He didn't set out to solve this as his you know his thesis or is his greatest achievement this problem
that haunted him his entire life.
It was more of oh I want to just come up with something that the public will understand something that
will demonstrate the intrinsic value worthiness of computers.
How about finding the shortest path using the rail network in the Netherlands and then that is actually
what went on to have a lot of implications and use cases to this day.
So Leslie let's talk about why that is.
Why is it still useful.
So the most obvious thing that I've already mentioned this as an example GPS GPS or any sort of mapping
software whatever app you use whether it's Google Maps Apple Maps or whatever other versions that are
out there or you have one of those old school GPS devices in your car.
Mapquest all of that involves finding the shortest path from one point to another and all of that data
can be represented using a graph.
Now of course there's a lot of other complications in today's world.
And like Google Maps its algorithm takes not only the distance but the capacity of a road the number
of lanes that traffic accidents whether time of day.
I'm sure there's many other factors I'm not even thinking about holidays.
Yeah.
There's a lot that goes into it but it's still based on fighting.
Finding the shortest path.
Now what makes something short might be different because our version we're going to talk about we're
looking at a single criteria like distance on a map.
We're not implementing traffic and all of that stuff.
But at its core we could take it take digesters algorithm as we're going to learn it and then tweak
it to add in traffic or to account for weather and that sort of thing.
Next up the network routing finding the shortest path for data across a massive network.
If you think of computers you know they're connected in a graph.
Let's just say a million computers.
How do we send.
How do we break up a large message into a bunch of little pieces.
Senator Krus bunch of computers end up at another computer which is the fastest shortest way to get
there biology.
It's used often to model the spread of of infectious diseases across humans often used in projections.
I have no expertise in that.
That's just something I read online.
What I found fascinating.
Airline tickets if you ever go on those Web sites and you know you enter where you're trying to go from
one city to another let's just say one way.
Of course you can optimize for all sorts of different things like duration price number of airline miles.
But if you're willing let's say you're trying to come up with the cheapest possible option and you're
willing to make like three different stops.
Well there's a lot of options and it would be a huge pain to try and manually compute that but using
a shortest path algorithm where it's minimizing it's optimizing for cheapest rather than shortest distance
you might end up flying across the world a couple of times that might be cheap and you might have long
layovers but the algorithm could do that could figure that out for you.
Looks like you put biology on here twice.
Whoops sorry about that.
And many many other uses as we'll talk about as we go but we're going to start with just a blended graph.
Maybe look something like this where we have numbers representing the distances between cities are junctions
in different paths.
But before we can even talk about the algorithm we have one small problem which is we don't have a way
of storing this data right now if we simplify it for that that math background we can't do this part
right here.
We don't have a way of storing the information about a given edge.
Our graphs are just vertices and edges.
They are undirected meaning there's no arrows.
They are both ways but they're also unweighted meaning there's no value associated with them.
So the first thing we need to do before we can find a shortest path we need to just add distances or
add a weight to our graph.
So it's not hard.
It will just take a minute or two and the next video.
That's what we do next.
So then we can actually implement the shortest path algorithm.
So in the next video I'll be back to write a weighted graph.