All right.
Welcome back.
So what we need to do before we can actually find the shortest path in a graph between two points.
We need to just assign values between those points so we can find any path short or long.
And to do that it's not that hard.
All we do when we add an edge instead of saying from A to B we just say from A to B comma 90 from B
to C comma 13.
So if we hop over to a quick little snippet we could just quickly redefine our class so we'll call it
weighted graph and I'm only going to worry about adding a vertex and adding an edge.
We won't worry about removing edges and vertices for now because let's just focus on the important stuff.
So class weighted graph what are constructor.
Exact same as an weighted graph.
We have an adjacency list.
The main difference though is once we're actually adding edges in what we had before looked something
like this or we had like a.
And then it just had an array where we had B and maybe C or something.
That's not going to cut it for us because we now need to store not only the edge itself from A to B
but the value.
So it's going to look something more like this where we have a field or it's going to be an object and
we'll have two properties node which to just say is B for example and then wait which will be 10 a number
and then of course we would have the same thing on B where the node is a and the weight is 10.
So instead of just simply the string B we now need to add in an object.
But as far as the vertex if we had ADD vertex it's exactly the same.
So I'd vertex just checks if the vertex is already in the adjacency list and if it's not then we added
in and set it to be an empty array.
So that's nice and easy.
Now we can add in our vertex like a and b and c.
Now to add the edge between two vertices need to accept two vertices so let's go with vertex 1 and Vertex
2 and then await.
And if we look at what we did for our weighted urch excuse me for unweighted graph from earlier in the
course.
If you look at adding an edge it's very simple we just do this stuff adjacency list of Vertex 1 push
vertex to this adjacency list vertex to push vertex 1.
So we'll have to change a couple of things because I use Virtex one instead of v v 1 but that's minor.
OK.
So vertex 1 for text 2 for text 2 but this won't work because we're not using weight.
So remember we need to store an object inside of that adjacency lists inside this array we're pushing
into.
We're going to have an object where there's a property called node does not have to be called that but
it could.
You could call vertex view on it too.
But let's go with node and then wait.
And rather than doing this wait colon wait cause I want it to be called wait.
And also the argument is wait we can do is just pass and wait here and it will do the exact same thing
as part of I believe that was added in 2015.
It may have been around before and I just didn't know about it.
The same thing here and that's it.
This should be our weighted graph class so see if it works.
Of course I just executed the code.
So let's make a variable called graph.
It's a new way to graph and what to add Virtex first just say a and b and c.
And now let's add an edge from A to B which is going to be I don't know nine.
And then let's do a to see which will be five.
Sure.
And then let's do BTC which will be seven.
OK.
Now let's look at the adjacency list rather than just trusting that it works.
So you've got a B and C and for each entry in the adjacency list we have an object with a node and a
weight.
So for example from a we can see there's a connection to be with the weight of nine.
And if we look at B there is a connection to A with weight of nine from A to C.
There's also an edge with way to five if we will see you there you are.
We have a see way to 5.
All right so this is all working.
Like I said we don't need to worry about removing edges and removing vertices for now because we're
focusing on the algorithm but it's extremely similar to what we saw before.
Except now you just need to remove an object but otherwise it's very very similar.
OK so now we have all the pieces in place to actually talk about the algorithm.
Moving on to Dijkstra's and the next video.
So this is our weighted graph class.
Very very simple class might be confusing if you didn't watch any of the graph section.
I should have mentioned that earlier in the video but I did say that early on in this section.
So definitely go watch that.
If you're confused about what I'm talking about here.
All we did was add in a weight to each edge.
So it's a connection from one vertex to another.
Now with an associated value.
All right.
Next up we're going to walk through the basics of the algorithm.