Welcome back.
Now that we have the weighted graph in place we can move on to diet.
That's nice.
Nope.
There we go.
It's a dumb joke but this is actually the three attempts took me to get it right.
I'm sorry to tarnish his legacy.
I can never remember how to spell his name but it's the bottom one here.
D i j.
Anyway what we're going to do now is walk through the steps of how the algorithm works for you to visually
go through it one step at a time before we translate it to code.
And the graph we're going to work with looks like this.
So it's a weighted graph.
Here's you know what six vertices and each edge has a number associated with it.
Hopefully it's clear what goes with what and the path the shortest path that we want to find is from
A to Z.
So there's a couple of options.
This is very small graph and most of the ones in the real world are quite large.
But even with this small data set there are many ways to get from A to.
Can go around the edges you can go through the middle there's what four plus options.
Not to mention could take some absurd wraps to get there including loops in anyway.
So that's our goal.
So here's the algorithm.
Boiled down or distilled to four main steps each time through the main loop will do something like this.
So we look to visit a new node that you know that the only way that this works has restarted a and we
visit nodes and there has to be some order that we visit them in.
How do we decide where to go next and we start by picking the node with the smallest known distance
to visit first.
So I'll come back to all of this visually in just a moment.
But we always pick the node that has the smallest known distance from A.
And we visit that first then once we move to that node we look at each of its neighbors and then for
each one of its neighbors we sum the distance from A to that neighbor.
And if it's smaller than what we currently know about if it's a smaller distance then we update our
file.
Essentially this is a lot to talk about without showing you.
So I have a bunch of diagrams like this.
We'll get to in just a moment but those are the steps.
So every time we visit a new node every time we're looking sort of to start the loop over we visit the
smallest known distance from A.
In our case we're looking for eight.
So we start with that we move to that node and we look at each of its neighbors and for each neighbor
we already have a distance on file how far it is from a.
And we will update it if the new distance that we have some together is less than what we currently
know about.
And I know that sounds crazy.
So I'm going to come back to it.
But here's our diagram.
This is sort of a setup for the next 30 something maybe 40 slides and just fade between them and you'll
see stuff come and go.
So the same graph is up here.
We're going from A to E.
It has the same values on there.
And down here is sort of the file I was referring to where we store the shortest distance from a for
each vertex.
So A is a special case because it's going to be zero but something like B Well eventually the shortest
distance from A to B is four.
Of course.
But then like E which we'll get to that's our goal is to figure out what the shortest distance is.
And anyway we'll be updating this as we go.
And then previous.
I'll explain in just a bit.
So let's begin and the very first thing we do is initialize the shortest distances from a for every
vertex.
And we don't really know how to do that.
That's the whole point.
We don't know what the shortest distance is from a to get to F..
Imagine there's a million vertices on here.
You can't just know from the beginning.
So what do we do.
We just put infinity in here we put a large value basically an unknown.
We can't we don't know any of these values except for one which is we know the shortest distance from
A to A is zero from one vertex to itself.
That's going to be zero.
So that's what we start with this is how we always initialize the set up.
So we'll make a data structure for this we won't talk about code just yet.
But just imagine you're writing this down on a piece of paper.
So A to A is zero A to B.
Right now is infinity we don't know.
A to Z is infinity.
So we ignore that.
Now remember the steps.
The next thing we do every time we look to visit a new node.
We'd pick the node with the smallest known distance to visit first.
Well we have one choice right now.
That's the smallest.
0 is clearly smaller than infinity.
So we start with A.
So we pick the smallest.
That's what that's showing here.
And I've added it to the visited list here.
Now what we need to do is look at each of its neighbors.
So from a we have two choices A to B A to see and I'm always going to go alphabetically.
Doesn't really matter.
So we're going to start with A to B.
So what we do is we go down to B and we check.
Well currently the shortest distance from A to B is infinity because we don't know any better.
That's just the initial state so what we found is that the distance from A to B right here is four.
So four is definitely less than infinity.
So we update this to say all right the new shortest distance from A is 4 and you'll see that we update
some of these a couple of times.
Of course we can see looking at the graph.
There's nothing shorter between A and B it's definitely four.
That's the smallest we'll get.
OK.
So we update that here and then over here in this previous structure we're going to update be said to
be equal to A.
So what that essentially does and I know I'm missing quotes is not valid code but what this does is
it says the way we got to be was through a.
And that's obvious in this situation.
But later on something like f if we update the shortest distance to f we want to remember that we get
there from D.
Or did we get there from C..
There's multiple options.
So this structure helps us piece together where we came from the node that happened or that occurred
right before be on our path.
So that's a simple one.
So we've we've done everything we need to do for a to b.
Now we look at a to see.
OK.
So currently from a to c we have infinity.
So we look at that distance the total is two.
So of course we're going to update this too is definitely shorter.
And then we come over here to see and instead of No we update it to say all right the way we got to
see was from a and that's it for a we've done both neighbors for note.
So now what we have left to do is we repeat the process.
We pick the smallest known value the shortest distance from A.
That we haven't visited.
So remember we've been to a.
So we're not going to pick a because we just continually do a over and over and over.
But now we have two choices.
B The distance is 4 and C the distance is two.
And when I say distance it's the distance from node.
OK.
So as you can see we start with C that is the smallest known distance.
So now we look at c and its neighbors and there's three choices but we've already done eight C so we're
not going to do that.
So now we have C to D and C to F.
All right.
So let's look at c to d first.
So what we do again is we look at what the current value is from A to D.
It's stored at infinity.
So we calculate the new value from A to D through C and the way we do that is by summing A to C plus
C to D.
So for example we know that C to D is two guys so take two and then we look at how did we get to see
what was the previous for C and the previous is a.
So then we figure out what is the distance from A to C 2.
So two plus two gives us four of course.
And obviously it's easy for us to look at but you have to think about what your code is going to be
doing.
So we sum those two together.
That gives just four.
And we'll update this right here to save for.
That's definitely smaller than infinity.
And then we also need to update over here to say how we got to D and the way we got there was through
C..
So that's what we add.
OK.
Next up we're going to look at C to F.
Same process.
So C to F is 4 and then A to C is 2.
And the way we know it's definitely this edge is if we look at c we stored a as the previous The shortest
way to get there.
So two plus four gives us six.
So we come down to F and we check is six less than infinity.
Yes.
So we update it.
So we store six here and then what we need to do is update our previous.
How did we get to f..
Well what came right before it was C so hopefully you can see how this becomes useful.
What we're storing here is the shortest path to any given node from a.
So the shortest way to get to D is from C and then the shortest way to get to see from a is directly
from.
So we only need to store the previous shortest path.
So it's sort of step by step how we get to each node What's the shortest way to get there.
And we combined them all to figure out how to get to e eventually which isn't done.
So we update it to say we came from C..
Now we start over.
We need to pick the smallest value shortest distance from A that we haven't visited.
So we've done a and c so we can cross those off and the shortest thing is either b with 4 d with 4 or
F with six.
Well definitely not six and I'm picking B First just because it comes first alphabetically.
But either one would work.
They're both four.
So now we look at B and B is easy because we've already visited A to B.
So that's not happening.
But we have B to eat.
OK.
So we'll look at that.
And that gives us three plus what came before B had we get to B we came from a.
So that edge is four.
So three plus four gives us seven as the new total.
And that's definitely less than infinity.
So we update this to say well the current shortest way that we can get to Z is 7 units or whatever this
is seven miles or something.
And then the way we got there over here we'll update this to say we came from B.
Right.
So if we stopped right now it's not the shortest path but we have a path that we could piece together.
So we got to e from B and we got to be from a.
Now out of the unvisited nodes where do we go.
So we've done a b c and now we have DNF or which are is smallest D.
So we're going to the next.
OK.
So here is D.
And we have a couple of options.
We've already been to see.
So we're not going that way.
So we either go to eat or F I'm going alphabetically so e comes first.
So we'll look at d e.
So that edge is three.
So now we calculate the total distance from A to E through D.
So the total here is 7.
And if we look at what we have stored for right now it's already at 7.
So that doesn't win.
It's not less.
It's not shorter.
So we're not going to update it.
You could if you wanted to you could write your code that you added seven here if they're equal.
But there's no reason we already have a path that has 7 units long.
This one.
So we ignore it.
Now we move on to the next which is D to F.
So our new total here get to F is 5 and if you look at what we have stored right now we have six.
Well five is less than six.
So we update it to say five and we come over here to f and we no longer come from C. That's what we
had before.
This was the shortest way to get to F..
But now it's actually shorter if we come from D.
So we update it.
So this is saying you know the fastest way to get to F is from D.
The closest the shortest path from A to D is through C the shortest way from A to C is well through
because there's a direct line from A to Z.
OK.
So that finishes up D.
We did this edge we did this edge.
So now we cross it off.
We visited.
There we go.
Now we're going to pick the smallest again.
So we have two options.
We visited all these for a b c and d.
Now we have E and F which is smallest which has the closest distance or the shortest path to a.
Right now that's f 5 is smaller than 7.
So we'll start here and we only have one option.
We've already done this edge we've done this edge.
So now we look at f t.
So the distance is one to go from left to E.
And what's the shortest path to get to f..
So we add that all together 4 5 6.
And if we look at what we currently have stored for e we have 7 we have 7 from this path on the outside.
We've now found something shorter.
So we update this to cross those off.
And now we add six.
And then of course we have to update how we got there because right now we're storing the old version
if you look at.
We were saying the shortest path from A to Z goes through B but that's not the case.
We now just found something shorter where we go through F.
So we update this.
If we look at E.
There we go.
We now say the shortest way to get there is through F and just that one letter difference now makes
a huge difference because it's a cascade it's a chain because we look at where F..
All right well just to get to F we went through D to get to DeviantArt C to get to see we went through.
And at this point we have nowhere left to go.
Aside from E.
And that means that we're actually done.
We found the shortest path.
So to break that down again I won't go step by step but every time through we pick the current smallest
distance from that we haven't visited.
We explore each of its neighbors and we Koukl the new shortest distance to each neighbor and if it's
smaller than what we already stored we update what we stored and then we reflect the change over here
in our previous data structure.
And this allows us to piece everything together.
So if we look at this we're done now all we have to do is work backwards.
So to get to e from a we started and we look at it.
All right.
Well to get to F from a the shortest possible way that's what this is all storing we end up with a list
of the shortest way to get to any node from the shortest way to get to D from a is through C and to
get to the C we have to go from a.
So a C D.
That's the shortest way to get there.
The shortest way to get to is through F and from f first you go through D from D.
We go through C C.
So this is our shortest path.
A C D F D.
So Dexters algorithm works not only if to give you the shortest path between two nodes at the end the
way we're implementing it will have a data structure that gives us the shortest path from A to all the
nodes and that can be very useful.
If you you know you run this once and you don't change your graph.
You have this structure that gives you the shortest path to go anywhere.
You don't have to rerun it for every you know if you're trying to go from A to B and then a to d and
e you run at one time and you get all that information.
All right.
So I know it's a lot.
I made these slides took forever to make and I hope they were helpful.
I definitely recommend stepping through them on your own and just without me kind of explaining what
I'm doing in the video trying and or even on a piece of paper.
That's how I learned it originally.
Literally graph paper drawing these charts out and keeping track of you know.
All right.
We've been to a cross it off we bend to be cross it off and drawing the graph out because from here
the jump to the code isn't that bad.
It's just going to be difficult if you're not sure how this actually works.
So I really really really recommend that you do that if you're at all confused.
If you don't feel like watching the video I don't play mutes long.
It's not that exciting to go through but it can be a little more engaging if you do it on your own.
And then once you understand it jumping to the code it's a lot easier.
All right.
So that's what we're going to do next.
I'll actually show you sort of real pseudo code if you will.
And then if you want you can try and implemented or because this is a little complicated.
Totally understandable if you just code along with me.
All right.
That's coming up next.