All right.
So let's give this a shot.
But before we even talk but the pseudocode.
Remember I don't know if you watched the early videos in this section but I talked about a priority
queue and how that played a role in the algorithm.
Here's where it comes in.
When we talk about picking the smallest value here like if we go back I don't know like here where we
had to pick the next smallest value.
So we visited a C and B we need to look at the rest and figure out what where we go next.
We had four for seven for e and 6 for f.
So we chose D that's for.
This is very easy to do with three nodes.
But if we have a million that we're keeping track of finding the next smallest one to visit can take
a lot of time if we're doing it naively.
So I mean do two implementations.
Here's the first version.
Say hit the next through on my slides Here's our simple priority queue.
And we're going to start here so that we don't get too distracted but this is going to give us the next
node to visit and all that it does.
It's just an array.
And every time you add something to it you give it a priority and then we sort based off of that priority
which is what happens here.
So every time we insert we resort and then we remove from the array.
So I've copied it over here to say you can see it and if we do something like I don't know how far Q
equals new priority queue like this.
And then I do queued up push when I push or actually it's technically it's called in queue.
When we include something let's say just the node A or let's not do a let's say B which has a distance
and Riskin a say of three.
I don't think that's accurate that's the priority that we add in.
And now we're also in queue C which has a distance of 5.
Let's do D which has a distance of 2.
And then also I don't know.
Q says a distance of 20.
Now if we look at Q Dot values you'll see that it's sorted now based off of that priority.
So every time we insert something it resorts.
So if I insert something again that's really small like in enqueue let's say P has a distance of 1.5
that's going to jump to the very beginning.
If we look at values again.
Right.
So every time we dequeue these are the two methods we'll be using sort is used internally and Q and
dequeue.
When I do a Q It's going to give me whatever has the lowest priority.
We want the smallest item.
So what we'll do in our pseudo code is just push in these values like going back here.
But suppose ignore the fact that we visited all of these let's say all of these were in the queue.
When we ask for when we dequeue we want whatever has the smallest distance from A.
That's what we're prioritizing.
So the priority queue is going to help us.
And this is not the best implementation it's simple but remember back in the binary heap section if
you watch that there's a better way a faster implementation for a priority queue using a heap.
This right here because we're sorting every single time it's off and log in.
Which is not ideal but it's simple so we're going with this and then we'll update our code to use the
binary heap and a bit.
OK.
So one more time.
Every time I dequeue it gets to me whatever the current smallest priority is.
But if I insert something else Id again if that smallest I should get that next.
So we'll take advantage of this in our code.
OK.
So that's the naive basic priority.
Q The goal is just to always get the smallest value out first no matter what else is in there.
Just give us the smallest thing first.