OK so now that we have the basic priority.
Q We've talked about how it works.
Here's the Sudoku.
All right.
So define your function on the graph and define it as a method on the weighted weighted graph class.
Just call it shortest path or Dykstra or whatever works for you.
It should accept a starting vertex and an ending vertex of going from 8 to from A to Z.
Are we going from SFO to L.A.X. whatever the vertex names are.
It accepts to start and end whichever comes first will be starting in our case then we need to make
a couple of data structures and we'll create our object we can call it distances.
This will act as this table here where for each vertex we're going to store the current shortest distance
from whatever start point.
It doesn't have to be a of course but let's say we're working with a to e again.
We're going to store in this object the shortest distance from A to B from A to C to D and at the very
beginning we initialize everything to infinity.
If you remember that because we don't know how far it is from A to C or ADA D The only value we know
for sure is a day which we start at zero.
Then after initializing the values and the distances object we're also going to make our priority queue.
So we make a new priority queue and starts out empty and we add each one of our vertices into that priority
queue where we set the priority to be the distance from A.
So basically we add all the vertices in with the priority of infinity except for a with a priority of
zero.
So of course we get a first but then later on we'll have actual values in there that aren't infinity.
And every time we dequeue we get the smallest value back and that's where we begin.
That's what we visit first.
OK.
So this just initialises things.
And there's actually one more step.
We also have to create our previous object where it's just a simple object where we have a key for every
vertex and we initialize it to a value of no.
So that's this data structure here.
But everything should start at No.
And we will update the value for each key as we go.
All right.
So it's mainly the set up that takes some time to explain.
Then we just loop as long as there's anything in the priority queue.
So as long as there's something to visit we're going to dequeue of vertex in the priority queue.
So that means picking the smallest distance from a what are we going to start with let's say D because
it has a value of 2 and everything else has a value of four or six or 10 or something.
So we start with that and then the first thing we do is we check.
Is this the vertex I'm trying to get to have I hit the end and if that's the case then we're done.
Otherwise we loop through each of its neighbors so we'd look at all the neighbors for D and we calculate
the distance to that vertex from the starting vertex and then if that new distance that sum is less
than what we're currently storing we update the distances object with a new lower distance.
So this is all what we did in the last video or two videos we go walking through.
We update the distance we update the previous object to now reflect where we came from.
And then we cue then the same vertex with a new total distance from the start note and that's it.
We keep going over and over.
So for example here we'd pick the smallest value using the priority queue.
Currently it would have D E and F in there because we've done a C and B.
So we dequeue which would give us D because it's the smallest with a value of four.
So then we're going to look at these neighbors.
There's two CNF and we start looking at the summit together it gives us 7 that's actually not less than
what we currently have.
So we don't do anything.
But then we move on to the next neighbor of D.
So that gives us five.
And if you look at what we stored right now it's 6.
So 5 The new total is definitely less than 6.
So we update it here.
Then we come to previous and we say all right the new shortest way to get to F is not from C anymore
it's actually to go through D.
So we just put D right there and then after that we want to end Q f with the new value of 5 so that
it's updated in our priority queue and we know next time are going to pick 5 first because it's the
new smallest value.
All right.
So let's give this a shot.
And if you want to of course try to implement it but definitely not something you have to do.
It's a little more complicated if you want to the pseudo code should get you there otherwise in the
next video I'll go ahead and build.