All right.
So let's let's give it a shot.
See how it goes.
First couple of things I've added the priority queue in this is our nave priority.
Q Will need to use that.
I have a new snippet.
I've added the weighted graph code in.
Again we only have a way to add in vertex and an edge.
I didn't bother with removing them for now and then down here this is new.
I implemented the graph from earlier just by adding the vertices and then that the various edges.
So we're looking from A to E with the shortest path is and the graph should match this graph here.
So for example A to C is to D to E is 3.
And just to verify what we have a to c s to and D to is 3 and so on.
So I tested it out and it was working earlier.
As far as the distances it can be hard to write these down accurately.
So I recommend you copy them if you want.
It's kind of annoying to type this all yourself.
All right so that's just the setup.
Now we need to start by defining our function and I'm just going to call it Dykstra just to make it
clear.
I'll do a capital D even if it's not super conventional and we need our two nodes.
Start and Finish.
So at the very bottom I want to be able to call graph dot Dykstra from a to z and we didn't really discuss
what the return value should be and that's OK.
The search is the most important part at this point but let's say it should return an array containing
the nodes in order.
So A to C to D to F or whatever it was to eat.
OK so we start like this.
And there's a couple of things you need to do we need to make a new priority queue.
So I'll use East 20:15 syntax when to call it nodes equals new priority queue which again is coming
from appear it starts empty.
We needed to make our distances object so call that distances and just initialize an empty object.
We need our previous object which is just again another object representing where we store for C.
The quickest path to see was through a.
Or for each.
The fastest way was through F and so on.
So if you're unfamiliar with it I'm talking about go back and watch.
Well I should say go back and watch this thing right here.
So this is distances and this is previous And that's really all we need for now.
OK so now we have the book for logic.
We need to build up like our very initial distances.
So let's just say build up initial state and what that involves is looping over the entire adjacency
list.
So let's just do a loop right now so I'll do 4 in loops of 4 let vertex in this dot adjacency list.
We have a couple of things to do.
First we need to set each key and the distances object to be infinity except for the starting vertex
which should be zero.
So to do that let's just check if vertex equals start.
So for example for looking at a we're going to set distances of Vertex equal to zero.
Otherwise I'll do n else just to make it clearer.
Are you going to set distances of vertex to equal infinity.
So that's just initializing everything so for going from A to Z this will initialize our distances object
to contain everything you know be through as infinity and A should be set to zero.
And if we wanted to we could just quickly count adult log distances to verify that that's working how
it should run this.
It is a zero and everything else is infinity.
And of course that's because we're going from A to B.
If we are going from B to E then B would be zero.
OK so we don't need constant like that now.
That's only part of what we need to do.
Along with that we need to add each node or add a value for each node to our priority queue.
So we know what to start with and what to take each time where to visit next.
So add each vertex with a priority of infinity to the priority queue except the starting vertex which
should have a priority of 0 because that's where we begin.
So we made our priority queue it's called nodes and I'll just do nodes dot and queue and we pass into
things the vertex and then a priority which will be zero and then down here will do the same thing.
Opps I hate that and Chrome doesn't give me an easy way to anyway.
All right and done here we'll add infinity.
So for every other node in our queue we're definitely starting with this one because it's zero compared
to infinity.
But then we'll will be updating will be skewing things later with a new priority that isn't infinity.
All right and then the only other thing we have to do for each.
Every single node we need to set previous of that node of that vertex to be null.
So instead of doing that in the IF in the else and duplicating it I'll just do it down here.
So previous of Vertex equals no.
So that gives us our initial state.
We end up with this structure here.
We end up with our priority queue reflecting this as well.
Then we end up with previous where we have a no b no C No.
And will update those as we go.
OK so next after we've initialized everything we now need to basically run some code.
A lot of comment here.
As long as there is something to visit and the way we can write that it's just while nodes dot values
dot length that's one way node is our priority queue and inside the priority queue we're storing values
so we can do dot length that that's fine.
While nodes that values start length and the first thing that we need to do is dequeue our node so start
looping as long as there's anything in the queue dequeue a vertex.
So dequeue should give us the current smallest value in there.
So I'm going to make a variable called smallest but rather than initializing it down here over and over
and re initializing it I'm going to set it up here I'm going to call it smallest and not set it to a
value but define or declare it.
I mean rather than re declaring it I'm going to just set smallest equal to nodes dot dequeue.
So remember from the priority queue video two videos ago it should give us whatever the current smallest
value is in there.
Give us the vertex with the lowest priority and actually we're almost there.
But if we look at what smallest is right here it's not quite what we want.
Factsheet my code smallest is going to be the entire node or this entire object that has the value and
the priority.
What we want really is just the vowel which is going to give us a or b just so we know which nodes we're
looking at.
We don't care about the priority right now anyway.
So now that we have that out of the way we're looking at we're going to have you know a smallest or
B smallest.
We need to do is check is that Vertex the same as our ending vertex.
If if that's the case we're done so I'm not going to actually fill out all the code but I'll just do
a simple check if smallest is equal to what we call R's finish.
If that's the case we'll come back to this but I'll just say we are done and we need to build path to
return.
But if that's not the case what we need to do is loop through each neighbor in the adjacency list for
that vertex.
So if we're looking at a we need to look at each of A's neighbors which includes B and C.
So I'm going to loop over those neighbors and the easiest way to do that smallest is just a variable
that looks like a.
And we have this thought adjacency list so this does a bit adjacency list of a would give us a whole
bunch of it would give us an array containing each edge.
So I'm going to put that instead of a of course I'm not going a hard coded.
I'm going to put smallest in there and I'm going to use a loop over this and I'll do a four in.
So I'll just call for let's call it neighbored.
In this adjacency list of smallest Then we could start by I just counted that logging neighbor.
Nice and simple like that.
And if I rerun my code you see what we're getting here is just a number.
And that's the for loop works because what we're doing here is looping over an array.
If we actually looked at this adjacency list we did that to this data adjacency list.
Hopefully you remember what it looks like one more time we run it.
This is what we're looking at.
So when we loop over A's neighbors we're just looping over 0 and 1 what we want to do from there is
take that number to figure out the actual edge.
So I'm going to make another variable called Let's just call it next node we call it neighbor node or
something equals this data adjacency list of smallest of neighbor and neighbor is just a number.
So now if we consider log next node this will actually give us what we're looking for.
This is each neighboring node.
So now that we have each neighboring node each time through we need to go and calculate.
So a lot to common here that just is basically like find a neighboring node calculate new distance to
neighboring node.
So let's say that we're looking at d currently as neighboring node.
We need to calculate the distance how do we get to D where we had consult previous The shortest path
to D is through C and so we look at what C currently has stored.
And then we add two.
So I know it's kind of difficult to explain without just showing you.
So what we would do.
It's not guaranteed that this is going to be smaller so I'm going to make a variable called I don't
know a candidate candidate and we're going to take our distances of smallest So smallest is whatever
the actual node or visiting is and then we're going to add next node outwait
let's say we're just starting out.
We picked a which is our vertex.
It's the only thing to start with.
It's a minimum item and we look at its neighbor B.
All right.
So what we're going to do is take the weight of B from A to B that edge gives us four.
So we take four and we add it to whatever we have stored for a which is zero.
So that went easy and we put that under B but now let's say we fast forward a bit and we're looking
at let's say keep going.
When we get to church we get to be here.
All right.
So we start with B.
B is our neighbor.
And we look at BT.
Well what are we currently have stored for B is for that represents the shortest distance from A to
B that we know about.
And we add that to the distance from B to E which is three.
And that gives us 7.
So that's what we're going to do.
Candidate equals the current distance for our node plus the distance to the neighbor.
So this distance is smallest would be like the four and then the neighbor value is this edge we're adding
in.
So this is going to be a hopefully smaller but definitely not always that this is now what we need to
compare.
Is this smaller than what we currently have stored for the neighbor.
So then that's next.
We're going to look at if the candidate are new some that we added together is less than what we have
for distances of not smallest but of next node dot note which is a bit of a mouthful there.
But what this is reflecting is the fact that next note looks like this.
It's an object and we need to access next node node which is something like f.
So I walk through this.
It's a lot.
When you think about it this way but if we go back to here what we're doing is basically checking if
I go forward to D as an example.
All right we're looking from D.
T.
Right.
So we start by taking a look at what are we currently have stored as the shortest way to get to D 4
and then we're looking from D D E that's 3.
So that gives us 7 total.
But what we want to compare that to is not 4 because of course it's going to be more than whatever is
at D because we're adding D plus something else.
What we want to compare it to is what's currently at the neighbor.
What's currently at e which is 7.
In this case and it's the same so we ignore it.
But that's what we're trying to do we take wherever we are d we add the current shortest value from
a to d plus this new bit and we compare that to the current shortest for E.
So back here that's what this is we're recalculating a new number this new sum.
This is to d.
This is plus E.
Then we compare that to what we currently stored for the.
All right.
So if that's the case we're now going to update what we stored for.
So next node distance is next node node and rather than doing next no dot node why don't we extract
this into a separate variable.
Let's just call it next neighbor.
Just like that.
And now here I can say next neighbor and same thing down here.
It's a small difference but I don't like having to do this but this run distances next neighbor equals
our candidate.
So this is just the equivalent of updating one of these lines distances of E for example equals seven.
It already is seven.
But imagine if something else we update this value.
All right if you're still with me hopefully this is the only way this really works and makes sense is
if you are able to walk through the diagrams in a couple of couple of years ago.
All right then what we do is we update previous previous is our data structure.
It's this thing here and we're going to say all right the way we got to previous of next neighbor was
through the smallest smallest is going to be D and decs neighbor might be.
This is just updating how we got there.
So to add a couple of comments this is just updating new smallest distance to Naver.
This is updating previous basically how we got to next neighbor to neighbor and then the last thing
we need to do is in queue in priority queue with new priority.
All right.
And that's easy it's just nodes that's the name of our priority queue and queue next neighbor comma
the value which candidate is what we call it.
This is the new sum.
All right.
So then that goes through and that's all we need to do.
As far as the bulk of the logic.
All right so just so we can see if it's working.
We're not returning anything but let's cancel the log distances at the end and let's also consulate
Lague previous that and let's see what happens next neighbor is not defined.
Did I miss two B's.
All right one more time.
That I knew something was wrong.
Oh my gosh.
All right I updated every one of these to be next neighbor with one B.
OK.
So you can see that what we end up with at the end is this set of distances that we've kept track of.
For example the shortest path to get to e takes 6 units.
And if we construct it working backwards from E..
We go to F from f we go to D and D we go to see from C we go to AA.
So we just want to spit out at the very end what I want this to return is basically an array that looks
like a comma and then from a we went to see from C to D from DB We went to F..
And then finally from f we went to e.
So we build it backwards because that's all we have.
We have E..
So we get to F F we go to D D C C do we go to a.
So I'm just going to add them all to an array and just reverse it at the end.
It's just a simple way of doing it.
But that's the return value I want so to make that array that path at the very end I'm going to come
up here and just make a variable called Path and set it to be an empty array.
So I'll just say to return an end.
OK then down here when we actually find what we're looking for when we're done to build up that path
to return at the end I'm going to start we need to use previous.
Right that's what this structure is and we basically need to loop.
So we need to keep looping from E to look at F and then from after like a D and D.
And where do we stop.
Well eventually we get to C C to A and then we look at a and it's no.
So we can do a while loop and this is sort of like traversing any sort of list even though it's technically
an object but it's just a linear path.
So I'm going to do while previous of smallest and I'm going to update what smallest is as we go.
So I'm going to pass up push smallest and then I'm going to say smallest is now equal to previous of
smallest.
So at the beginning smallest will be is at the end of our code running.
But at the beginning of this bit.
So previous smallest e gives us F..
So we push it in.
And now we say smallest is equal to f and then it starts over.
So is there a previous smallest f.
Yes there is.
So we push f right here and then we set smallest to now b d and we keep going until we get to a.
At which point there is no previous.
Of.
Because it's no and we're done.
Now what we need to do is add a break here so that we don't keep looping.
I want to stop this loop because even though we found what we're looking for this loop keeps going while
there are nodes in the priority queue.
And of course there are more nodes in there.
Well it's not of course it's it's possible that the last thing we look at but it's likely that there's
stuff in there.
So we're going to break out.
So that will stop everything.
And then at the very very end if we come down here boy I hate doing this.
Where do we need to go see our loop stops right here.
All right.
So after our loop we're going to do just let's do a constant log of path and see what we have.
And I run it.
All right so we're almost there.
The only thing is that we need to also reverse it.
So to reverse it.
And we want to add in a because a is not in here.
So to get a in there which is our beginning we want a c d f e.
It's pretty simple to fix.
We can just do return path dot.
I mean it concat a in there which is smallest dot reverse.
And if I run my code now there we go a C D F to E and if we tried changing it instead of a to e which
is the shortest path you get from A to C.
Well I went to easy go for me to see how about to F A C D F about 2.
I think they're all pretty simple at this point.
They are all along the same lines a C and D.
And we are done now.
This is a lot of stuff and the code is quite intimidating if you are unable to go through and process
the slides and kind of walk through step by step if you're just trying to learn it by looking at this.
It's really difficult.
But I think that it makes some sense as you go through and step through and understand each time through
what we're actually doing if you write it down with pen and paper.
If you look at what each of these values actually is when we pick the smallest node smallest priority
we add the new total together and we compare it to what we had stored for the neighbor.
And we update potentially if it's smaller.
There's a lot going on.
But if you're able to do that with pen and paper then this should be easy enough.
Well not easy enough.
It should be doable.
Either way this is Dijkstra's and this is our unoptimized version where we're using a priority queue
which is not well.
This priority queues not ideal because it's not implemented with a binary heap.
It's a bit slow because we're sorting the entire array every single time.
If we use a binary heap it's faster.
Remember from that section.
So next up we will fix this up just to make it a little bit quicker.