Welcome back.
In this video we're just going to upgrade our code a bit using a binary heap priority queue.
So this is the priority queue we wrote earlier in the course.
We were doing things like with hospital priority queue.
So I'm going to get rid of that.
I copied it over and not just altering the original.
And we can actually leave everything the same.
So we have NQ and dequeue.
And it's the same interface.
It takes a value in a priority a value in a priority.
So all that we have to do now is just add our code into this.
This file here there is a node class but we don't have to interact with that.
The priority queue does if you have never seen this code definitely recommend to check that out first.
It's a lot going on but it's much faster than doing our naive priority queue here.
Then we'll just take everything else like this.
You know I just deleted it all.
Copy it and move it over here and I'm going to put it up top.
I think that we have the weighted graph class first and then I'll move all of these variables and method
calls down to the very bottom and if we take a look there's a lot of code going on here.
But we have our weighted graph which interacts with the priority queue which is a binary heap.
This priority queue implementation uses a node class and then at the bottom we're creating our graph
we're adding the edges and then finally we're testing it out.
So Moment of Truth and it still works.
If you made it through the binary heap section you should know that this implementation of a priority
queue is much faster than a naive version just using an array even though the binary heap itself is
stored in an array.
The way it works is much more efficient than traditional just sorting the array over and over and over
and picking the minimum value.
All righty.
So that's just upgrading our code a bit.