All right welcome back so I hope everyone made it through the important stuff in the last video.
I get it.
If you skip the introduction the objectives all that stuff.
But it's really important to understand the difference between a binary heap and a binary search tree.
They look similar but they are different.
So here we have a max binary heap 41 is the root.
The two children need to be smaller.
That's really the only rule.
Also notice that we fill in the left first.
So I mentioned that in the last video the left child was added and then a right child.
And then if we were to add a right one here the next child would be added to the left down here.
So we'll come back to that when we actually implement this.
So suppose we wanted to represent this wanting to basically write code to model this just like we've
done with every other data structure we could implement a tree class and a node class and each node
has a left and a right and we could do the same thing we did for a binary search tree but there's actually
an easier way.
So we can actually use a built in data structure an array or a list.
Same thing just different names and different programming languages.
We can use that to store a binary heap and I'll show you how.
OK so there's a little tiny bit of math involved here.
Not much just a little multiplication and addition.
But if we look at this binary heap.
So this is a max binary heap again.
We have 100 up top the largest value and then below it we just have two values that are smaller than
100.
So again we don't have the two next largest numbers.
It just two numbers that are smaller 19 and 36 and then they both have two children.
So it's kind of hard to see in this diagram but if we were to actually expand it vertically we wouldn't
have any space left to show this.
So this down here is our array or list.
We're restoring values.
It's indexed.
So we would have 0 1 2 3 and so on.
So we put 100 we put the root at the first Index index of 0.
Here we go.
I added in the indices down here and then what we can see.
Let's say we want to find the children of 100.
Well we know where they are.
It's the next two values.
The left child is 19.
The right child is 36.
So we have index of zero.
It's children our index of one and index of two.
All right.
Well that part's easy because it's sort of a special case at the beginning.
But now if you wanted to look at the children for let's say 19 Well we have to skip over 36 right.
And if we look at this diagram 19 has two children 17 and 12.
So the 17 is a love child and 12 is the right child.
So we have a parent at index 1.
It's left child is index 3 it's right child does index 4.
OK next let's go to 36.
So we had 36 we have to hop hop frog leap frog over to get to 25 which is its left child and five which
is its right child.
So index of two corresponds to two children at index five and six.
OK.
Where I didn't do this for every single value I promise we're about to skip ahead.
Seventeen though it's children start at index of seven for nine.
An index of eight for 15.
So can you figure out the little mathematical relationship here.
What if you have an index for a parent.
Where are two children located.
Here's one more.
Five is the parent.
Its children are located at index of 13 and 14.
So index of six was was the parent indices index not indices and its left child was 13 its child was
14.
So what's the relationship here.
So for any index an inside of an array the left child is stored at two and plus one and the right child
is at two and plus two.
OK.
So if we take index six for example we find it's children by multiplying that by two and adding one.
So six times to give first 12.
We add one we get 13 so that to the left child we add two or we add one more really we get 14.
So they're side by side or let's take this index 12 sorry this index for the value of 12.
It's children.
We multiply 4 by 2.
8 we add 1.
So that's going to give us 9 in 10.
We had one we had 2 6 and 11.
Is that correct.
Yes.
If you follow this line it's hard 12.
Children are 6 and 11.
So that's the formula to actually find a child based off of a parent.
We take the number to the index and we multiply by two and we add one to get the left.
We had two to get the right and we'll be doing that in our code.
Hopefully the relationship there makes sense.
And you can see how that works and why it works.
If not just we're going to come back to this and you can just add this into your code and just assume
that it works.
But I think if you kind of if you think about it you know there's you know two children per each node
and we need a way to flatten that and store that I can.
Yeah I like this diagram just shrinks it all and smashes into this list and you can see how it works
as you move further and further down.
You have a lot more children anyway.
So the other thing is we can work backwards if we have a child node and we want to know it's parent.
So it's the same exact math relationship.
You just go the other direction.
So if we have a child of six at index of nine its parent is an index of four or if we have index 12
for the child we can figure out that its parent is an index of 5.
And the math for that.
So if we have a child index and we subtract one divide by two and then also we floor it meaning we just
chop off the decimal because we can't have you know point five decimals in as far as an index of whole
integers.
So if we go back and say we're working with 13 right here index 13 the value is 1 to find its parent.
We subtract 1 which gives us 12.
We divide by 2.
Gives us 6 so it indexed 6 we have the value 5.
And that indeed is the parent of 1.
Let's try one more.
How about index of 10.
So at 10 we have this value 11 to find its parent.
We subtract 1 which gives us 9.
Then we divide by 2.
Remember it's one divided by two floored.
So we take ten minus one that's nine.
Divide by 2 4.5.
Well there's no index four point five.
But if we floor it we just chop off the decimal.
We get four right here.
So the value of 12 is that indeed the parents of 11 yes it is.
There it is.
So that's the math that floor part is important because we can't have.
Like I said we can't have four point five as an index.
OK.
So those two things we will return back to you because there will be situations where we have a parents
and we need to find it's children in which case we do two in plus one two and plus two or if we need
to find a parent based off a child and minus one divide by two floored.