All right welcome back.
So here is our base structure for our max binary heap class.
It's very simple.
We are implementing only a max binary heap.
But to change it over to a binary heap or to make a man heap is very simple once you know how to do
Max.
So either one could have for it.
So we defined the class Max binary heap and the only property it needs in the constructor is a values
property.
So values will start as an empty list or an empty array and that's it.
We don't need to make a node class like we did for our other tree.
We don't need to make a note class like we did for length lists.
We don't need previous pointers or next or left or right.
All we need is an empty array to start.
And in this video we're going to walk through how we would add an insert method so that we could say
Max Bryner insert 10 max Bryner insert 50 and we'll just be storing things in this values array just
like I showed you here where we can take instead of having to create a bunch of nodes connect them manually.
We store them in an array and we use their position to model the actual structure the position their
index the individual numbers corresponding to each item's position is what actually gives that the structure
of the heap.
So we'll move things around and swap them.
So to make something something is parent it just goes to the correct index.
So we'll come back to that.
But that's all that we need to store is an array of values.
OK.
So as far as the process to insert something into emacs binary heap it's a little bit more complicated
than a binary search tree but it's still I mean I think it's relatively straightforward but it makes
sense if you think about it it's logical.
So what would you do.
We fill it out from left to right.
So all that honestly means if we have an array like we have here if we were trying to insert something
to the tree the only place for it to go is at the end.
So we just push on to our list.
We just do you know array or list up push the new value whatever it is.
Now of course it's most likely not going to be in the right in the right spot right off the bat.
Let's say we push in 500.
Well that is the largest value in here.
Five hundred is going to need to work all the way up to the top.
So we added to the end and then we do something called bubbling up.
And what that means is basically we swap it until it finds its final correct resting place in a max
binary heap the larger values are going to bubble up to the correct spot.
So what that looks like if we were to step through it if we add 55 to the end of the list to our array.
This is what we're actually storing in our class.
This is just a nice visualization but this is what stored.
Fifty five goes to the end.
That's not the right spot but we just put it there to start.
And that means by putting it here it's index means it is a child of 33.
So this is index of two right here.
So its children are at index 5 and 6 2 times 2 plus 1 2 times 2 plus 2 right.
So this is 0 1 2 3 4 5 and 6.
Those are the two children as we can see here.
It's all set up correctly.
Okay so next we bubble up.
And what that means is we take this node and we compare it to its parent.
So we compare 55 to 33 and we swap them because 55 is larger.
Theres a little swap not quite an animation but you can see it there and the change is reflected here.
So before we had 55 as the child of 33 that was not the correct place we just put it in without caring.
Then we compared it to the parent and we swap.
Then we compare it to the parent again.
How about 41 and 55.
Well we swap them.
So now our data structure looks like this where we have 55 as the root and its two children are 39 and
41.
All is good.
Everyone is happy in the world of our max binary heap because now every node satisfies the property
that its two children must be less than the node itself.
So again we insert and then we bubble up by swapping.
And this is why its important.
When I talked about how you could find a parent based off of a child.
So if we had like we had here fifty five we added to the end we need to find it to parent at 33 and
compare them.
Then we swapped them then we need to find 55 new parent 41 and compare them and we swap them so here's
an animated version on visual.
I'll go figure out a visual.
Whatever it is they give you numbers here so you can see the actual order in the array in the list.
That's underlying it.
So you would read it you know left to right.
This is the first item and second third and so on.
So if we were to insert a value let's say 26 is not going to be exciting let's do about one hundred.
Insert that.
The very first thing we do is add it to the left it the way we added it always goes to fill with the
left first and then the right.
And that's I mean we're using an array.
So just by adding it to the end of the array by pushing onto it it's going to be added here automatically.
OK.
So we start here and then we're going to compare it to its parent 144.
This is a max binary heap.
So we are going to swap them and now we take 100 and compare it to its new parent which is 70.
Well 100 is still larger.
So we're going to swap them.
And now we take 100 and we compare it to 99.
It's larger.
So we swap them again.
And now we're done.
And this is our new max primary heap.
If we entered another value here like 15 it's going to go right there and that's where it stays at least
for now.
If we were to insert another one it goes to the left and it stays there looks to a larger value.
Sure.
Fifty eight we insert to the right.
We swap.
Now we're done.
So again there is no order between the left and right siblings.
There's no shared property other than that they are less than their shared parent in a max binary heap.
OK.
So the pseudocode to do this.
Here's the simple version.
You just write a method called the insert.
It accepts a value.
We're not working with nodes or anything it just accepts a number.
Insert 10.
You add 10 to the end of the values array.
You just push 10 into values and then you bubble it up to its correct spot.
So that's that's the more complicated part it's easy to add it to the end of the tree.
Super easy or the end of the heap to get it to go to the right spot.
So little more work.
So here some more detailed pseudocode.
If you would like to do this all in one method called insert.
You can do that.
You could also write a method called insert which calls another method called bubble up totally up to
you.
But the way bubble up will work.
Once you push the value in to the end of the values the list or the array.
It's at the very end and it's probably in the wrong spot.
It could be in the right spot but it's most likely in the wrong place.
So here are the basic steps you're going to take the item at the last index the end of the array.
The very last thing you added and then you're going to find its parent.
Remember the math that we should that I showed you index minus one divided by two and you floor that.
So that gives you the index of the parent and then you just compare the value at that index compared
to the value that you just added to the end of the array.
And then you see which one is larger.
It's a max binary heap.
If the one at the end we inserted is larger we swap the values.
If it's not then stop you're done.
It's in the right spot and you keep repeating that process as long as the values element at the parent
index is less than the values element at the child index or the other way around as long as the child
is larger than the parent.
Keep swapping.
So you'll swap and then you'll reset the index to now be the parent index.
So you moving in.
Right.
So if we went back to this example the very beginning we add 55 to the end.
We find its parent let's just look down here so we add 55 to the end.
We find it's parent based off of the index we subtract one we divide by two index.
Is this item at the value is 33.
Index is to compare.
Fifty five is larger.
So we swap.
Now the index that we're looking at is this index here too.
And so now we find using that number two we find the parents of two minus one gives us 1 divided by
two gives us one point 0.5 floored it gives us zero.
So the index now that we're comparing it to is index 0 and we compare these two items and we end up
swapping them and then we stop because there is no next index to look at.
There's no parent of this.
So you could add that into your code.
Make sure that it you know accounts for that and it doesn't break or you don't hit it undefined or something.
OK.
So those are the basic steps.
Again insert just pushed to the very end of the list or the array that you're using to store the values
and then bubble up.
And here's a pseudo code for bubble up.
So try it on your own right to method if you prefer or do it all in one insert method in the next video.
Have an implementation.