All right welcome back.
So let's implement insert on our Macs binary heap class.
But first we need to actually define the class.
So I'm going to do that now.
Max binary heap it's super simple at least the skeleton of it is we have our constructor and all we
have is the property values which is an empty array.
That's where we're going to store the heap.
And down here I just have in the comments sort of our initial This is exactly the same representation
or the representation of this data here.
Just so that we can work with it and visualize what's happening.
So the pseudocode we're going to define a method called the answer.
It takes an element or value and the easiest part and we push it on to this of values just added to
the end.
So for example if this is what values looks like if we just pushed fifty five onto the end that's the
first step then we need to do the harder part which is bubble up and I'm going to define a separate
method just to do that just to keep this.
I just personally like it like to do it this way.
You definitely don't have to.
You can do all the logic here.
So I'm going to call this up bubble up which doesn't exist.
So we had to find that bubble up and then in here we'll put the actual logic.
So remember what we need to do is take this item take the index of this item in order to find the parent
which is going to be if this is index of 6 we need to take 6 minus 1 which gives us 5.
Divide by 2 which gives us 2.5 and then a round down or floor which gives us index of 2 which is this.
So let's make a variable to store the element and also its index.
So we're just going to find the last element.
So that's going to be this dot values dot length.
Minus 1 gives us the index so let's make a variable called index.
This will keep track of where the newly inserted item is.
It will start as the last index.
But if we swap we're then going to update index to be here for example and if we swap again we'd update
it to be wherever we swapped with I'm using and cons just to get to include some East 20:15 syntax.
So that's the index.
Let's also going to make a variable just to store the value of the element itself.
So Konst elements of index is going to be changing content will just stay as the element.
So it's going to be this dot values
idea.
This is just an easy way.
I mean we could also make it so that the method bubble up accepts the element and you wouldn't have
to do this.
I'm fine with habitus here.
So we're grabbing the index six in our case.
And when I say in our case actually right now there is no heap that exists.
So I should do that now let's do it.
Heap equals new max binary heap and I'm just going to initialize it a cheat just have it start this
so that we don't have to insert those manually then we're going to call insert fifty five OK.
So if we've just done that we've added 55 to the end for Called we've called bubble up indexes 6.
The element is 55.
OK.
Now what we want to do is loop.
So I'm going to start with just a while true and just continue to loop over and over and over and then
break out at an appropriate time.
So our process is going to be to take this element and compare it to the parent element.
So first we need to find the index of the parent so to calculate that'll make a variable called parent
id x.
Remember the formula if you don't it's over here.
We take the floor of the index minus one divided by two.
So I'm going to do math.
Floor and then we need to add extra parens subtract one first and then divide by two.
OK.
So let parent indexical math up for index minus 1 to get right to and actually let me just get rid of
the loop for just a moment.
Let's just do a that log parent index to make sure that's working.
Run my code.
Three B's that's not correct hopefully you saw that before me try that again.
OK.
So it's giving us to printing out too which is the parent index.
Is that correct.
Let's look at 0 1 2.
That gives us the element 33.
That is indeed the parent of 55.
And if you want to verify that based off of this sort of a visualization you can see.
Thirty three is the parent.
OK.
So now what we want to do is compare the item at this index to our element 55.
Compare those two things.
So we have the index of the element and we have its parent index.
Now let's do a comparison.
So I'm going to make a separate variable to do this because it's a little bit shorter.
So let parent equal values of parent index because we have to we don't have to do a variable right.
We could just compare this but I like to just label it as parents then what are we going to do.
Well if parents can do it either direction if element is greater than parents that means we want to
swap.
So I'm just going to do this that values of parent index equals elements.
So that's putting 55 here.
And then we need to set this start index up the values of index to now be parent.
So that should swap the values at least one time.
We're not looping still.
So and that's only if the element is greater so in our case it is when we insert 55.
Let's just see if it works.
OK.
So let's look at our help now and you can see we have 55 where 33 used to be.
So that's correct.
Now we just need to get it to happen again or keep happening while what.
Well I'm going to keep it as while true for now but I'm going to change my loop a little bit so we're
getting the parent index reading the parent We're checking if the element needs to be swapped.
Then we're swapping.
But if we leave it at this we're going to have an infinite loop that goes forever.
And also we're never updating index indexes always still remaining 6.
So every time through a parent index it's going to be this.
So we're going to be comparing six into those indices over and over and over.
So what we want to do is actually update index to the parent index because if we swapped fifty five
and 33 we now need to look at what's at 55 and find its parent.
So we need to change index to be this the old parent index.
So we're almost there but rather than doing it this way where I'm checking if element is greater than
parent I'm actually going to change my logic entirely.
Well I'm going to flip it on its head and change this conditional to be the opposite if element is less
than or equal to parent.
If that's the case break and then otherwise do this.
So it's just a slightly shorter way of saying that.
So while true forever find the parent index find the parent the value there.
If the element is less than or equal to the parent break we're done.
If that's the case if for example we inserted I don't know 11 compare 11 to its parent 33 we don't swap
were done.
However in the case of 55 first time through this is what we had then we swap so that we end up with
33 here and 55 here and then index.
Now is this.
And parent indexes right here.
So we're working to zero in two and we compare again and we swap again.
So if we actually look at what we get it's still not going to be totally correct.
But if you look at heape you can see that 55.
OK you can see what's happening we've got a swap where at index 2 we have 41.
That's correct.
So we swapped 41 and 55.
So we went from just put them all in a row from this where we had 55 at the end we swapped it to here.
Then we went to this where we swapped 41 and 55 but our code keeps going one more time because it's
trying to compare 55 which is index of 0 and then it's trying to find the parent index which is zero
minus one negative 1 divided by two rounded down or floor down index of negative 1 which is going to
be undefined and it's comparing undefined to 55.
And so you can see it actually does a swap and we end up with 55 at index of negative 1.
So this is a simple fix.
We just want to stop instead of while true let's just say well index is greater than zero because if
index is now zero we know that the element is the largest element.
For example 55 we swapped it.
We swapped it again.
We should stop now.
There's nothing we could swap it with.
So just stop.
Now let's test it out and see if it works.
Now look at our heap.
All right we have 55 there.
Now let's insert something that's not as large.
Let's insert something that that isn't going to be swapped at all.
Let's do like one look at our heape.
Nope not here.
If you look at it you can see right it stays at the end.
Now let's insert something like I don't know.
About 45.
And we look at the heap again.
So we made a swap with 18.
So we it was on the end here we stopped it.
So then 45 was right here and then we did one more swap between 45 and 39.
So we end up with 45 right here.
And that's correct.
And then finally let's just make sure we try and insert something massive that is larger hundred ninety
nine.
It should bubble.
Oh my gosh the same typo again.
It should bubble its way all the way up top.
Let's just look at the values and it does OK.
So that is insert.
Again it's just one way of writing it.
There are many possible variations but they all follow the same idea where you insert it at the end
and then you bubble it up to the correct spot.