Hey welcome back.
So we've seen how to insert nodes or elements into a heap.
Now let's talk about the opposite.
Removing things the standard place the the one area we usually remove from is the root.
So in emacs binary heap that means removing what it means with root in either case.
But it means removing the maximum element the highest value and in a binary heap it means removing the
lowest value the minimum.
So the method we define We could call it remove.
We can also call it extract maximum or extract Max and that's pretty common to see that.
So when we go on to implement a priority queue for example where each element is assigned a priority
level and we want to remove things based off of their priority level.
Well the highest priority in emacs binary keep at least will always move up to the top and so that's
where we'll remove from in our priority queue.
I can't speak well always take that route out.
It will be the highest priority item anyway.
The way it works is similar to insert where we can't just remove this and do what we can't just leave
it.
Of course we have to have a new route but then we can't just put some we could swap with any element
and just put it there.
But it's most likely going to be wrong.
It's not going to be you know that the correct compact heap.
So what we do is we remove this element and we swap it or we put the the current last value.
This is a standard way of doing it.
The last value 12 in our case would go here and then we adjust.
Which I've always heard as sink or sinking down.
But I was looking at Wikipedia.
There are many terms for it.
The procedure for deleting the root from the heap effectively extracting the max element in a max heap
or the minimum element in a min heap and restoring the properties so making sure everything is all kosher
again is called down heap aka bubbled down percolate down sifted down trickle down down cascade down
and extracts min and max.
Nowhere did it actually say sink down.
Which is what I've always heard so I was a little bit offended by that.
They have so many options but my life is a lie.
There is no sink down.
It's the same idea though right.
So we had bubble up which was when we had an element at the end.
There is an end in the incorrect spot.
It's the last item and we bubble it up to the correct spot.
Well in this case what we're going to do is put an element at the root that is most likely wrong and
have it bubble down sink down sifts down trickle down whatever to the correct location.
So for example if this is what we start with Nothing's been removed yet.
But if I want to remove the root I call extract Max is what what are element or what are methods.
It's going to take 41.
Remove it from this array or this list and then take 12 and put it in place.
So we end up with this.
We removed 41 and 12 goes to the beginning and so we end up with this structure which is not correct
at all.
So the next step is to then call whatever you sink down or sit down and we compare it to its children.
We take 12 and we look at its two children.
We take whichever one is larger which 39 is and then we're going to swap.
Assuming that 12 is indeed less than 39.
Meaning that 39 deserves or should be the new route.
More than 12.
So if that's the case which it is.
We swap.
OK so now that 39 is in the correct spot we go back to 12 and we compare it to a new child or both new
children actually.
And we're going to swap it with the larger one.
If one of them is larger.
If both of them are smaller than more in the correct spot and we don't need to swap.
But in this case both are larger.
So we're going to swap 12 and 27 and would do just that and we're done.
12 has now sunk down to its correct location which is basically at the very end again.
It's just that it used to be over here on the left because we had an extra node but we removed that
node and so it had to swing its way down to the correct spot.
But now everything is happy again in our binary heap.
So let me show you one more slightly better animated example on visual algo visual go they call it extract
Max.
It's not called remove but if I call it step backwards it removes that root which is 70 and it's going
to swap.
It's not actually a swap it's going to replace it with the last element 31 so 31 gets up there.
And obviously that's that's wrong.
It's not the largest elements not the max.
So we compare it to the left and the right.
And both of them are larger but 67 is larger than 65 so we're going to swap there.
Now 67 is the new route it's the new maximum a maximum element.
It's in its correct spot.
It's cemented in.
Now we do the same thing.
We compare it 31 to 45 and to 58.
Both of those are larger.
We're going to swap it with a larger one which is 58.
There we go.
Now there are no children left.
We have nothing to swap it with.
And so it's in the correct spot.
And then we would presumably return 70 which was what we removed.
Right.
That's the whole point.
We're removing the Macs and we probably want to return it one more time just for good measure will go
faster this time.
What was the Hellmann up top.
Sixty seven.
All right we remove it.
We replace it with 15 and now we compare.
All right.
Sixty five is largest.
So now we swap there.
Now we have 15 and 40 and 53.
We swap a 53 because that's the larger one.
And now it's at the that its final resting place.
It doesn't go anywhere else.
All right.
So here's the pseudo code.
If you want to try and implement it right a method on our class or Max binary heap called you could
call it remove or I'm going to call it extract Max or extract the maximum.
It doesn't take any arguments you call it.
And what it is going to do is just return the root the old root.
But also it's going to delete that root and update the tree or technically the heap.
So you can follow the pseudo code if you want.
You don't have to do this line for line but basically take the first value and swap it with a last one
then remove that last one.
Use pop so that we get the old root.
So we're going to have the root swap it with the last item and then pop the last item.
But effectively take the first item out and then replace it with the last item.
Then you have to get to the sink down portion.
This sifts down percolate down.
Basically start at the root index start at zero.
Start with a little counter or an index variable and find the index of the left child and the right
child for that index.
So for zero it's easy.
Right we know that if an element is at location 0 it's first child it's just location 1 and index 2
is the right child.
But basically do this math two times index for us one two times and X plus two and take those two values
that you find the two children then take those children and compare them to the element at the parent.
The first element the new route.
And if one of them is larger you're going to swap.
However I'd take note that if both the left and the right children are larger than the parent then swap
with a largest child.
This we we saw over here.
If I step backwards when we swapped 15 up top we compare it to 58 and 65.
Both are larger.
But you're going to swap with 65.
And then after you swap if you do swap the child that you just swapped with that index becomes the new
parent index and then you look for its new children and you repeat the process you loop and keep swapping
loop and swap until neither child is larger than the element which means that you've successfully sunk
down that element that you put at the root and needs to sift its way down to the correct spot and then
at the very end returned the old root.
That's the whole the whole point that should be the maximum.
So give this one a shot again remember the math here it's two times index plus one two times index plus
two to find the left and right children given a parent index.
Take that.
Find those children compare both children to the element that is now at the root and then swap if you
need two.
And then you kind of shift your window over so that instead of looking at the root You're you're looking
at you know the new index and looking at its children and you keep going until there's nothing to swap.
All right.
So give it a shot extract Max.
I'll have a solution.
Up next.