All right.
Welcome back.
So let's go ahead and implement extract Max or remove whatever you want to call it to remove the maximum
element in our maxed binary heap.
So I'll define our method extract.
Max no arguments and we basically have going back to her pseudocode a couple of basic steps.
We want to take the first element and remove it and replace it with the last element.
So there's a you know there's a couple orders you could do that and I think what I'm going to do is
first store the value of the max.
So I'm going to call it Max just equal to the first value this values zero.
So that gives you the first element.
Like suppose we had I don't know 55.
Yeah sure.
Just coffee this one.
If this is what we have I'm going to take Max instead of equal to 55 but it's still in there.
Then I'm going to pop the last item off.
So I'll call it.
And this values pop.
So that gives me and then I'm going to take and which is now not there to a variable and I'm going to
put it here.
So I just set this values zero equals and.
OK.
So that puts 12.
Here what was it 12.
Yes.
That puts 12 right there and removes it from here and now 55 is in max.
So at the end we do want to return Max returned Max.
But of course 12 is not at the correct spot.
We now need to start that bubbling down process or whatever simmering percolating down.
Yeah.
OK.
So there is one edge case here that will come back to me make a note of that.
So don't forget.
OK.
So once we swap after this point.
So this is putting the removing the first element the max replacing it with the last element which is
almost definitely not the max.
Now we need to do the whole bubble down thing whatever you want to call it.
Yeah trickle down.
OK.
So I'm going to define a method to do that.
I'm going to call it this doesn't sink down just like I did with over here.
Bubble up.
I'm going to just make a separate method.
OK.
So instead of trickle down I guess I'm going to sink down.
So over here I'm going to define sink dink down sink down.
Again no arguments.
You could write this too except actually an index.
It's possible that you would want to you know something in the middle you want you swapped it or you
want it to sink down or you didn't remove from the beginning although that's pretty rare.
But I'm just going to make it start at the top element always and sink down from there.
The first the index of 0.
So I'm going to start with an index variable.
So index is going to equal.
I don't even mean anything it's just an equal zero.
It starts as the very beginning.
So if this is what we're working with and let's say that we just put 33 here this is what we're working
with needs to sync down.
We're going to start an index of zero right there.
And now we're going to find it's children.
I'm also going to define a couple of other variables here.
Equal to the length of the array so I'm going to call it length.
Just said that to be just values tell it like this is going to help me shorten my code a little bit.
And also I'm going to do one more for the element itself so I can have the value
like this or I could actually just set that to be zero.
So rather than you know having to write this to check the element I'm going to do this value zero.
So it's just going to be equal to 33 at the beginning and I'm going to stay at 33.
We might be moving where 33 is but the element it's always 33.
That's what we're trying to position that number 33.
OK.
So I'm going to loop while true and at some point I'm going to break out but that's going to be a little
ways from now because we have to start with our main logic which is we found the parent index.
Let's find the two children on the left and the right children two times index plus one two times index
plus two.
So let's start by computing left child index left child index let's do id x equals two times Id X plus
1.
And then I'll duplicate that line for right child index but instead add two.
So the first time through We're talking about zero it's children are here and here.
But we're talking about 39 children.
We're going to multiply that index one by two.
So like you just to let me add one index of three.
So it's child here and here.
OK so this gives us the two child indices.
I'm also now going to make variables to store the value at those indices but I can't just right away
say that I couldn't do left.
Child equals this values.
Left child index.
And the reason for that is that there's no guarantee I could do the same thing for right.
There's no guarantee that I'm going to find an element there.
There's the potential that this is out of bounds.
For example 41 right here has one child at 12.
But if we calculated the index for it's right child it's out of bounds and if I tried to access it I
would get an error.
So we need to make sure it's valid.
And I did this right here make sure it's not out of bounds.
So I'm going to do that before we actually access the value.
I'm going to just for now just initialize or declare left and right but leave them or call them left
child and right child and just leave them empty.
OK.
One more variable I'm going to make and this variable is going to keep track of.
If we did any swaps in this loop and at the very end if there were no swaps so I'm just going to say
if swap is no we're going to break.
So this is our condition at the very end to get out of the loop if we never swapped.
So at some point we're going to set swap equal to true or just something else but not yet.
OK.
Now we have those variables out of the way.
Let's start with the left side.
The first thing I want to do is check is this index in-bounds.
So if left child index is in bounds and that's easy we can just say if it's less than the length if
it is greater than the length or equal to it then it's out of bounds.
So if it's a valid index we're then going to set left child this variable that has no value right now
to equal the value at that index.
OK.
So for this case we start with 33.
We calculate left and right child and debt indices.
So the left index is the number one.
So we check is one less than the like.
That's.
Yes that is.
So we're going to set the variable left child to be this set of values of 1 which is 39.
So now we have 39 in a variable and what we're going to do is compare it to 33 which is our element
and that's easy we just check if left child is greater than the element then we're going to set swap
equal to left child index.
This is this variable swap is going to keep track of the position that we're going to swap with.
So for example in this situation 33 in the incorrect spot.
We compare it to 39.
And at the beginning it looks like this is where we're going to swap it to.
But then we also compare it to 41 and it turns out oh wait 41 is actually the larger number we're going
to swap it with this with index too.
So we're going to keep track of that index with this variable swap and we're going to reset it to know
every time through.
So that if we don't find a number larger is the only time that we're swapping or setting it to anything
other than no is when we find a large number.
If there is no child left or right left nor right I guess that is larger than swap will stay no.
And then we'll break out.
OK.
So that's the left side.
Now we need to do the right side same sort of thing if.
Right.
Child index we got a check if it's if it's a valid index before we try to access it.
We're going to set right child equal to this values right.
Child's index.
OK.
So that gives us the value like 41.
Now we compare 33 and 41 is that right child greater than element.
But there's a little extra logic here because remember we only want to swap with the value that is largest
of the two.
So in our case between these two the right child is largest.
So this would work fine if right child is greater than the element.
It's the last thing we check the left first and then the right.
But imagine that it was the opposite which is ignoring the fact that this may not be a valid tree or
I mean let's say that this is what we had if we're trying to compare this to 41.
OK.
So we we decide this is larger We're going to swap to here.
But then we look at the right child.
All that we're doing is comparing 33 and 39.
Well this is larger than 33 swap here.
But remember we want to swap with the largest of the two.
So I'm going to change just a little bit to say if we haven't already swapped meaning if the left child
was not charged with an element.
So that would be if swap is equal to nor still and right child is greater than the element.
But there's also another scenario that this doesn't cover which is when the right child and the left
child are both larger than the element.
But the right child is largest.
So to cover that because that means that swap is set to the left already.
So that would be like in this scenario where thirty is larger than 33.
So we set swap to be this index of one but 41 is actually the largest the right child.
So I'm going to add a second condition in here where we're going to say or if swap is actually set to
something and at the same time the right child's is larger than the left child.
And this is kind of a gross little statement here so we also need parents around this entire thing.
I like parentally so I'm going to do it like this and indent so that we can read it a bit better.
So these are the two conditions where we end up setting swap equal to right child index because either
the left child never was set.
So swap was never set to the love child.
None of this was true.
So swap is no.
But the right child is larger than the element or swap is nominal meaning that the left side was set
to be swapped but the right child was left is larger than the left child oh boy it gets tough talking
about this stuff sometimes.
So if that's the case we're going to set swap equal to right child index this whole little conditional
here I shouldn't say little this long conditional is checking to make sure that the right child is the
one we're swapping with like we have in this case versus in this case we're going to swap with the left
child.
OK.
So at the end of the day at this point swapper should be set to the left or the right child index or
no.
And if it's still not the end that means we're done.
So we have this if swap equals no break otherwise.
If this doesn't run it means that swap is either left or right index.
Then we need to actually do the swap.
So the swap is going to be this stock values index which we haven't seen in a while.
Remember it started at zero.
So this is the current this is the index of the thing we're looking at 33 to start.
In our example OK so this stock values index equals the stock values of swap.
Now swap is going to be an index.
It's either the left child index or the right child index.
So it's either this or this.
OK so that's part of the swap.
Then we have to do the other part of values of swap equals elements which we already saved in a variable.
So we basically say all right the thing that was here is now equal to 41.
And now this index we're putting 33.
So we swapped the two.
OK.
And the final thing we have to do is update the index.
Keep looping and swapping out this part of the child index you swap to now becomes the new parent.
So here we just set index equals the thing we just swaps to so that if we started with this and we swapped
41 and 33 now our index that we're starting out is here and we're looking at the children that correspond
to index of two rather than zero where we started.
Now index is set to two.
So then we calculate the children which is going to be two times two plus one.
So index of 5 3 4 5 and then index of 6 which doesn't exist.
So that's why we have this check in here to see if those exist and we keep going.
OK.
Let's test this out if it works.
It's kind of a lot of code to move this down or get rid of that.
I'll come back to this edge case in just a moment.
So we insert.
This is what it looks like at the beginning.
I may run the code see if any.
No typo so far.
OK.
Now let's try and do a heap of extract max.
So we get 55 which is the max.
And what does he that values look like.
OK.
So if we look at it we took 33 and put it here.
Remove that from the end and we got rid of 55 and we compared it to it's two children.
We should have swapped 33 and 41.
That's correct.
And then we look at 33 children and there's only one child to compare it to.
Which is this child.
And we don't swap.
And so we're done.
And that's what we got 41 39 33 18 27 and 12.
Let's try one more let's look at values again.
So we took 41 out and we replaced it with 12 here and then we repeat the process which means that we
swapped 39 and 12 and then we look at 12 and compared to its children well it has two children which
are 18 and 27 and we swap it with 27 the larger of the two.
So 12 and up back here 27 ends up right there.
And there we go.
So this is now what we ended up with 39 Tony 7:33 18:12.
OK.
Now the edge case I was talking about if I keep extracting Max how many are left in there.
OK here we go.
If I try and do it on the last one it should be empty now.
But if we look at it it still has 12 and I extracted again I could do it many times and it's still a
set to 12.
What's happening is just a little bloop up here where if there's only one item left we are basically
popping it off and then reinserting it because if this is what our list looks like with the number 12
we're saying all right the max is equal to 12 then the end is also equal to 12.
So pop it off and save it in a variable called.
And then we're adding this up values of zero equals.
And so we're putting it back in there which we don't want to do.
So we only want to do this.
We only want to add it back in and sink down if there's anything in there we should leave it empty otherwise.
So let's just add an if and just say if this stock values that length is equal to or let's just say
is greater than zero.
Then we'll run this code.
Otherwise we're not going to because it's empty and we don't want to mess it up.
OK.
Let's see if it works now.
So we have our help and I'm going to do a extract Max and keep doing that.
OK.
And now we hit the values and it should be empty.
And it is.
And every time I try and call it we get undefined and that's good that's how it should work.
If I do an insert that get hyped up values again we have 10 in there.
Let's do one more here.
Insert ninety nine.
It should be in front.
OK.
Perfect.
It's working great.
That's the basic way of writing things down.
You can also do this recursively which I chose not to do here because I feel like just confuses a lot
of students.
But you can find some nice recursive solutions share some if you have something that's more succinct
which is not that hard to do.
This is pretty verbose but I wanted to make it sort of step by step easy to look at and understand rather
than focusing on just making it super brief Anyway that is the process to remove the root whether it
is a max or a man.
You know we would have to change a couple of things to make it a man binary heap as far as the comparisons
because we want to look to see if something is greater rather than smaller or the other way around.
But other than that it's the same general approach.
So you take the lot you take the first item you take it out you swap it with the last item and then
you sink it down.
OK I know it's a lot.