All right we'll come back so early on I think it is the first video in the section I talked about why
you should know or care about binary heaps.
Yeah they come up in interviews.
Yes they're taught in pretty much every computer science course but also they're used really commonly
to implement something called a priority queue.
And I gave it a five second rundown of what a priority queue is.
And I said we'd come back to it later.
We are now doing just that.
We're coming back to it.
We're going to explain in more detail what a priority queue is.
Give some use cases for it but then also implement one using our binary heap code.
So we don't have to write a ton of new code.
It's really just modifying what we've already done or duplicating it and changing a few things.
So that's what we're going to do here.
But first let's just understand what a priority queue is.
So according to Wikipedia it's just a data structure where each element has a priority associated with
it and elements with higher priorities are served before elements with lower priorities.
So we have a collection of data in each node.
Each element has a priority associated with it and we want to basically be served that's passive voice
say Yes you want to retrieve.
We're going to take one element at a time out of this list or this structure whatever we're using to
store it.
We want one thing at a time that we're going to tackle next.
Just like in an emergency room at a hospital you have a bunch of people waiting everybody's assigned
internally at least some sort of priority level and then a nurse or doctor comes out and retrieves one
person at a time based off of that priority level.
So you know somebody who walks in with a gunshot wound is going to be seen before somebody with a scratchy
throat for example.
So any time you need to manage data or information of varying priority and have things you know that
you're inserting and they may not be the lowest priority you're not inserting things in order.
You might be adding something in like in the E.R. example someone walks in with a gunshot wound.
Well there could be 100 people who were there first but they all have the flu.
The person with the gunshot wound is going to be seen first.
So a priority queue should account for that.
It always serves the highest priority element.
Here's a more real world example on Unix machines well on every machine.
There's there's a bunch of processes processes happening behind the scenes.
You know thousands of different things that are running behind all the magic of your computer and you
can view it or view a lot of them at least on a Unix machine by typing the command.
And I've added in some additional options but what it's showing me here is the process id and then here
this is it's technically not called priority it's called nice but it is a priority level and you can
see that are pretty much all the same.
But then we have certain things that have a higher level or higher nice value which actually means a
lower priority Im pretty sure.
So if zero all of these are going to be basically served in the order that they are added in but then
occasionally there is something.
Is or anything else come on those.
There you go.
Area.
This thing has a nice level of 10.
Its just a priority or same thing here.
This is another thing for Adobe apparently.
So I am not the person to explain how this all works.
I know very little about you know the underpinnings of your operating system and what's happening behind
the scenes.
I basically know how to find one of these and stop it if it's broken.
And that's about it.
But what I'm trying to illustrate is that there's a ton of things happening at any given point on your
machine but at the end of the day there is an order.
They're not just all going at the exact same time.
Things are being served are being worked on in an order and there's a priority that each element gets
which is used to determine that order.
Another thing worth knowing is that priority queues are separate from heaps.
They are just an abstract concept you could implement a priority queue with an array or a list which
I'll show you in just a second.
It's not a great version.
Slow but it's possible.
It's just like when we say list the idea of a list.
Well you could have a list as a linked list.
You could have a list implemented as an array.
There are different ways of implementing them.
It's just a generic sort of abstract concept a priority queue.
So you could go about it like this.
You could use an array or a list and just store things as they come in.
So something's inserted you put at the end or at the beginning and then when you need to remove something
when it's time to you know serve the next item you would just iterate over the entire thing and just
check what's the highest priority keep a variable restart.
OK priority 3 that's the highest.
And then we we hit one.
Also it's worth noting oftentimes a lower number actually denotes a higher priority.
So in this case if we're working for the lowest number we would start here.
OK the lowest number is three.
Then we get to 1.
OK well that's lower So this is our new element that we're going to serve.
But let's keep going.
Nope.
This is still greater.
This is greater.
This is greater than we hit the very end and we realized Alright this is the highest priority thing
we're going to serve.
The lowest number the highest priority.
So that's not a great approach because every single time we need to search something new.
Have to go all the way through and compare you know something to every single item because it could
be at the very last note it could be at the very first item.
It's not a nice way of doing it.
It's simple but it's naive.
So as you've already probably surmise we're going to use a heap.
So here's an example of how we could do it.
This is using a hospital sort of metaphor emergency room people walk in and they have different injuries.
So at first he is empty.
There's one person who walks in with a low fever so they're going to be the next person to get help.
We always remove from the top or from the root of our heap.
Right now there's only one element.
It is the root.
So they get help first.
But let's say that before they get helped someone else walks in they have a concussion.
That is a higher priority element or value.
Right.
They need to be seen before someone with a low fever or a high fever.
That's up for debate.
A low fever though I think they can wait.
Just take a little Tylenol.
What is that Motrin whatever you take.
So they the person with the concussion or the next to get help now they are the root.
Someone else walks in and they have a lower priority.
Well we don't put them at the root.
It's a heap so this value is less than this priority.
So they're going to be below it.
It's a child of this parent.
So we're still following the rules whether this is a man tree or men heap or a max heap it doesn't really
matter as long as we're consistent.
So what we end up with is that concussion is going to be served there the next person to get help but
then someone comes in off the street with an exploded head.
It's not good.
And they need help immediately.
So when we insert something with a higher priority like this it's going to remember how this works.
We add it to the end and then we bubble up in our heap.
So if we added it here we bubble it up to the top.
We end up with exploded head with the red priority is the next thing to get help then concussion is
his first child.
Then the drunk person then the low fever.
But really all that matters is what the next thing is.
And then someone else comes in they have the flu.
Well they're not as high a priority as an exploded head.
So we're just going to put them here for now.
So then let's say the exploded head person gets help.
So what happens when we remove this node from our heap.
And remember what we do is we swap it with the last node and then we have it sink down to the correct
spot.
And this is what we end up with.
So now our heap is serving somebody with the next highest priority person with a concussion.
And if we were to remove this one again we would end up with a new route as the flu.
So everybody who has a yellow priority will be served before I went to that green priority.
Anyone with the red priority is served before everyone else.
Anyway that's kind of a convoluted explanation but that's how a priority queue works when you use a
heap.
All that we care about is the top level element the minimum or the maximum thing and every time we add
something in that could potentially be updated every time we remove something we always remove from
the top.
And so there's going to be a new element there that wasn't there before.
So he works really well because insertion and removal are they have a time complexity of log and compared
to if we just did this naive version if we had a million let's say a thousand elements in here every
time we wanted to remove something if there was no order to them we were just comparing every single
priority to find the lowest or the highest.
We're working with 0 of end time complexity.
So if there's a thousand elements we're talking about a thousand comparisons roughly.
So that's not good.
That's not a good version.
It would work but free is a heap.
It's much faster.
OK.
So that's an explanation into what a priority is or priority queue is using a heap.
But again you can implement them in other ways but a heap is a classic one on Wikipedia it goes as far
as to say that many people confuse the two or conflate the ideas because a priority queue is so commonly
done with a heap.
But again it is an abstract concept.
You can implement it in many ways.
All right so next up I'm going to give sort of my overview the pseudo code for how we could implement
our own.
And then after that I'll have a solution.