All right.
So if you want to try and implement the priority queue class using what we've already learned about
binary heaps it's very very similar.
We just have to change the comparison to tiny tiny little bit.
So make a class called priority queue.
Basically you could just rename your binary heap class just copy it so you can if you want to save the
original.
Change it to priority queue.
We're still keeping a list of values and that's that's all we need structurally aside from all the methods
we just need to store the value so that's unchanged really aside from the name.
What is different though is we're not just storing numbers like we were in the past where we stored
numbers and we just use the values of the numbers and compared.
We didn't have a class we didn't have individual items that we were storing.
We had numbers but we didn't have a secondary class like node which we are going to with our priority
queue because now each element has a value or each node has a value and a priority.
Oops I spell this out right probably.
I guess that is right.
I mistakenly thought I spoke wrong anyway.
So we have this node class and each node will look something like this.
We have a value it could be a string it could be a number it could be something else.
It doesn't matter because we're not using the value to compare.
We're only using the priority.
So each node has a priority and that's the value that we use when we actually construct and rearrange
the heap.
If something is inserted we are going to compare its priority to the other elements priorities.
Once we remove something from the top we need to sink down.
You know a new element to the correct spot.
We're going to compare using its priority.
Also just for some variety here we are going to implement a min binary heap rather than a max.
We've done everything as emacs often as like in the case of a hospital.
Also with the way that Unix the nice values work a lower value is going to be served first.
So in this case priority one is the highest priority.
Two is a medium priority three is a low priority.
So in the hospital at least some that I've been to the most critical emergency things are like Level
0 level 1 and the most or the least critical or level 5 or something like that.
OK so we have two classes now a priority queue class and a node class.
Each node has a value which doesn't matter for what we're doing.
We just need to initialize it and a priority and that's important.
OK so here's how it should work.
Write a min binary heap so all that means to make it a min heap you're going to need to change that
comparison a little bit.
Where in the past we were swapping things if one thing was greater than something we now swap if one
thing is less than or vice versa.
Otherwise it's the same idea.
So each node has a value in a priority.
Use the priority to build the heap as something is inserted.
Compare the priority as something is removed compare the priority then to methods rather than an insert
method and an extract Max.
We're going to Riskin them as NQ and dequeue.
Honestly the naming doesn't really matter but you do need to change in your code is that when you insert
something into an already mentioned you compare the priority of eval you don't compare the value of
the element itself.
You compare the priority when you remove something you're going to remove the root of the heap.
The toplevel thing which is the highest technically the lowest number but the highest priority.
We remove that and then we have to have you know we swap it with the last element we have it sink down
or percolate down.
Compare using the priority.
So that's our goal.
Give it a shot in the next video.
I'm just going to take our code we've already written and alter it so you won't have to watch me that
you know reconstruct the entire heap over like half an hour of code.
We'll just take what we've done and just turn it upside down a tiny bit to make it a priority queue.