All right welcome back.
So let's implement our priority.
Q By copying what we've already done.
So here's my max binary heap.
I just copied it into a new file and I'm going to first change the name priority queue and we're going
to leave it as values.
Then at the bottom or somewhere else I'm going to define our class Node and node and the constructor
takes in a value called vowel and we just set this dot Vau equals Val and then we also have.
It also takes a priority.
We did not add that and there we go.
OK.
So now we have each node has a value and an associated priority.
Now we have two things we really need to do.
The first is make sure we're comparing based off of priority everywhere rather than value or while not
even value rather than just the element itself.
Because we used to not be using this node class at all.
We used to just in certain things as is so when we insert something we're not just going to insert an
element we're going to insert something.
So we're going to take a value and a priority and then we're going to make a new node.
So let's do new node equals new node Vau and priority.
And then we're going to pass that in this value used up push instead of element it's new node.
So that's going to add it to the very end.
And then we need it to bubble up which is what we have here.
So that's all good.
But then when we look at bubble up we have a small prop Well it's more than a small problem.
Our code isn't going to work at all because we're not using priority.
We're just comparing values directly.
So index is going to be the same element is fine while the index is greater than zero parent index.
This is all fine but we want to compare if element dot priority is less than or equal to parent priority.
Well break otherwise the values.
OK.
And that's all the same if we are trying to make this a man.
So I'm actually going to leave this first as a max binary heap and we'll come back to that.
But just note this is going to need to change.
The other thing I forgot to do is change this to B and Q Which doesn't really matter.
That's not how you spell it isn't it.
I can never remember.
I think that's it.
Yes and no D'Errico.
So enqueue bubble up.
All right.
And then instead of extract Max are going to have the Q I think that's right I hope.
And we're going to see we're going to remove the zero element.
Where we're going to swap.
That's all fine.
Then we're going to sink down.
So in sink down we are taking the element that's all fine the indices everything is good here.
But now what we need to check is right here if left child dot priority is greater than element dot priority
if and then same thing over here right here right.
Child priority greater than element of priority.
Same thing one more time left Schild dot priority.
OK.
So remember right now this is a max binary heap still first I might have forgot something let's just
make sure it works.
So we're going to make a new We'll call it.
Let's say were in the hospital so we'll call it E.R. equals new priority queue.
And then we're going to do E.R. dot instead of insert.
It's now in Q and the first thing we'll have is I don't know how about just common cold.
The priority if we're doing a max binary heap how it is right now this will be a low number like let's
say 1 and then let's do a couple more.
Let's also do.
How about gunshot wound.
It's going to be a priority of like five.
And then we'll also have some high fever will be a priority of two.
OK so let's try running this.
And if we look at our E.R. first let's just check out the order.
OK.
So you can see gunshot wound than its first child is is common cold that second child has high fever.
That part doesn't matter.
Right.
And it's not going to be in order with only three elements most likely but it will rearrange.
Hopefully when we do.
So let's check our dequeue we would expect to get gunshot wound.
All right.
Next we expect to get high fever which you did and then common cold and then nothing.
OK.
So that's working.
We have a max binary heap where we're getting elements you know based off of the largest number the
priority if we wanted to switch it around.
It's just a matter of coming up here and changing these less than signs to a greater than sign.
Same thing where else is the other one here.
Change that to a less than sign or just reversing our logic.
And one other change we should make right here.
Instead of calling this variable Max that we're removing it now refers to the men.
It doesn't actually make a difference functionally but it's just nice to call it men instead.
OK so let's do our same thing except now I'm going to change these priority numbers because something
like a gunshot wound will have priority level one high priority a cold maybe you will have like five
high fever will get priority of for let's do a couple more let's do a common cold.
How about gunshot wound.
I don't know.
Broken arm.
So that will be pretty high priority but not the same as a gunshot.
So let's give that priority of two.
And then also let's do another priority of let's do three.
So middle priority not that bad let's say like glass in foot.
I don't know.
OK.
I don't know if this ordering actually makes sense because I'm going to run the code and we're going
to do our first dequeue And what would we expect.
Well we want the value that has the lowest priority gunshot wound.
All right that worked.
Next we expect the value with the next lowest which is broken arm then glass and foot then high fever
then common cold.
So you can see that it doesn't matter what order we inserted them in.
It's all about the priority and it's giving us the highest priority element or the lowest value priority
but the highest actual priority at any any moment and it's a binary heap.
Now it's logically the same thing we just change some comparisons and renamed variable from Max to min.
Otherwise it's the same idea.
Now one thing that we should consider is what if something has the same priority.
If there are two elements in here with the same priority.
Well right now our code doesn't guarantee that they actually would be returned based off of insertion
order so that you know.
Q So you would expect it for example of someone with a common cold got there first and then we have
another person who has you know another common cold.
Same priority level you would expect to serve or help this person first.
And you can add logic to make that work.
But by default with our help it's not going to work that way or there's no guaranteed order between
siblings between things that are on the same level of a tree.
All of a heap.
Technically a tree but in our heap It's just that a parent has a relationship with its two children.
But the two children aren't necessarily the siblings aren't in a particular order.
So what we could do is add logic basically to add in a time here so we could do like this diet.
I don't know insert time equals date now or something like that.
And then when we're comparing instead of just comparing the priority we would also say if the priority
is identical which one of these was inserted first and then we would swap based off of that.
But that's not really that important at this point because the actual algorithm for your prior to cue
the comparison itself will likely change if you're ever actually writing one in the real world.
It's usually not just you know a priority level it might be a priority level.
Plus like how many resources it takes up or how resource intensive it is Plus how long it spent waiting
these different things that might impact the comparison rather than just a direct priority versus priority.
Anyway here's our priority queue.
It's a binary heap that's powering it.
Or that we're actually implementing it with you inserted things using enqueue in whatever order they
go in.
It doesn't matter.
It's based off of their priority level.
Pretty nifty I think.
Much much better than trying to do this with an array or a list and just traversing the entire thing
to find the next item with the lowest or highest number.
This is much faster.
We're going to talk about big-O but it is log and for time complexity for insertion and removal.
All right prior to Q done.