Welcome back.
Let's wrap up with by Mary heaps by talking about how they perform their Big-O notation mainly for time
complexity so binary heaps both min and max heaps are great.
When we're talking about insertion and deletion that's really what they excel.
They're very fast big-O of log in for time complexity.
So remember from a binary search tree that is very quick when we compare it to all the other sort of
standard Bigos that we've seen.
So all the way down here and this sort of light green not the dark green but the light green So as and
grows the amount of time that it takes to insert or to remove something from a binary heap grows slower
it goes grows at the rate of log and approximately.
So let's talk about why that is.
So first remember when we say vog and it's actually log based to have an is what it's really referring
to although that doesn't actually matter because we're just kind of referring to this general trend.
But if we think about it that way and we talk about a binary heap we're talking about log based to events.
Well each time we go down a step in a binary heap or just any binary tree structure we have two times
the number of nodes we have one node than 2 and 4 then 16 and so on.
So let's focus on insertion if we want to insert the number 200 into this heap worst case which we know
is true actually because it's it's the largest number.
It's going to end up over here but along the way we only have to compare it one time per row right one
time per level of this heap.
So we compare it to the first parent which is nine because remember everything is inserted on the left.
So 200 is going to be a child of this 9 element.
So we compare it.
That's one comparison we compared to a parent to comparisons.
Again three comparisons.
And then the fourth comparison and then at this point we realize OK well 200 is the largest element.
If this is a max binary heap it needs to be the root.
So that's for comparison.
So for 16 elements we're talking about four comparisons.
So you can think of it as two to what power gives us 16 to the fourth power two times two times two
times two gives us 16.
Or if we were to hop over here this is a maxed out.
Unfortunately I actually can't insert anything else into this.
The limit is 31 nodes but if we were to insert something right here this is where it would go next to
the 30 second node we would if it was let's say we insert 100 which is larger than the root to find
its way up here.
It's one comparison to comparison's three four and then five comparisons.
So for 32 nodes we're talking about five comparison's five operations.
So its end grows to 32.
We think about two to what power gives us 32 to 2 the fifth power.
Two times two times two times two times two.
So another way of putting that is every time we double the number of nodes every new full complete layer
we are only increasing the time that it takes by one.
So when we get to 64 nodes we're talking about six operations and hopefully you can see why would be
the same for removal because we insert the that we remove from the beginning we swap something to be
the new route and then we have to compare and if it has to sift all the way back down the max number
of comparisons is going to be the same as we saw here.
Its log and its the same idea between insertion and removal.
Now you might remember from when we talked about binary search trees where they also had a log an insertion
time in general or an average slash best case.
There was also a worst case scenario.
Remember this that very depressing tree that really doesn't look much like a tree sort of looks like
something else.
The big O time complexity to insert into this tree or to search is o of and because of the way that
it's set up right if it's constantly just right.
Right.
It's going to take you know how many nodes are in here.
That's potentially how long it would take to insert if you were trying to insert 100 or something.
This is not a problem when we're talking about heaps.
Now why is that.
Well heaps can never look like this is against the rules of a heap.
Remember that when we insert into a heap we always fill out the left side first.
So unlike a binary search tree where we might have you know an incomplete row I shouldn't call it a
row an incomplete level.
Instead everything is always filled out before we move on to the next level.
So this entire row this entire section is done and then we start inserting here and here and then we
keep going across.
So there is no possibility for us to have such a crazy unbalanced unhinged depressing tree.
And because of that worst case is still.
Oh of all the way back here again for insertion and removal now binary heaps are not really made to
be search well like if you really care about optimizing your search then you probably want to use a
binary search tree or something like that.
So time complexity for search is over.
And remember that when we look at a binary heap like this there is no guaranteed order or even an implied
order between siblings.
So if we're searching for the node that contains the value 1 we start with the beginning.
Well we can't make a decision.
We can't know with a binary search tree we could say all right.
Well less than 86 so it's somewhere over here.
That's not the case here.
It could be anywhere because one is less than 86 it's the only condition that we know for sure is true
about all of these notes.
Is there less than 86.
So then we have to look over here and well once again we can't really make a decision.
It's somewhere down here maybe but it still could be over here.
And so we keep going and you know we have to search here and here and here and here and finally find
one.
But it also could be over here.
There's no rule that it has to be here it's just in this given scenario.
It is and that is a bit of a worst case.
Now if we were looking for something closer to the top of our heap like we're looking for the number
let's say 80 when we started here and we know that 80 is definitely less than 86 so we have both of
these.
Well over here we know that 80 is less than 85.
So it's going to be over here potentially.
Over here we have 77 well.
Seventy seven is not greater than 80 so we can cross off this side of the tree.
There is no number greater than 77 over here.
So if we can make a decision and eliminate some of it but there's no guarantee every step of the way
that that's the case.
And it depends on the value that we're looking for.
So technically if you do look it up.
I believe that big-O for searching is of and divided by two on average but remember that when we have
a constant like that and divided by two and times two and times 100 it doesn't matter.
We simplify it to big o of.
And so as n grows in general the amount of time it takes to search also grows just at the same rate.
And so it's linear.
And so these are not optimized for searching but when we're talking about insertion and removal that's
the name of the game with heaps.
All right we have time for a quick recap so we've seen a lot of time talking about binary heaps which
are a type of tree.
Well technically a binary heap is a type of a heap.
We could have other types of heaps just like a binary tree is a type of a tree.
So we have binary heap which is a type of a heap which is a type of a tree.
OK.
So they're useful on their own but also to implement other data structures like priority queues.
Think we just saw a couple of videos ago.
They are either one or talking about binary heaps they're either Macs binary heaps or many binary heaps.
And the way that it works the one rule that governs it.
Aside from the structure meaning that each node can have a maximum of two children.
The other rule in emacs ordinary heap is that every parent is larger than its two children and a binary
heap every parent is smaller than its two children or however many children it has.
We fill them out from left to right so we don't end up with these unbalanced wonky one sided trees.
A heap is always filled out from left to right.
It looks like a heap.
It's a pyramid of stuff.
It's a heap a pile.
And with this a little bit of math we can pretty easily represent heaps using a raise.
So we don't have to make pointers.
We don't have to make nodes that point to next dot next or left and right or child or whatever we can
just store them in an array because the rules that we follow makes it very easy to flatten out or represent
just using numerical indices.
And so that's a nice easy way of doing it.
You don't have to represent heaps that way.
You could do heaps.
You could make your own class and you know make a bunch of notes like we did for binary search trees.
It's just easier to do it this way.
All right so that's binary.
Heaps.