Welcome back all of the sorts that we've seen so far our groups together in a group called comparison
sorting algorithms.
All that means is that whether we're talking about bubble sort or something more advanced like quicksort
at the end of the day beneath the surface the base comparison that we're doing is between two items
at any given point.
So we have one item on the left let's say and another on the right and we're deciding which one comes
first or which one comes second depending on how we're sorting.
So comparison sort just means we're comparing two things.
That's the most we ever compare at a given time.
We're doing less then versus greater then and then we're deciding where that one item goes.
So when we talk about average time complexity for something like bubble sort of squared.
Same for insertion and selection sort.
Then we saw a slight and well more than slight improvement we saw a pretty big improvement with quicksort
and merge sort which had average time complexity of 0 of end log in.
So the question is are there faster sorting algorithms.
Can we improve upon of and log it.
Can we do better.
And the answer is sort of answers yes we can but not by making comparisons.
So mathematically there is a lower bound an asymptote for our average time complexity in a comparison
sort.
So no matter what the actual comparison algorithm is with the sorting algorithm is quicksort.
Heapsort shell sort any of the ones we've seen cocktail shaker sort haven't heard of that one.
All of these.
Well not all of them.
Some of them are slower like we saw with bubble sort.
But the best average case time complexity that we can ever hope for in any comparison sort is an log.
And if you want to learn more about the reason for it you can read this wikipedia article it goes into
a little bit of a proof down here that explains how it how it how we arrived there.
It all has to do with the limited information that we can gain from a single comparison.
There is a mathematical bound to that anyway.
That's not really the focus here because we have a solution we have a way around this but only in certain
cases.
So there are other types of sorting out rhythms that are not comparison algorithms and these algorithms
take advantage of special properties of the data.
For example there is a group of sorts called integer sorting algorithms and they only work with integers
with numbers and we don't actually make direct comparisons.
So one of those is radix sort.
So when I say that we don't make direct comparisons I mean we're never actually comparing is this number
less than this number is this number greater than this number.
So we end up sorting the data in a different way.
So radix sort is kind of fun and it's very different than anything we've done so far because we're not
making comparisons.
So let's talk about how it works.
So I mentioned it's a special sorting algorithm that doesn't make comparisons and it works on numbers.
So usually when this is actually used it's used with binary numbers and the number can be expressed
in binary.
Also you could take any strings or images if you wanted to and convert them to binary.
So it's possible to sort other data but the actual data we work with at the time that we're sorting
it needs to be numbers.
And we're going to work with base 10 numbers like 950 or 17.
So never makes comparisons between two elements that nevers asks what's smaller what's larger.
Instead it exploits the fact that information about the size of a number is encoded in the number of
digits.
What I mean by that is that if a number has more digits but say a four digit number it's larger than
any two digit number it doesn't matter what the two numbers are.
We're not comparing the two numbers but we know that something with more digits is larger than something
with fewer digits.
So here's actually how it works.
We actually take a list of numbers let's say this is what we're trying to sort.
We have some numbers that are 1 digit.
These are all based 10 to digits three digits four digits and we create 10 different buckets and these
buckets represent all of the possible numbers the one digit numbers in base ten.
So 0 through 9.
So for every spot in a number it could be 0 1 or 2 all the way up to a 9.
And what we do is we go through the entire list of our numbers and we start by looking at this digit.
So the first digit in the number from the right side.
So 6 4 6 3 8 OK and we group them into buckets based off of that number.
So you'll see all numbers that have a two in the rightmost position go in the two bucket all numbers
with a six in the rightmost position.
Whether they're two digits 100 digits it's just that we're looking at the rightmost digit.
We group them together here.
So we're not sorting them within this bucket.
You can see that these are not in order.
We take all sevens all eights all nines and then we form them back into a list keeping the order that
they're in right here.
So this will be at the beginning.
And then this number and then this number you can see here.
So the numbers that had to is your last digit come before the numbers that had three or last digit.
And then at the end we have numbers with nine as their last digit.
Now we repeat the process except we look at the next digit to the left.
So we're going to look at this digit.
And this one and this one.
OK.
So now we group them based off of that second digit from the right.
So if we look at this column this bucket we're talking about zero which this has it's a 0 4 0 8 0 in
that position.
I know 2 does.
But then these numbers which are one digit numbers don't have any digit in that position so we just
put them in this year bucket.
There's a zero there.
Right we can write any number as 0 7 is the same as 7 0 4 is just the same as 4.
So then we end up with if we go over here we've got all the numbers that have 5 in that position.
All the numbers that have 8 in that position and we're getting closer each pass through here.
We're never comparing the numbers to one another.
And now we reformed them into this list and you can see it's getting closer to being sorted.
But we're still out there.
So we repeat it again where we're talking about the third digit.
So the first the second the third digit.
Do it again.
OK.
So you can see the smaller numbers are already grouping up here and we have for example here five this
number has five and it's third spot and so on.
And then we reformed into a list again and then we have to go one more time.
So the number of times we have to actually do this process depends on the largest number.
How many digits it has.
So we have a couple of four digit numbers.
So we have to split them up four times.
If we had a 10 digit number in here we would have to do it 10 times.
OK.
So here's our last time.
So now they've been split up.
We're talking about the fourth digit.
None of these have a fourth digit.
This one does some does and so on.
And then Re-Forum them again into our list and we're done.
So when I say we form them into the list I mean we just take the order that's already in these pockets
so we start here then here all the way up to nine or two.
And then we take this bucket.
This one is empty.
So this one and we keep going.
And now the numbers are sorted.
So we never made any comparisons between the numbers in our list.
Instead we took advantage of a special property of numbers.
So Leslie here's a nice animation of radix sort.
All Hit Play.
What we do is you take a look at that right most digit and regroup them in those 10 buckets.
So if we're talking about base seven numbers instead we would have seven buckets.
We're talking about base 10 so we have 10 buckets.
OK.
And now we reformed them you can see the order we're talking about we just pull them out of the buckets
in the same order that they're already stored in.
And now we take a look at the second digit from the right and we form them into buckets.
OK.
And again in this case our largest number is a four digit number.
So we're going to have to do this process four times.
That was two times down.
Now we have two more.
So now we take a look at the third number from the right and numbers that don't have a number in that
position.
We put them in the zero bucket and we're almost there.
We just have to take a look at the fourth digit from the right and group things into the correct bucket
based off of that digit.
So we're almost there.
So a couple things to keep in mind in order to make this work.
We have to be able to figure out a digit in a number at a given position.
So in the next video I'm going to talk about some helper functions we need to write.
For example I need to be able to ask hey what is the second digit of this number what's the fourth digit
or the first digit.
And most languages don't give you an easy way of doing that.
We have to write our own method to do it.
So that's what we're going to start with before we get to the buckets anyway.
That's radix sort.
It is a special case of a sorting algorithm that is not a comparison sort.
It's an integer sort that works because of a special I wouldn't say a loophole but a special property.
And it allows us to sort numbers very fast compared to having to do comparisons anyway.
Well implemented in the next couple of videos.