All right now that we have a basic understanding of Radix Sort Conceptually we need to implement a couple
of helper methods so that we can actually write the main algorithm and the first one that we have to
do is called Get digit or something like this.
That takes a number and a position and returns the digit at that position.
So we might have one two three four five if we called Get digit one two three four five with one as
the position that should give us this number.
So this is the zero position the one to three to four.
So it's not you know a string or an array.
We start to zero over here.
We move to the right.
This is going the other direction and get digit is really important for sorting things into these buckets.
Right.
If we have we're starting the very first pass on this list we need to take a look at this digit the
zero digit in our example and put things in the correct spot.
Then the next time through we need to look at this digit.
So we need a method that will give us that digit.
And unfortunately there's no easy way of doing that.
Out of the box we need to write a method.
So if you want to do this on your own rather than breaking this up into three different videos for the
three methods I'm going to show I think I'm just going to combine them into one.
I know that I'm going to combine them into one.
I'm already recording it.
The focus is not about this logic the focus is on the sorting logic of radix sort.
But anyway if you do want to try these POS video and do it now two strategies you can do.
You can convert to a string and then use the correct index to access the number you want and then convert
it back to a number.
The only problem is that as I already mentioned the strings are index from the left side.
So if somebody asks for position zero of this if you convert to a string and you get zero.
Well that's going to be the complete wrong side.
So you could do some math so that you can convert you know working backwards using negative indices
or something like that.
Then come back to a string or you can do some math.
So this should only work with base 10 numbers by the way.
You don't have to make it work for binary.
We don't need you know a user.
If we were doing other bases a user could pass in what base.
But assume base 10 numbers.
So there's some math you can do each one of these positions represents a power of 10.
This is the 10 to zero position tend to the first 10 to the second which the way I learned it in school
was not tend to the second tend to the third.
It was the one place the tens place the hundreds place.
So what you can do is divide by that power of 10 and then do some other math which I'll show you in
just a second to get the answer.
OK.
So if you want to implement it on your own posit Otherwise here's a spoiler here's a solution.
I just took this from Stack Overflow and it's called Get digit.
It satisfies our requirements.
Let me show you how it works.
Let's say we're taking a look at a number like 73.
Sure that number.
And if we pass in so if we did get digit of that and I'm looking for whatever number is in this position
0 1 2 so I'd pass into the math is that this number here is 300 right.
It's a three.
But in the context of this it's a 300.
So we're going to divide by 100 as you can see here math power 10 to the eye so tend to the second which
is I gives us 100 so we're going to divide this whole number by 100.
So I'll write this out here.
We can ignore the math that apse the value just for a second.
That's just so that this works with negative numbers.
If I passed in in a negative number this should still be three.
We don't want to get negative for three.
This is just three is a digit we won.
So that's what the math of the absolute value is.
So we'll ignore that if we take this number and we divide by 100 which is what this is right here.
And then we floor it down here.
So we get seventy three point two three if we do a floor we just get 73.
OK.
So then we have 73 maade 10.
So we divide 10 into there.
How many times does it go in.
It doesn't really matter.
But it goes in seven times.
So we get 70 What's the remainder.
Well the remainder is three.
So if we do mod 10 we get three.
And that's what we're looking for.
So we divide by the place the hundreds place.
Then we floor to get rid of the decimal then we mod 10.
And that's the math.
So just to prove that it works.
Run the code and then let's pass it in zero.
We get the correct digit also with 3 1.
What you get 2 three we get to 7.
And if we pass in something that's not in there we get zero.
Perfect.
So this works we're all good.
The next helper we need has to do with figuring out how many digits are in a number.
And the reason we need that if we go back here is in this example we need to know how many times we
need to sort things into buckets how many times do we have to you know reorder everything.
And the answer is four.
Because the largest number we have has four digits.
So that's you know that's our bound if we have one 10 digit number in here.
Then we need to do it 10 times.
So we need to write code to figure out how many times we need to run it for a given list of numbers
and all that we need to do is figure out which number has the largest or has the most number of digits.
So there's two methods will right.
The first one will give us Digic count for a single number and then the second one will use Digic count
to figure out the largest number of digits for the entire list.
So we'll have you know Max digits which calls digit count.
So Digic count just you pass passing a base 10 number and it should return to you.
How many digits are in there.
So this would give us three digits.
This is a two digit number.
This is a one digit number.
You could do this as a string converted to a string find the length or you could do some math which
is what I'm going to do.
So posit if you want to try and implement this on your own very loud motorcycle upside.
Otherwise here's a solution.
All right I copy this solution over.
It's called Digic count.
And there's a couple of things we'll talk about here.
So first things first log 10.
This is the log base 10 which what that does.
If you didn't watch the log video early on in the course it's basically asking ten to what power gives
us this number.
So if I called Digic count on I don't know.
Let's do 423.
To what power gives us 423.
Well it's not going to be a nice clean number.
So that's why we do the floor.
But let's do math.
Log 10 of 4:23 gives us this.
And when we floor that we get two because we're just getting rid of that.
So our answer here was two and we're close.
Except that we need to count the number of digits which we need to add one in.
So we get three.
So just one more example if we have a larger number like this.
OK.
We're doing math at absolute value again because we want it to work with negative numbers.
If somebody passes in negative this number still has the same number of digits we don't we're not going
to worry about negative numbers for our sort.
But these are from Stack Overflow and it's always good to be conscientious of that.
So if we take this number and we do math don't log 10 of that and then we floor that we get four and
we add one which is five.
That's how many digits are here.
One two three four five.
OK.
So if the math is crazy to you don't worry it works.
And this is something I feel like it's totally normal to just take this from Stack Overflow and add
this to your code if you really need it.
So did it count.
The only special case is if number is 0.
So if somebody passes in well not there.
But if we did this this is a one digit number.
But the problem is that if you try and do your math out log 10 of 0 you get negative infinity.
That's not what we want.
So we have to add this special case.
OK.
That's Digic count.
And then our last method we need is called most digits.
And this will take a list of numbers and just tell us which number has the most digits in it using Digic
count I mean it should use Digic count because we just wrote it.
I guess you could just do it again.
So what I would do is take Digic count and run it on each number in this list and then keep a running
tally of what the maximum is and just return that number so you don't even have to return which number
itself had the most digits just the count.
So for example in this list it would return five because this is the largest number it has five digits
in this list.
It returns to all the numbers have two digit digits.
So this one's the easiest I think because we already have this code.
If you just want to copy it the focus again is not on actually writing needs yourself but I just want
to walk through them.
So most digits Here's my solution looks like this I'll copy it over and it just takes a list of numbers
and we start a max variable Max digits.
It starts at zero.
And then I loop through Gnome's and amusing math max which if you're not familiar with it you just pass
in two numbers.
If I do zero and 12 it's always going to give me a larger number.
And so this allows me to instead of doing like an IF statement if x is larger than my current max then
reassign the current max I'm just setting Max digits to equal the maximum between the current value
of Max digits and Digic count of numbers.
So for each number.
So if I do most digits of that see 23
OK this at the beginning Max digits will be zero.
And then it loops through and it becomes two because the largest number we've seen so far has two digits.
But the next time through three next time through it's still three then it's whatever this is and it
stays at that.
So let's run this and I get eight because this number presumably has eight digits.
It does just count 8 digits.
OK.
So these are the helpers we need.
And now we can actually implement in the next video we can implement our radix sort using these.
And the logic isn't that bad once we have these done.
You don't have to worry about recursion or any sort of crazy logic.
We basically just loop over and put things into buckets and then join them together and do that x number
of times where X is the number with the most digits.
OK.
See you then.