Hey welcome back.
Time to actually write radix sort.
So if we if you watched the video on the helper methods that's actually the harder stuff.
Now we just call those helper methods a couple of times in the loop and we make the buckets.
And that's kind of it.
So here's the pseudo code if you want to add this yourself the Find function that accepts a list of
numbers just call it radix sort something like that and then the first thing we have to do is figure
out how many digits the largest number has.
Well we just wrote that method.
Most digits if we go back here we need to figure out which number has the largest number of digits or
what is the largest number of digits in any of these numbers.
And in this case it's four.
There's a couple of four digit numbers with this more than a couple.
So we're going to need to loop four times because we're going to need to sort them into buckets for
this digit this digit.
This digit this one and this one to four different times.
If we had a six digit number we need to do it six times.
So once you figure that out using the method we just defined back here then you need to start a loop
from zero up until the largest number of digits.
So for doing this four times we need to go from zero to 1 to 2 to 3.
And each time through we're going to create buckets for each digit.
Now a bucket is just an empty array.
So we'll have an array that has 10 Subba race.
That's how I would do it.
And there they all start empty.
So index 0 of this array starts as an empty array index one is an empty array.
And then each time through this loop we're going to take each number put it in the correct bucket based
off of it.
It's OK.
That's a really difficult thing to say it's case digit.
Meaning that whatever this loop is we start at zero.
We're going to put it in each number in the correct spot correct bucket slot using the zero with digit.
And then the first digit the second digit.
So if we go here right if we run sort go first thing we do.
So we make these buckets.
Here's our 10 buckets.
Each one of these is an array inside of one larger array with 10 slots.
And this is index 0.
This is index 1 index too.
So all that we do for any number which one is next.
All right.
So when we take the 0 with number which also happens to be zero.
So we take this number and put it in the slot zero index zero and we keep going.
So here we go we take the zero with Number of this we already wrote a helper method to do that.
We call that what we call it digit get digit something like that.
So get digit index 0 is going to give us 7.
So we put the whole number in slot 7.
So we keep going with that.
And then the next time through our loop we're going to look at index of one and then index of two index
of three.
And then the other thing we have to do is replace our existing array with the values in the buckets.
So this is where we reorder them a bit a bit.
So in this example you know we put them all in the correct buckets can speed this up a little bit.
And then at this point we reformed them into almost using the order that they're currently in.
And there's an easy way.
There's a couple of easy ways of doing that.
You don't have to loop through manually and do this.
I would just concatenate into a new array and so we just keep that order and then we start the process
over.
So there's going to be two loops.
There's the outer loop which happens four times.
So we're looking at digit 1 or 0 and all the numbers digit 1 and all the numbers 2 3 and the numbers
and then we need an inner loop to actually do something to each number in the list.
OK.
And then at the very end return not list.
So I'm going to implement this in the next video.
Totally fine if this one is a little challenging.
I mean it's always fun.
It's not my place to say that but this is one that I think if you look at the code itself the solution
ignoring the actual math from the last video about finding the digits and the log 10 and dealing with
it you know Maggiolo and all that stuff the logic in the sorting function itself is relatively straightforward.
So we'll do that in the next video.