All right.
So we have this true code laid out.
We have our helper methods written let's write the logic.
So the first thing I'll do I need my helper methods I'm going to keep those and I'm going to define
a function called radix sort and it takes a list of numbers and the very first thing after that I need
to figure out how many digits the largest number has.
So we have this method.
Most digits.
So let's make a variable called most digits or something like that Max digit.
Let's do that Max digit count equals most digits of numbers.
And then let's just print that out so we can see that it works
OK.
And then let's call RADICH sort down here and pass in a list of numbers with a couple small ones some
larger ones.
OK.
So what is the max digit count if this looks like it should be for the largest number we have is a four
digit number.
If we run the code we get four.
All right so now we know we need to loop four times so we can start with that loop from K.
It doesn't have to be k but k equals zero.
Up to that largest number of digits.
So let's write a for loop for k equals zero K is a less than max digit count K plus plus.
So this gives us an index k going from 0 to 1 to 2 to 3.
So we can use that and pass it into this method get digit so we can ask for the zero digit or that the
third digit.
OK now that we have that written we need to make our buckets.
So I'm going to make a list.
I'm just going to call it digit buckets with one B and we could you know manually construct this make
an array and then push in 10 empty arrays.
But there's also an easy way relatively easy if we do array from and then here right here if we pass
in a length.
I set it to be 10 and then we tell each one to be an empty suburb.
So if I just copy this over here and paste it in.
If we look at what did your book it is it's an array of 10 empty arrays.
So if I changed it slightly to be an array containing the string.
Well we end up with 10 sub arrays each with EHLO Well is there one element not what we want but we want
an empty array.
So now we have 10 buckets 10 slots inside of this one larger bucket called did one array called digit
buckets and they're all empty.
Now we need to loop over every number.
So this part's easy let's just do for zero is less than numbers that length plus plus.
So for each number we're now going to take that individual number just numbs I.
And we're going to figure out at position k so at index 0 of each number what what value do we get.
And then K will change of course.
So we're going to do get digit of Gnome's I comma K and so that will give us digit 3 5 7 2 5.
The first time through.
And then K will go up and K will be 1 2 then will look at this number.
The index one number and then will go up again and will keep going.
So we don't just want to get that number.
We want to take that number that comes back and then put Gnome's I in the bucket at that index.
So if we if I just print this out right now it's going to be pretty ugly but you'll see what we end
up with here on our code.
So a lot of comprador logs.
But the very first time through we end up with 3 5 7 2 5.
So 3 5 7 2 5 2.
So we need to take those numbers.
We need to put this number at index three.
This number we got five.
We need to put it at index 5 so we could just do this.
We could do it in one ugly line which I don't like digit buckets.
Of that result so digit buckets have indexed three or index five or whatever we get back.
Push number.
I know this is kind of a gross line in my opinion.
I'm going to break it up.
But if we actually do this and let's just do it one time and then let's just print out at the end of
this loop the chip buckets you'll see.
Well I don't want to comment for the hatch but everything should be in the correct spot like the first
time through.
We end up with all the numbers that have to as their first digit are in the two bucket.
We have 23 in this bucket.
We have these numbers that end with the 5 and the five bucket.
So that's all working.
But I just don't like how long this line is.
So I'm going to break this up a little bit and make a variable called digit just like this.
Copied one extra part and then we'll do index of digit.
Push comes I.
So we're going to get the digit.
So that would give us three.
And then this is just a way of breaking up the code digit pockets of three.
Push the number OK.
So we're almost there.
But the one thing we're missing is after we break them into their buckets we need to recollect them
into a new array and do the same thing.
Otherwise we're just keeping them in the same order.
And then just sorting them into buckets.
So we're sorting them based off of their first number and then we're doing the same thing based off
of the second number but we're never actually ending up with a new order to the main list called Nomes.
So we need to afterwards right here where we're printing out after we've put them in the correct bucket
we need to then concat the array.
So there's a nice easy way of doing this in javascript.
We reassign numbers to be array dot concat and then I'm going to use spread digit buckets and I use
the spread operator the special syntax with the three dots which you're not familiar with it.
It allows me to pass in all the arguments or every element in digit buckets as an individual argument.
And the reason I need to do this rather than just passing in digit buckets is if we imagine here I'll
do it down here.
If I do a duck can cats and let's say that I have three arrays because this is an array of arrays right.
What we're looking at here.
So let's say that digit looks like this.
It's very simple but it looks something like this.
If I call a radar concat it's going to concat these into a new array.
But they still are in separate buckets.
If I want to take these numbers and just combine them back into the original form.
So this but in a different order if I use the spread operator that dot dot dot I end up with this just
the values there turned into a new array.
So this is what I want.
This is a nice easy way.
I don't have to manually you could loop over digit buckets for each bucket loop over all the values
in that bucket and push them into Gnome's or a new array.
But this is a nice succinct way of doing it.
And that's all we need to do aside from returning names.
So let's do that and let's see if it works.
What I would like to do here is do a constant log.
Let's go with digit buckets here.
And then afterwards after we can get back into Nom's can count about log numbers.
OK.
Let's run the code.
All right.
So first time through we end up with everything sorted or not sorted but everything put into the correct
bucket based off the zero digit.
The first one from the right.
Then we can catch this.
So the order is preserved.
Think of it as just smushing them all together into this array.
Now number looks like this.
So we have 12 digit 2 followed by 9 8 5 2 which ends in a two and then which one end in a three and
a five and so on.
So we took this order and just smashed them together.
Then we went through and put them into buckets based off of this number.
So you can see them here.
So this is in slot one bucket one.
This is in bucket to bucket for.
And then we can catch them again.
So we keep this order and we end up with this.
So each time we get a little more sorted then we do it again and we look at the index to 0 1 2.
So some of the numbers don't have a value there in which case they're in the zero bucket.
So the smallest numbers are already in the correct bucket.
But the three and four digit numbers are still working their way to their correct spots.
So we can catch it again.
We end up with this.
And then one more time.
Put them in buckets based off of their index of three number what digit is right here.
And then we can cat we end up with this we're done and we return that and that is radix sort.
So I think it's kind of a fun one.
Once you actually write the methods or you find the methods on Stack Overflow for getting a digit counting
digits finding the most digits the logic itself can get rid of the concert about logs.
It's relatively straightforward I think aside from you know this if you haven't ever seen this operator
this is just a simplification.
A nice short way of doing this.
But the idea of what we're doing I think is simple.
We're separating things into buckets based off of a digit in a given position.
And then we Re-Forum them into a new list or a new array and then repeat it on the next digit.
For all of those numbers and keep going until we've done it for every digit in the largest number.
All right.
So we'll talk about big-O in the next video and then we are done with sorting rhythms all right.