Welcome back.
All right let's wrap up.
Radix Sort quickly by talking about its big owner station.
Now I should start by saying that there's a little controversy around this and there's room for argument
around radix sort but here is the generally accepted notation.
So time complexity for best average and worst is o of and K so n is the number of things we're sorting
the number of numbers are integers.
K is the length of those numbers.
What's often called the word size for a number.
It's not really a word but the number of digits.
So if we have really really really long digits that's important to consider.
It's not just a constant we can ignore it.
You know that's always the same.
It's not like two or three and if we have really long numbers then that does significantly impact the
time and the length of the array the number of numbers we're sorting.
OK.
The number of digits in those numbers.
And the reason I say it's controversial is that this can be significantly better on paper at least than
a comparison sort.
Which best case for their average.
Oh of and log again if we go over to Wikipedia the radix sort page down to efficiency there's a relatively
large.
Two paragraphs are making two arguments an argument and a counter argument about the time complexity
for radix sort.
And it has to do with how numbers are actually stored in memory on a computer.
And if all the numbers are distinct in whatever we're sorting a list contains all distinct numbers then
according to this K or what they called W has to be at least log n.
So if we plug to log n for k that's going to give us and log end which is the same as what we talked
about for a comparison sort.
So that's one argument which is if you're dealing with all unique randomly distributed data then this
simplifies or it doesn't simplify this becomes law again because of the way that computer store numbers
store information.
I don't have a great understanding on exactly why that is but if we accept that that means that radix
sort is equally as good in the case in the average case if we're talking about and K where k is again
it's the same as analog again.
Then there's a bit of a argument down here that says well actually fine if you're going to say that
radix sort isn't as fast as it claims to be then we're going to talk about some of the problems with
comparison sorts and that there's actually shortcomings in how random numbers are compared and that
it's a little slower than you expected.
Sounds something that I can speak on myself at all.
I actually have always assumed that it was for radix sort o of W N or K and where K or W is just the
word size.
And that's what pretty much every textbook or you know big O cheat sheet type thing that I've seen says.
Then I went to just double check and fell into this rabbit hole.
So keep that in mind I guess.
So theoretically radix sort can be faster than any of the comparison sorts but apparently because of
limitations on how computers actually store numbers in memory that may not actually be the case.
And it might just be tied with compar. sorts.
But either way I think that RADICH is a fun algorithm because it's sort of quirky.
It takes advantage of a specific feature of our data of numbers and that we can use the digits in any
given number in the number of digits in those numbers to sort things without having to ever directly
compare any numbers.
We're never checking what's larger which What's greater.
We're simply moving them into buckets and then regrouping moving into buckets regrouping.
So yeah I like radix sort.
It's fun.