Hello welcome back.
So this is the first of many sections on data structures.
The first one we're going to talk about is called the singly linked list.
We also have a doubly linked list.
We'll see that later.
We're starting here.
So quick preface a warning a note if you're unfamiliar with the 2015 class keyword javascript's approximation
or syntactic sugar to sort of look like traditional object oriented programming.
If you've never seen that before or you want to refresh your memory on it take a look at the previous
section.
I think a lot of students may have jumped to this section if you did I would check that out.
If you're not familiar with how it works it's quick little section.
And the reason is that we're going to use that class keyword in pretty much every data structure we
make or every data structure we create will define our own javascript class.
We're going to make a singly linked list class in this section and do the same thing for graphs and
every other structure we see.
OK.
So quickly our objectives.
We want to explain what the heck a singly linked list is.
We're also going to compare it to the list structure we already know the built in array.
We use it all the time so that stores a list of data.
What's the difference.
And then the bulk of the section will be devoted to actually defining or linked lists class and adding
in a bunch of methods a lot of functionality to push things into it or to pop things or to search and
traverse or to delete things to all sorts of things.
So that's what we're going to do in this section.
OK.
So let's start with that definition.
What is something to list.
So it's a data structure that stores whatever data you want strings numbers.
It doesn't matter and it's ordered It's a list of data just like an array.
But there's a really big distinction in an array.
Each item is mapped it's indexed with a number.
So I can get the fifth item the 6 item and anytime we add something in it gets an index that map to
its position a linked list on the other hand just consists of a bunch of elements with no indices who
are just pointing to the next element.
Sort of like a bunch of train cars connected where one car connects to the next one and that one connects
to the next one.
But there is no index that we use to access things we can't say.
Give me the thing.
We've just started the first one and then moved to the second one moved to the third one moved to the
fourth and then moved to the fifth.
So just some terminology here I'm going to show you a diagram in just a second but we say that each
element is a node.
So a link post consists of a bunch of nodes.
A node stores a piece of data like a string or a number but it also references the next node or if it's
at the very end there is no next node references no and then three properties we keep track of.
The head is the beginning of the length list.
The tail is the end.
So we don't keep track of every single item in the middle.
We just keep track of the head and from the head we can figure out the next one.
And from there we can figure out the next one all the way until the end.
And then also we keep track full length to make things easier.
So here's sort of a diagram of what a length list looks like.
Notice there is no index so we don't say this is zero with the first the second the third.
If we want to access something from this list we start at the beginning.
If we want the second to last item we have to start here and ask for the next item which gives us 6
and we have to ask for the next item which finally gives us the second to last item.
So a length list is just a bunch of nodes pointing to other nodes.
So one node points the next one points the next one.
Sort of like a chain of elephants.
Back before that band elephants at the circus in the US they would grab each other's tails with their
noses and walk in a line.
I kind of like to think of it as a skyscraper that has no elevators.
So in an array there's elevators you could say take me to the fifth floor and takes you right there.
If you're in a length of list there's only stairs and each set of each floor is connected to the next
one set of stairs.
So to get to the fifth floor we started the first one take the stairs to the second then go up to the
third and the fourth and then we get to the fifth.
I don't know if that's a great analogy or not.
By the way the terminology singly linked list comes from the fact that each node is only connected one
directionally to the next node a doubly linked list which will get to said don't worry about it right
now.
Also as a connection pointing back to the previous node and we'll talk about the pros and cons to that
later on.
So here's a visualization on visual algo vige I'll go and never not say this.
It's a great Web site though and it's going to be very useful here.
So this is a lengthy list where each node just contains a number.
Remember it could be whatever we want.
We could have no strings we could have other could have an array and each one doesn't matter and they
all just point to the next item except for the last one.
There's nothing after it and let's say that we're going to.
I don't know.
Insert something actually would start with searching for something.
So if we want to search for let's say 43 in this list we have to start at the beginning and check the
next then the next then the next then the next and then we find 43.
OK.
If we wanted to insert something into here if you want to insert something in the middle it's one let's
say at position for you want to insert the number 90.
We have to start at the beginning then move down to the next to the next.
Keep going till we get to the correct spot and then we inserted in.
Now the actual process of inserting will come back to we're going to write our own insert functions.
It's pretty easy though especially for inserting I mean to the beginning or the end.
All we have to do is say to insert it at the very beginning.
Is just make this the new head and have it point to the old head and all of a sudden we're in business.
Unlike an array where we'd have to well we don't do this but in the array every single item would have
to be re-index to get a new position number.
OK.
So we're going to come back to this and spend a lot of time sort of working through this as we build
our own methods.
Well let's wrap up with a comparison with the race so linked lists don't have indices or indexes.
I guess I wrote I think it's indices.
They have no numbers that correspond to each item.
Instead we just have the head pointer which is just a variable that says this is the beginning of the
list.
And we have a tail.
You actually don't have to have a tail.
It just makes it easier if you're trying to add to the end.
But we have to have that head.
That's the beginning.
And then we can just move to the next and to the next and to the next until we find what we're looking
for or we insert something unlike an array there is no positional there's no indices.
So each node is connected with a next pointer.
What this means random access is not allowed so random access means I can't just ask for the tenth item
and get it immediately.
We have to traverse from the beginning all the way to the tenth item.
Just like the analogy I explained with a skyscraper.
If you have an array you get an elevator straight to the tenth floor.
If you have the length First you walk all the way up to the tenth floor.
However one of the things that length lists are good at insertion and deletion.
So because arrays are indexed.
If we insert something at the beginning or in the middle we've already talked about this.
It has this cascade ripple effect.
Everything has to be indexed in length list.
That's not the case and we'll get into this further we'll talk about big-O of certain operations throughout
the section but just know that that's one of the reasons really the main reason you would want to use
something for us is if you really care about insertion and deletion especially if you're working with
really really long pieces of data to not piece of the data with a long data set lots of information
and you don't need random access.
You just need to store it in a list.
While you might want to use a linked list but will again we'll come back to this.
Remember a lot of this right now is just going to be very sort of theoretical and conceptual.
Don't get too caught up on you know.
Why would I use this if we already have an array.
Because at the end of the day you could use an array for all of this but there are advantages to make
lists and will expand on that anyway.
And the next video we're going to define our length less class and add our first method in.
So that's coming up next.