Hey welcome back.
So let's start writing our code.
Remember that a linked list is just a collection of notes.
So let's start by defining a class for each node in a node is very simple.
It just stores a piece of data we'll call it Vau or value and then it stores a reference to next node
which we'll call next.
So let's define our class or call it node.
We need to add our constructor and it will just taken a vow.
Whatever the piece of information is and we'll just set this dot Vau equals Vau and then we'll initialize
this dot next to be No.
Because at the beginning there's nothing that comes after it.
All right.
So this is actually all we need for our node.
It's very simple and we could sort of approximate a linked list right now what we're going to do is
define our own singly linked lists class that will utilize node.
But for now I could just do something like this for our first equals new node and let's say our first
node is high then I could do first next equals new node to capitalize there and then do the same thing
again next.
Does that make sense.
We're starting with the first thing and then we're just accessing the next and setting it to be a whole
other new node and then we're taking that value and giving it a new dot next a whole other new node.
So I'll do hi there.
How are you overcommitted to the number of words here.
All right we'll leave it at this.
How are you.
I think I need to I need to do next.
I don't have any of my shortcuts in this go.
So this is a very bad way of representing it like this because if I were to add something in I need
to keep writing.
Next up next up next up next what will be defining later on is will have a linked list class and I should
be able to say list does push you for example and that will add on to the end it will keep track of
where to add that.
Anyway this is what we have for now.
So if I actually run this if we look at first.
All right.
That's what we have the value is high and there's a reference to the next node.
If I click on it we can see next is this no that says there.
And if we can come that I can see that the next is on that is a value that says how we could keep going.
So let's actually define our linked list class to make this a little bit cleaner so we don't have do
all this.
So down here I mean define class singly linked list and or constructor.
And it's not going to actually take anything.
Our interface is going to be something like this will define a new length list so new length list.
Technically it should be singly linked list so quickly update that save it to variable.
Let's say it.
I don't know list equals.
So the interface will be something like this.
We create a new singly linked list and then we can say let's push something list out push Hello list
up push goodbye and this will add on to the end of the list and we don't have to do next dot next out
next up next it will just keep track of it and do it for us.
So this is where we're going.
Still very simple but much better than having to do it this way.
So our constructor we don't initialize whole thing for us with any data.
So it's just empty it's not empty.
But it doesn't take any arguments and in here we're going to define a couple of things.
Remember that a length list has a pointer to the head of the list.
A pointer to the tail.
Those are just variables and then a length.
And so at the beginning it's not length should be zero.
Also head and tail will be null.
So this dot head equals this tail equals nil.
So we've now defined the basics.
Here are two constructors that are actually done.
We're not going to change those.
What we are going to work on is adding a bunch of methods into singly linked list.
So what we're going to do in this video is add a push method so push should take a piece of data let's
call it Vau.
So I should be able to do this list.
Push.
Hello.
And it should assign a new node should it create a new node like we did over here and assign it to the
head of the list.
And also the tail because there's nothing in here.
And then if we push something in again it should now assign goodbye to be the tail of the list and have
it the head hollow point to the tail of goodbye.
So if we were to visualize how push would work right now we have an empty length list.
And if I try to insert.
So push means inserting at the end.
So we're going to go with this option after the tail.
So if I insert 80 at the beginning it's super easy because we just set the head and the tail to be 80.
But now Phi inserts something else at the end.
Let's go with 100.
OK.
I guess that's too high.
Let's go with 81.
All that we do now is take the head and have the next property point to 81 and then we set the tail
to be 81.
All right one more.
Let's do eighty five.
Go and real high here.
So I mean insert this at the end.
All we have to do is take the current tail and point it to 85 and then update that to be the tail.
So inserting pushing to the end of a list is super easy.
If we have a thousand or a million items in here we don't traverse the whole thing as long as we're
keeping track of the last item in the list.
All we have to do is say hey take that last item pointed over to this new last item and now the tail
is we update the tail to be the very end 85.
So here's some pseudo code.
If you would like to try and implement this on your own in the next video of go through a solution.
So we're going to implement a push method I already defined the skeleton here.
All it needs to do is accept devaluate or to give that to you create a new node using that value that
we passed it.
So if we pass in 50 you should make a new node where the value of that notice 50.
Now there's a special edge case if there is no head.
If Meaning if a list is empty set the head and the tail to be that newly created node.
That's the first thing we saw over here where we had an empty list when we added in aty the head and
tail both pointed to 80.
Otherwise if there is a head set the next property on the tail to be the new node and then update the
tail property to be the newly created node.
Once again if we added one more thing in here this is our current tail if we add in 90.
All that would do is take the current tail pointed to the new node with 90 and then set the tail to
be 90 and then finally increment the length by 1.
We are keeping track at full length.
So add 1 because we're pushing something in.
All right.
So those are the basic steps.
Give it a shot if you'd like in the next video.
Obvious solution.
If you do get stuck.
Don't be hard on yourself if you've never seen like this before.
I recommend attempting as much as you can get through the section and then if you have time or the energy
at some point go through all the exercises and try them from scratch and see if you can replicate it.
Nobody's expecting you to get everything right.
The very first time through.
OK.
The next video will be a solution to push.