All right.
So let's write up the solution to push.
If you don't care about it if you already got it and just check your work.
Just look at the file included with this video.
OK.
So I made a new snippet just so we can keep track of.
The first one I'm going to do this for every single function or method we add.
Anyway here's push.
We already have a skeleton.
So this first bit is done should accept the value.
Now what we need to do is create a new node using the value we pass in.
So that's easy enough.
We have our node class.
We just need to make a variable of us call it new node equals new space node pass in the value.
So for example when we call when we make a new list I'll just give it the name list it's empty.
Then we do a list of push Hello it's going to take that string hello and make a new node.
It's not added two of us had to just exists.
Next we need to check if there is a head property on the list.
If there is set the head and tail to be the newly created node that's the edge case when it's empty.
So to check that we could just do if this head to actually do if not this data.
So if there is no head meaning it's an empty list like it is right here.
What do we want to do going to make this head equal to new node.
And then we'll set this tale to be the same thing.
We could just do this that tail equals the stuff that makes sense.
So they're both pointing to new node the head and the tail are the same thing.
So right now push will work one time only the first time.
And if we look at lists that just read the code we can see that.
OK.
Well first of all the length is incorrect correct needs to be updated.
It says zero still.
But otherwise the head and the tail are pointing to the right thing.
But if I push something else in like goodbye nothing will happen because I do stop push 10 or 1.
Nothing happens because it's all guarded by this if statement which this is not true anymore.
So nothing happens except we make a new node and it just never gets added.
So onto the next part which is otherwise set the next property on the tail to be the new node.
Instead the tail property in the list to be the newly created node.
So this only runs if it's empty.
Otherwise what we want to do is take the tail so take the current tail tail take the next property and
set that equal to the new node.
So if I have hello as the tail and I push goodbye we're going to take goodbye's the new node take the
current tail Hello set the next to be goodbye and then we just have to update this tail to point to
that new node like that.
That's our new tail.
OK.
So we took the current two we added on to the end of it and then we move the tail marker over.
And then the last two things we need to do is we need to increment the length by one and the last thing
return of the.
I didn't actually click that far in the last video.
I apologize.
We do need to return it.
So let's go back and do that now.
We're just going to increment the length of this delta length plus we'll just do plus plus and then
return.
How do we return the whole list just returned this and that should be all we need to do.
So if I'm going to get rid of this for now and just call it I'm going to rerun my code.
OK.
If we look at a list right now it's empty all do list up push let's push in high.
OK so now the head and the tail are both pointing to high.
Cool.
Now we do list up push.
I you I don't know this makes no sense if we look at the head.
It should still be high.
And if you look at the tail it's you and our length is two.
So that's all working.
So just let's just do one more stop push you let's push in the number ninety nine and we look at list.
The head is high the tail is 99.
So if I did list that head next that gives me you next Again that gives me 99.
And then there is no next call.
So push is done.
This is the basics of pushing onto a list.
We have the one edge case if it's empty.
Otherwise we just take the current tail.
It's nice and easy.
It doesn't matter if it's a million items in here it's really fast.
We just take the tail and add on to the end and then move the tail one spot over.
OK.
So let's push in the next video.
We're going to get into pop and pop is a little trickier and you'll see why.