They Hey welcome back.
Our next method to implement is pop.
So just like on an array a pop a pop when we call pop it removes from the end of full length list.
It takes the last item on the tail and returns it to us.
Now that seems simple because we're keeping track of the last item the tail.
So we we should just be able to return it.
The problem is to remove it we have to assign a new tail.
And that involves going all the way through the lists from the beginning because we don't have a backwards
pointer.
We can't just take the tail and say Give me the one before this.
That's not how singly length singly length list is set up.
If we look at visual algo again if we try and pop off of this we just say take the last item off but
we have the tail we know it's 90.
I could give you the last item very easy easily but to then update the tail here.
Otherwise we're not actually popping it off or just getting the last item to move the tail here.
We have to start at the beginning go to the next go to the next and go to the second to last item and
make that the new tail.
So if we insert Let's walk through this.
No he's not inserting let's remove.
We want to remove from the tail.
So that would be popping.
We go to the second to last item.
All right so we found it.
Let me slow this down a little bit.
And rerun this.
If you want you can look at that code on the right but I'm going to walk through let's go step by step.
OK.
So we start at the beginning.
We go to the next thing.
That's not the end.
And we have two variables because we need to keep track of the second to last item.
And how do we know with the second to last item is.
Well if we have the first variable in the end so we have this sort of like offset by 1 1 node.
So we have this one variable called pre or previous node or second to last.
It doesn't matter or new tail and that's going to keep track of what we're actually going to set the
table to be.
And we're just trying to find the second to last item.
OK.
So we have now found the second to last item.
So we remove 85 and all that that means is taking this item next.
Setting it to know that severs the link and then we return.
We take this and save it to a variable so we can return it and then we set this to be the new tail.
Does that make sense.
Hopefully it's a little more complicated and I'll go walk to the pseudo code.
But the first thing that we have to be able to do is traverse our list so to traverse it it's not that
bad.
All that we do is start at the beginning using the head and then we can loop and keep going.
While there is a dot next.
So this isn't the solution but if I wanted to make a method called traverse all that we would need to
do.
Let's say I just wanted to print out every item in the list.
So we're going to start with a variable.
Let's just call it current.
If I can spell equals this head.
So we start with the beginning and we can do a while loop for loop.
You could use the length and do a for loop.
I'm going to do a while loop and just say while there is a current just like that we're going to say
print no not print come to log current Val and then we need to update current equals the next off of
current.
That makes it keep saying does that make sense.
Probably not.
It's confusing.
So we started the head.
If we have hello goodbye and let's do exclamation point at the end like this if we started the head
we're going to set current to be this node.
Hello.
And we're going to cancel that log hello then we're going to change current to be current next.
Which means it's now goodbye.
The loop starts over.
This is still true.
So we counted that log goodbye.
Now current is current up next which is exclamation point it starts over.
Still true.
We print exclamation point.
Then we set current to be current.
Next.
There is no next to no.
So this loop now is done.
And if we tried running this can
and if we tried running this to do list traverse up I have three hours.
Hopefully you saw that before me.
Try this one more time.
Rerun it would do list of Traverse again.
All right.
So we get hello goodbye.
Exclamation point.
Nothing's returned so we get undefined.
So that's one way of traversing a list.
And we're going to need to do something like this in order to figure out the new tail.
Now there's a slight distinction which is we don't want to get all the way to the end of the list.
We need to get to the second to last item and we don't need to print anything out.
So I'm going to actually comment this out.
We're not using this in our code.
I just wanted to show you one way of traversing.
OK.
So if you want to try this on your own.
First thing you need to do is define.
I didn't at this time to find a function called Pop and it doesn't take in any variable or any data
right.
It just pops the last thing every time.
If there's nothing in the list.
Nice and easy return undefined.
So you could check if there is no head.
Or you could check if the length is zero.
Whatever metric you use return undefined if it's empty.
Otherwise loop through the entire list until you reach the tail.
But it's not that simple because what we're actually doing is trying to get the thing right before the
tail.
So loop through until you get the tail but also have a variable that keeps track of whatever the last
item was like we saw in visual algo where we all this is a bad example.
If I go back and I go back here here we go.
So we have two variables and we're getting to the end with this one called temp and then prae is always
one.
It's like getting one item one node behind that that's going to give us the second to last item what
once temp hits the end.
All right.
So we just set the next property of the second to last known to be no and then update that tail to be
that second to last node.
And then we subtract one from the length and return the node that was removed.
So that is important and it's stored in a variable.
So you can return it.
OK.
So that's pop.
This one actually pushes pretty straight forward I think Pop is one of the trickier ones.
Some of the other things we'll see later on are actually easier.
It's just that push and pop go together.
So I felt bad about splitting them up.
Anyway give it a shot.
Don't feel bad if you get stuck.