So second attempt at this video I recorded the whole thing or I thought I did.
But Mike was muted so giving it a second chance.
We're going to write pop the very first thing we need to do is define the method.
Pop takes two arguments and then we'll start with the edge case.
If there are no notes in the list return undefined.
OK so let's define pop and check if there are no nodes.
We have a couple of ways of doing this.
May clear down here.
We could check if the length is zero or I'm going to check if there is no head.
So if no this head if.
If not the stud head or the start tail just return undefined.
We can do it on one line.
Nice and easy.
So the next piece is loop through the list until you reach the tail.
Except really we're trying to find the tail.
And the second to last thing that comes right before the tail.
So when we loop we're going to have two variables one that's going to be called I don't know current.
It doesn't really matter.
Just the thing that is going to hit the end and then two which will call previous or I like to call
it new tail because it's what is going to become the tail.
Right.
If our list looks like this.
Hello goodbye.
Exclamation point.
We're going to start at the beginning.
They're both going to point here current and new tail and T.
Right.
And we're going to loop through and I'm going to move current appear and check.
Is this the end of the list.
Nope.
It's not.
So we move Nutella.
Then I'm going to move current up again and check.
All right.
Is this the end of the list.
And it is.
So I don't move new tail.
And this tells me that this is my new tail so I'm going to pop this off by severing this hero and then
I'm going to make this the tail.
So that's kind of our workflow here to reset them back to the starting gate.
I think it deleted a bracket over here.
OK.
So to do that loop McCalmont that out not valid javascript is it.
What I'm going to do is start by making those two variables.
So var current and I'm going to start at the top of this head and then I'm going to make my other variable
called new tail and I'll set it to be current.
The same thing at the beginning.
They both started at the very beginning.
Now we loop over.
So from the last video I showed you one way of doing this.
I'm going to do.
While current dot next that means while there is something so if current is goodbye is there a next
yes but when current is exclamation point there is no next.
And that's when we're going to stop.
There's a couple of ways of writing this code.
If you didn't do current Up next you made it work.
If it's if it works it's totally valid.
OK.
And although we're going to do is set new tale to equal current and then move current forward one
so new tale is always lagging behind new tail set to whatever current was and then to move current one
forward and we keep going until there is nowhere for current to move forward to.
So with the end of this if I just did a comparable log current Vau and then counsel that log new tail
Vau you'll see if i do list up pop we end up with current exclamation point Noad and goodbye new tail
as the previous one goodbye.
It's the one right before it.
Okay.
So that get to what we want at the end of this list.
Current new tail are the correct values.
So now all we need to do is move the tail.
This tail is now pointing to new tail.
So at the end of our little simulation current is referencing this right here and new tail references
goodbye.
So all we do is say all right this thing right here is the tail.
That's what this does.
Then if we reference this we need to set the new tails next node to be no.
So we'll just do this tale next equals no.
So there's nothing that comes after that severs the connection with exclamation point.
So it's not enough just to say this is our new tail because if it keeps pointing at something then that
doesn't mean it's the end of the list.
So we need to sever the arrow which is what we've done now.
So we have current.
So we know at the very end of this we want to return current.
Okay.
And the other thing we need to do is decrement length length minus minus and this will get us ninety
nine point ninety nine percent of the way there this meets all the requirements and if we test this
out get rid of this for now let's push on this.
OK that should work.
Let's give it a test.
I'm going to refresh my code executed list.
Right now it has three things in there.
It returns to me.
Exclamation point.
And if we look at the list it's now two items long and the tail is goodbye.
All right let's pop one more time.
It returns to me goodbye.
That's correct.
And if you look at list it is now one item line.
OK.
So it seems like it's working let's try pushing something on push.
Ninety nine point nine on the lookout list it's two items long.
The head is hollow the tail is 9 9 9 9.
It gives me that number back.
OK.
So that's all good but if we do list up pop one more time it does pop off the value of hello give me
what I expect.
But if we look at it list it still has a head and a tail but the length has gone down.
So there's a special case when there's one item left in the list and I didn't specify this in the instructions
so most I would expect nobody to catch this unless you actually went through and tested this.
If there's one item there's a problem because we're never setting the tail the head and the tail to
be No.
It should be empty if there is no if there's only one item left and we remove it.
Well we've done that.
But because the way our code works new tail and current are set to be the exact same thing.
So I'm going to show a refactored version of all of this at the end of the section.
But one really simple work around that is it's kind of clunky.
But if we just check if the length of the list is now zero.
So down here if we subtract one from the length we just check.
All right.
Is the list empty now.
So if this length equals equals zero.
Or we could also check if the head is equal to the tail Madieu three equals.
If that's the case we're now just going to say this dot head equals no tail equals nil.
That means that there was one item.
We popped it off and we subtracted one from the length.
So now there is zero items in there.
So we just reset head and tail to be No.
Let's verify that it works.
So we have our list.
If we do list pop first thing gone.
Second thing going right now it is one item long.
So if we pop this time it gives us the correct value.
And if we look at it list it now has the length of zero.
The head is no the tail is small and if we try and pop again we should get undefined.
And the lists should still be zero items.
Often times I have seen this where you know it keeps going into negative numbers.
That's not correct.
We want to be zero.
All right.
So that's my solution to pop.
If he came up with something better more elegant please share it.
I'm going to show you a nice refactor later on that will slim this down significantly to one line by
calling another function another method we're going to define so it can be one line on it's own right
now.
But once we do find this auxiliary auxiliary function it will be shorter anyway.
That's pop.