Hey welcome back.
Next we move on to something nice and easy compared to pop shift.
So shift removes a node from the beginning of the length list so whatever's at the start remove it.
All that really means is taking the head and deleting it and then moving the head over to whatever the
second item was.
So if we visualize it if we go to remove from the beginning from the head all that it really means slow
that down again.
One more time.
Remove from the head.
Actually I posit.
So we take whatever the current head is we need to save it to a variable because we want to return it
and then we take it next and make that the new head and then we sever that connection.
Like that and we return the old head.
So it's really easy.
There could be a million items on the list to insert at the beginning.
It takes constant time.
Always compared to an array where we have to reassign every index.
If there's a million items it's a lot of indices to change over and over and over to cascade and ripple
down on a length list.
It's super simple.
So here's some pseudo code.
If there's no nodes return undefined.
Otherwise store the current head property in a variable then update the head property to be the current
next node so move it over one and then finally document the length by one and return the value of the
node that was removed of the old head.
OK so go ahead and give this a shot if you'd like.
Nice and easy compared to pop in the next video.
I'll have a solution.