OK so let's type this out.
First we need to define shift and it doesn't take any arguments.
And then let's start with this first one liner.
If there's no nodes if it's empty return undefined.
OK.
So down here we'll just do shift and we'll check again there's a lot of ways of doing this.
If this Dalt length is zero if there's no head it doesn't really matter return undefined.
OK next store the current head property in a variable.
So I'm going to make a variable I'll call it current head equals knothead.
This is pointing to in our case below at the beginning then we're going to move the head over to the
current head next node.
So you say this dot head equals the current heads dot next.
So we've saved this to a variable called current head and we say this is the old hood.
Well now the new head is right here.
We take current head next and make that the new head.
All right.
Almost there then we need to document the length by 1.
So this length minus minus.
And then finally return current head which is technically no longer current.
So you could have also called this old head removed head doesn't matter.
This is what we took off.
And if we test it out run our code if i do list that shift we get hello which is the beginning and if
we look at the list now it's two items long in which the head the head is now.
Goodbye.
Let's do it one more time.
We got good bye off.
Now the head if we look at the list again is equal to this head and tail are the same thing.
I will note though if we do list that shift one more time it does give us the right value.
And if we look at list the head is no the tail isn't.
No and that's not really going to be a problem because as soon as we reassign something to the head
as we push something back in the tail will be reassigned.
However if we wanted to fix that if we wanted it to be no we could just add an extra conditional check
and just check you know right here if this basically just copy this code.
Set tail to be null just like that.
So if we refresh our code run it again list that shift shift again.
Right now the list has one item in it which is the exclamation point.
If we shift to a more time and we look at the list it now is NO NO.
Lanc this year so if you try it again we get undefined the lists unchanged the length is still zero.
Let's just make sure we can still push something in let's push 100 in.
We look at the list head and tail are both one hundred push or more thing in one thousand.
Anyway it's working.
All looks good.
Let's pop gives us 1000 list.
That shift gives us 100 and list is now empty.
Perfect.
All right.
So that's shift.