All right we'll come back and this video we're working on adding another shift to our singly linked
list.
So upshift is a way to add a node to the list.
However unlike push it adds to the beginning of the list.
And fortunately it's pretty easy because of the way the singly link first works works.
We already have the head.
All we have to do is say Here is a new head and pointed to the old head.
So if we walked through it over here let's do an insert at the beginning to insert the number.
No there we go 13.
OK I'm going to posit.
So all we do is we have the old head and we now point the new head at the head and then move the head
to be the new head.
It's kind of confusing when I keep saying all that new head but we just take this old pointer and the
value there we take the new node pointed at that and then set this to be the head.
And that's it.
So if we were to walk through the pseudo code to find the function accepts the value that you're going
to add to the beginning you're shifting or you're shifting.
So we create a new node just like we did with Bush.
We need to check if there is no head.
Then we set the head and tail to be the new node.
Otherwise set the newly created nodes next property to be the current head and then move the head to
be that newly created node and then increment the length the list by 1 and finally return the linked
list.
OK.
So try and do this on your own if you'd like.
In the next video as I have been doing this whole section I'll have a solution.
All right.
That's coming up next.