All right.
So let's get to work writing and shift.
So you go over to my snippet and I'm just going to define on shift which takes a value that we're adding
in and the first thing we need to do is make a new node.
So I'll just do var new node equals new node and pass in that value.
OK once you've done that we now need to check our edge case which is if there's no property so we'll
just do if there's not ahead.
In that case we set both the head and the tail to be that new node.
So do this head equals new node tail equals new node or godhead just like that.
They're now both set to the new node.
If there was nothing in the list to start after that.
Otherwise we're going to set the newly created nodes next to property to be the current property on
the list.
So if this is what our linked list looks like right now.
Hello is the head.
If we added something to the beginning let's just say it was a star.
For some reason and this is still the head all we do is we take this new node and we point it at the
head.
So that's just a matter of saying new node dot next equals this dot head.
So that gives us this connection but this is still the head.
So then we need to update the head.
So we just say this dumbhead equals new node.
And then that effectively moves our head over here and that's all we have to do.
So no matter how long our list is.
Again I've been saying this a couple times.
If it's a million items long it's just one little thing we have to do.
Unlike an array even though us humans don't have to do anything behind the scenes.
If we add something to the beginning of an array of two million items long the entire thing has to be
re-index every single item gets a new index and that's not good.
So I think all we have left to do is to increment the length of the list and then return the list.
So we'll do this at length plus plus return the whole return this.
Let's test it out.
So you get rid of that.
We've created our list here.
I execute the code.
So we have our list.
It's three items long legs due in shift of I don't know I'm going to write first.
Looks like I have a typo in here.
Ah.
If not this head.
Hopefully you saw that before me.
Let's rerun this code one more time.
OK.
List has three items and shift first looks like it's working.
Well actually we can't tell from this it added something in.
Indeed the head is first and it's pointing to Halo which is pointed to by which is pointing to exclamation
point which points to nothing.
Now there is one issue with our code that only becomes clear when we have an empty list.
So I'm going to do pop a couple of.
I guess that's a dumb way to make an empty list but that's one way to do it.
Just pop everything out there.
Or you know you could just start from an empty list.
But I didn't think of that.
So we have our empty list now.
If I shifted list on shift let's say add me it looks like it works the head and a tail are both set
correctly but the next property on the head and the next property on the tail are actually self referential.
You can keep clicking next and it's always pointing to at me.
So this is wrong.
Now as soon as we shift to something else let's shift one hundred and we look at list.
Now the head is one hundred and it's pointing to add me but add me is still pointing to add me over
and over and over.
And our table is still set up like that.
But if I push something at the very end and we look at it now it should be fixed.
If we look at our head or to the next is add me and it's next.
And.
OK.
So it's not the end of the world but it's not good.
We don't want that.
And it's happening because of this logic right here.
It's a very small change that we need to make.
Right now we have an if statement to check if the list is empty if there's no head.
And then we have this other code that always runs.
In reality it should be.
And it's actually in the pseudo code it says if there's no head do this if it's empty.
Otherwise meaning else.
And we don't have that else right now because what's happening there is without the else we are setting
the head in the tail to be the new node.
If it's an empty list we go back let's just do.
L equals new singly length first Ellas empty right now.
If I do Elda on shift hello It sets the head and tail to be hello and then without this.
Else here it takes Hello next instead to the head which is hello.
So we're saying hello Nexus Hello.
And then it said to the head to be hello which is not what we want.
It's already set to that.
So we add the else in.
So this code only runs when there's at least one thing in here in the list.
This code only runs if it's empty.
And then this code run runs needs to run in either scenario.
So let's try refreshing running it again.
This is a very stupid way of doing this.
OK let's start on shift.
Add me.
If we look at this now it still works but there is no next set on me.
It's set up correctly.
All right.
A tiny change but important.
That is an shift.
Next up we're going to take a look at some other methods that have to do with retrieving values based
off of a position or an index called Get set.
And these are a little bit trickier.