All right welcome back.
So next we're going to add or implement get so get a method that takes a number an index or a position
and it returns the item in that position.
So if we give it the number 0 it should give us the first item the head.
But if we give it the number 4 it should give us the fifth item.
So starting at zero.
But that's not really the important part the important part is takes in the number and you traverse
the list that many times and then you return the item at that index.
So visual fish fish will go fish.
It has to be a visual go so only way could pronounce it.
It doesn't have a built in get method that it illustrates.
But if we just looked at this list we can sort of mouse through it.
So if we pass in we get.
And then we pass in the number three.
Basically we start at the beginning.
This is number zero the head.
And then we just do it next.
And we keep doing next until we've done it three times.
So zero to 1 1 to 2 2 to 3.
And so we'd return this value which is six.
So there are no indices that are that correspond to each individual item.
It's not like we can just access and get you know the seven hundred item immediately.
We have to start at zero.
The very beginning the head and count how many times we do.
Next we have to loop until we hit that item.
So whenever we say index in this video it is not like an array that has a built in index that corresponds
to every element we are manually counting.
So it's not that efficient compared to an array.
If we need to access something based off of it's position all the time then you might want to use an
array.
It depends.
Again we'll come back to considerations like that later on.
So here's a pseudo code function should accept an index.
So a number that we pass in if the index is so these are edge cases.
If it's negative or greater than or equal to the length then we're not going to do that.
We can't find something that index negative 2.
So we return.
No.
Or we could do undefined but just return something that signifies it was not found.
Then we're going to loop through the list until you reach the index.
In return the noted that specific index.
So I recommend having a counter variable and you just loop through continue like we've done with a WHILE
loop for loop doing next.
Next up next and each time through just add one to the counter.
And then once you get to that however many you know the index the fifth item the tenth item.
All you do is return the value.
So give it a shot in the next video.
I'll implement it.
Surprise surprise.