OK let's get going with get.
So we're going to define it down here and it takes an index and the first thing we need to do is check
if the index is valid.
So if it's not valid meaning it's negative or greater than or equal to the length of the list return.
No.
So if index is less than zero or index is greater than or equal to this dot like return and no undefined
it doesn't really matter to me.
We'll do no.
So we have that out of the way.
Otherwise what we need to do let's say somebody's past is in the index of three I added in a couple
of items here.
So we now have five index of three.
That means 0 1 2 3.
We want the heart pack is what we should get.
So to do that we need to start here and basically count with a counter starting at zero and continue
to traverse one at a time while adding one to our counter so we go 0 to 1 and then we would add one
again when we traverse to this to give us 2 and then add 1 to our counter which is 3 at which point
we would stop it because our counter was equal to the index 3.
So I'll make a variable called counter started at zero or count it doesn't matter.
Then I'll make a variable called current to start at the head.
This is what will keep track of our current position as we traverse and then current is what we will
return.
So I'm going to start with a WHILE loop while and we'll just do while counter is not equal to index.
So at the beginning if we called Get three counters start to zero they're not equal.
So what are we do we just add one to counter and we change current to now equal current next and then
add 1 to counter.
Okay.
So we go through this and this is actually all we need to traverse it.
There's only one thing we're missing at the very end which is return current.
So if we step through this we're going to have at the very beginning current equals this and then I'll
just visualize it here's our counter.
All right.
So very first time through current is equal to the head counter is zero and our index that we're looking
for is 3.
So we need the loop runs we change current to now be this and we add one to counter.
So it's one.
OK.
We keep going through because counting is not equal to 3.
So we move current down to the exclamation point node and that means that we add 1 to counter which
is now 2.
Still this is true.
So we run it again.
So we move current down one more time and we add one to counter.
At which point counter is now equal to the index if we're looking for 3 then all we do is return current
which is this node.
All right.
Let's test it out.
So we have our list which has five things let's do list does get index zero which should give me hello.
The first thing let's try negative one shouldn't work let's try 100 doesn't work.
How about three.
So that gives me the heart and the did for that should give me a smiley face if we do five.
There should be nothing there but if we push something on let's do a dollar sign Friday list does get
five.
Now it works but six won't work.
OK.
So that's a solution or a solution to get.
Next we're going to work with its counterpart which is set.