All right.
Next up we're working with the set.
So set is a method that will accept two things a position or an index and a value to update the item
at that index too.
So we would pass in for example this visual go doesn't actually have the capability to illustrate this
but if I were to say this list don't set one as the index comma.
Hello world what that is saying is take whatever that index 1 says 0 1 Take this node and update or
change its value set it to Hello World.
So to make it work you need to define a function that accepts two things a value and an index.
I actually like to put the index first.
So I should have written an index and a value but it doesn't matter as long as you are consistent.
And we can actually use our GET method that we just defined in the last video to help us out.
So we're going to use our get function to find that node or if it's not there or get function we'll
handle it.
For example if you tried to update the negative 10 item but it should return to us the found node and
then we just updated value.
So if the node is not found return false if the node is found update its value and then return true.
So it's a nice short one.
It's like four or five lines I think.
So in the next video we'll have a solution ready set go.