All right we are all set to implement that.
Yeah.
All right.
So I'm going to hop over here and I'm going to add my method set which takes two things the index and
then a new value to set it to.
And all we need to do is call our GET method with that index.
This does get with the index that was provided set it equal to a variable civil which we'll call it
found node.
And we're just going to check if that returns something valid or not.
I don't know what I'm doing that for.
It was already indented properly just fidgeting.
So get we'll take care of it.
And it's either going to return to us no or the actual node.
So if it's found in just you if found node all that we need to do is update found node vowel equals
the value that was passed in here and then returned true otherwise return false.
We don't need to do the return.
Else we don't need to do else return false because it's only one or the other either or.
OK.
And that's actually it.
So it's nice and easy because we have this method already defined.
But let's test it out.
So we've got all this here let's do well let's run the code and I'll do list doesn't get.
What's the item at index 2.
All right.
It's an exclamation point.
Let's now set it list.
Set at index to to be triple bang triple exclamation point.
And if we look at the list and we look at list doesn't get indexed to now it's triple exclamation points.
However if I try and do list data set something in index I don't know six doesn't exist.
So it's false.
And if we look at our list and we do let's just look at the tail.
The last thing is still the smiley face.
What else could we do here let's do list set negative 1 and set that to be Hellawell.
It's not going to work because our method is rejecting it returns no.
So we return false and that's all there is to set.
Nice and easy hopefully.