Welcome back.
Next up is insert so insert is sort of like set in that it takes two pieces of data.
It takes an index and a value.
However instead of updating an existing node insert is going to insert a new node at whatever position
we specify.
So for example I could call on this list insert at position to the number 17 in which case we would
go 0 1 2.
So we would put the number 17 a new node right here and would connect this node to it and then connect
it to 77.
So let's actually do that.
So this allows me to insert at the beginning and shift it or push to the end after the tail.
Here I can insert out a specific Index index of two I said 17 and posit.
OK.
So what we want to do if we pass an index of two we want to find the item an index of 1.
And we're going to connect that to our new node.
So for inserting 17 OK here we found index of 2.
So we know we need to insert between these two things.
And so we take our new node which is 17 that's the value and we're going to have it point at 77 so we
hook it up one way and then we need to change this so that the prior node is pointing at the one we
just inserted like that.
OK.
So it can't.
This is can be a little more complicated than some of the other methods but we also can make use of
methods we've already built.
So let's talk about how you can define a function.
It takes two things in the index in the value.
And if the index is less than zero or greater than the length return false because we can't insert something
there.
Notice that it's greater than the length not greater than or equal to.
Because if the index is the same as the length that means just inserted at the end in which case your
code can just rely or call upon your existing push method.
So if we're trying to insert something at the end just use push don't rewrite it.
Same thing if it's trying to be inserted or if someone is trying to insert something an index of 0.
Use your unshipped method.
Don't rewrite that logic.
So the first little bit of the method can be a couple of conditional statements so if none of these
are true it means that the index is somewhere in the middle of our list let's say index of 3.
What we want to do is basically find the item an index of 2 and we have a really easy way of doing that.
Now we have that get method we built so we can just call get but pass in the index minus 1.
So instead of get of the index we want the item before.
So remember if I was trying to insert 17 index of 2 0 1 2 we could call get on index of 1 which would
give us this node right here.
Then all that we need to do once we have the previous node the one right before where we're trying to
insert we take that previous node and we said it's next to be the newly created node which I didn't
specify you need to create a new node but you do.
So we create the new node we find the one right before using get and we connect that sort of pathway
from the previous one to the new node.
Then we have to connect the new node to the old next node.
Right.
So if we find this here this is our old one.
We need to connect this to this and this to this.
Now the order they go in.
It doesn't matter which one you do.
You just might need to use a temporary placeholder or variable.
OK.
So then the final thing is to increment the length because we've inserted something and then return
true.
So one quick note.
Ideally your method will return only true or false.
So if the insert was successful it returns true if it was unsuccessful it returns false.
The problem is that if we're going to rely on our push method and our unshipped method for example those
don't return true or false.
So if you want to get fancy you could coerce the return value of push.
And of upshift to be a boolean true or false.
But don't worry about that honestly I'll show you a really quick way of doing that in the solution but
it's just a note that to make this a little nicer it should always return true or false.
OK.
Insert is probably one of the trickier ones so give yourself a break if you can't get it.
Well see in the next video.