OK so let's get defining insert.
So it takes an index and a value.
And the first thing we want to check is if it's a ridiculous value if it's negative or if it's greater
than the like so we'll just do.
If index is less than zero zero is OK but if it's less than zero that's not ok.
Or if index is greater than this length and it's OK if it's equal to the wavelength.
That just means insert at the very end.
So even in this scenario the greatest index is 3 right 0 1 2 3 if we wanted to insert at 4 that's OK.
Even though there is no current index for it.
So if that's the case let's return false.
OK so that's if there's a problem.
Next we have.
If the index is equal to the length.
So if index equals this length what do we do in that case.
Well we'll just do this dot.
Push the value OK.
And I'm just going to return that and we'll come back to this because push on its own.
If we pass in a value we go all the way back up where are you.
It doesn't return true or false returns the whole list.
So if we wanted to make everything true or false in this method we have a little work to do but let's
leave it for now because we have another scenario which is if the index is zero.
So if index is equal to zero what do we want to do.
We're going to call this dot and shift with the valve that inserts at the beginning and we'll also return
that but and shift doesn't return true or false or returns the entire list.
So we need to address that later.
But functionally this should work.
So if it's invalid return false.
If the index is equal to the length call push with the value push it to the end.
If the index is equal to zero call an shift added to the beginning.
OK so now we have the rest of the logic.
This means that the index is somewhere in the middle of our list let's say index of 2 which would give
us this 0 1 2 right here.
OK.
So we need to find the item right before it.
So we can just use our Get index minus one and save that to a variable.
I'll call it previous.
Right.
So that is going to use get which we defined up here and it's going to give us the item break before
it.
So if we're trying to insert here it will give us this note.
So once we have the previous The other thing we need to do sooner rather than later is make our new
node.
So we'll call it new node equals new node and pass in that value.
OK so now we just need to connect previous to our new node and new node 2 whatever came after previous.
So if this is previous we're going to put our new node right here and connect previous to new node new
node 2 this.
Now the thing is if we just went right ahead and did previous next equals new node there's a problem
which is we are erasing the connection to this node because all that we had connecting this node to
this one was next on this.
Right next is equal to this.
So if I change previous next to be our new node like this and I try and set new node this is gone because
it used to be right here so I need to use a placeholder variable.
So I'll just make one called I temp var temp equals the current previous dot next.
So I'm just saving whatever was in there.
All right.
So we've now set previous next to be the new node.
So we've connected one part of it.
Then we just need to set new node next to equal temp which is just holding what used to come after it.
So if this is where we're inserting it right here this is previous.
OK.
And so we're saving this to a temporary variable right here and we're just inserting the new note here
and we're saying previous dot next is new node new node.
Next is temp and that's just place holding it.
So now we have 2 0 5 or whatever the number is we're trying to insert 225.
I think what I said anyway.
So all we have left to do now is add 1 to the length.
So this dupped length plus plus and we need to return true because that means it works OK.
So if we run this code right now if we look at our list right now it's four items long.
If we want to insert index zero do list out insert zero and let's insert just the string first.
If we look at our list the first thing is now first and that points to 100 which is the old head.
All right.
So if we do get what's the last index we have in there I think it's four right now.
Let's get four is the last thing if we did five.
There's nothing there.
So if we do an insert at index 5 the string last.
This should add something to the very end which will trigger our push rate here.
Notice that what we get back.
Well it works.
But what we're getting back is the whole list.
And I I I mentioned it would be nice to get true or false because if we do list insert at index 1 I
don't know.
Insert thirty seven at index of one.
It gives us true.
If I do list insert negative 1 or negative to something it gives me false if I insert at index 100 It
gives me false.
So it would be nice if it was consistent and always gave me true if the insert worked.
So there's a simple way to change that.
If you didn't want to expand these into separate like you could do this right.
If index equals this length do brackets here multi-line and then move this inside and say this stop
push vowel and you could just do you know return true for example and we could do the same thing down
here.
Or we can do that sort of sneaky thing which is to put double banks to double the negate whatever comes
back from push or from unshipped.
So that means it's a boolean operator not.
So if we just had a string like high if we do not high.
No not like that.
It's going to give us the it's going to coerce it to a boolean value.
Give us the opposite of it.
So if we do bang bang it gives us true.
If it's truth the bang bang of two it's true but bang bang of zero is false.
So this is just a way of converting this to a boolean.
This push is going to return the entire list and shift returns the entire list.
So if we coerce it to a boolean it should just return true.
So let's test it out and just rerun the code.
If we'd now do a list insert an index of 0 first.
It gives us true if we do with the end of the list.
What is our last index right now.
Let's get it for.
OK.
So if we did 5 it would be the last thing.
So if we do list insert at 5 last it gives us true versus insert at one hundred.
It's not going to work.
It gives us false.
OK.
So that's insert.
Personally I would sort of put this on its new little new section just to separate these edge cases
out.
I think that's all I want to cover here.
So that's insert a little more complicated.
Next we're going to talk about Remove which is sort of like a sister to insert.
That's coming up next.