Hey welcome back.
So we're talking about a method called for move.
We're almost done with singly linked lists.
I promise.
Remove takes in an index and it removes the value at that index and it matches up the list around it.
So if you were to remove from the beginning just take out the last item right.
My gosh takes the first item.
If you remove from the very end it takes the last item.
But if you removed from the middle it's a little more complicated.
So if we take an example if we remove the index of one from here all we have to do is first find that
item.
This is the one that's going to be deleted.
Index of 1 0 1 and we take it out.
But to do that all it really means is taking the previous one and setting it next to the deleted ones
next.
So set this next to this.
So here's a pseudo code to find a function should accept an index if the index is negative or it's greater
than the length return undefined.
Or something.
No.
Whatever you want if the index is the same the length minus one.
So technically this should be greater than or equal to the length because you can't remove you know
if there's five items the length is going to be five.
But the greatest index is four.
So we can't remove from five.
We can only remove from 4.
So if the index is the same as the length minus one you want a pop.
Just use our pop method we've already written.
Same thing with the beginning if the index is equal to zero.
Use our shift method.
Otherwise use our Get method sort of what we did in the last video where we used to get.
But we passed an index minus one to get the previous node and then we just set the next property on
the previous node to be the next of the next node.
And then we subtract one from the length and returned the value of the removed node.
So give it a shot in the next video.
Surprise surprise will have a solution.