All right.
So let's write a solution for Remove going to hop over to my snippet and we'll define remove which takes
an index and the very first thing it needs to do is check if that index is valid.
So if it if the index is negative if it's less than zero or if the index is greater than or equal to
the length what do we do we return no or undefined it doesn't really matter.
Just something bad.
Yes he could return false too.
If the index is zero we're going to return this dot shift.
That means remove the first thing and if the index is the length minus one.
If it's the last item then we return this top up.
OK so those are the three edge cases.
Then we have the rest of the logic.
So this means if we get to this point and we haven't returned yet it's somewhere in the middle of the
list that we're trying to remove.
So we need to find the previous node.
So let's make a variable called previous node equals.
This get index minus 1.
So retrieve the value of retrieve the Node 1 before.
What we're trying to remove then what I'm going to do is make a node a variable called removed and it's
going to store a previous node next.
So this is what we're going to return to the very end.
Can actually just do that now.
Return removed but it's not removed yet.
So now all we need to do is set previous node next equals removed next.
So if we're trying to remove this right here we find the previous Node 2 0 1 and we make a variable
called removed and we set it equal to this dot next.
So this is going to be in our removed variable.
Then we take the previous node next and set it to removed next.
So we take this and said it's next to this.
At which point this is out of the picture we have it in a variable so we can return it at the end.
But we also need to before that.
Subtract one from the length.
So this dot length minus minus and that should do it for us.
Let's try executing it let's do list.
Does it remove the first item.
So that gives us 100 and the list now starts at 2 0 1.
Let's remove from the end remove.
Actually that's do from the middle first let's do index of 2.
So that should be if we remove this index of 2.
It's going to be the last thing isn't it.
OK that's two index of one.
So that should give us 250 and it does.
And if we look at the list now it has 2 items in it 201 and 350.
Let's do.
Let's remove the last item index of 1 cool so that called Pop.
And if you look at the list now it has one item left let's do list.
Remove the zero with item and we look at the list.
It's empty now.
Try and remove something that isn't in there that's not going to work.
Have it a positive number.
Cool.
So that is remove.