Hey we'll welcome back.
So next up our final method on our singly linked list is called reverse and this is a really classic
computer science interview question.
I'm not sure why.
To be honest because in my experience it's just not very practical.
It's not a very commonly done thing where you have a lengthy list and you need to reverse it.
But it is a pretty common challenge and a lot of textbooks a lot of interview prep books.
So you take a length list and you reverse it in place so you don't make a copy.
That's a little easier.
You don't make a duplicate and return that.
You do it in place so you traverse as you go you reverse things traverse and reverse.
So here's what it looks like.
I couldn't find a little animation to use or a way of visualizing it so I made my own sort of ugly attempt.
So if this is sort of linked list singly linked list we have our head in our tail and a bunch of next
pointers if we want to reverse it.
Basically what we're going to do is start at the beginning.
We can only move one direction.
We can start at the end.
So we start here and we're going to make this the tail and then we build the list backwards from there.
So we do dot next which gives us this node 27.
And we're going to set twenty seven dot next to be 13.
But we also need to keep track of what 2007 does next used to be which is 32.
So we don't just overwrite it.
We need to make a second variable to store the old next which is 32.
So let's say we're on 27.
We're going to store 32 on the side just remember 32 is in a different variable.
Then we take 2007 and we said it's next to be 13.
There we go.
Now we're on 32.
So we take the next of 32 which is 71 and we save 71.
Put that on the side.
Then we take 32 and set it next to B 27 and now we go back to 71.
There is no there's nothing after 71 there's no next.
So we just take it and said it's Dotun XT to be 32 and then this becomes the head.
So as far as the logic it's a pseudocode is it's a little bit tricky to walk through.
I tried to word this in a way that was a little easier to understand but I think your best bet is going
to be to just try this loop through things.
Don't try and follow my instructions exactly because there are other ways doing this and I don't want
you to get too hung up on it.
But with that said here is my pseudo code.
So start off we're reversing in place or you write the method reverse no arguments.
Swap the head the tail then create a variable.
You can call it next.
Again the variable names don't really matter but create a variable called Next.
Another one called previous and then a one of a one a variable called node or current or something and
initialized it to start at the head.
So we would start all the way back here.
This would be our node variable or current and then from there to fast forward we're going to loop through
the list and we're going to set the next variable to be the next property on whatever our current node
is.
So that's what I talked about.
We're going to store the current next so that once we change the dot next to the item that came before
it we haven't lost that connection forever.
So then we're going to set the next property on the node to whatever the previous was and then we set
previous to be the value of the node variable set the node variable to be the value of the next variable.
Like I said trying not to get too lost and hung up on the actual variable names and I debated.
I wasn't sure if this was helpful because it is just so ugly and confusing to read all this text next
previous note and very well sort of walk through that one more time if you want to make sure practice
or review you start and swap the head in the tail.
And from there we take the next to the tail 27 and we're going to store the current data next to 27.
We're going to store a variable called Next to keep track of 32 so that when we take 27 next and we
set it to the previous thing 13 we still have a reference to 32.
So in this scenario 13 would be previous 27 is our current node which I called the node variable and
32 is next.
So you make this connection and then we now set twenty seven to be previous and 32 to be current and
71 to be next.
So we set 32 connect to 27 and then we move our previous variable to be 32 and our node current variable
becomes 71 and we connect them and there is no next.
OK.
I hope I didn't lose anyone with this one.
I know it can be tricky.
Give it a shot.
I'll have a solution coming up.