All right.
So let's implement reverse on our singly linked list.
The first thing I want to show you just to make this a little easier.
I did a method called Prince.
This was not something you were expected to do or I didn't even mention it until now.
But it's just going to make it easier for us to see that our reverse worked because it's kind of annoying
when all that we have is the head or the tail to have to you know iterate over it or check if we did
it correctly because for all we know we might have swapped the head in the tail but the inside might
be totally wrong.
So I made a very timid method called print and it's very very simple.
All it does is it returns.
Eric actually doesn't return anything.
It prints cancels out logs all the values in our linked list in order in an array.
So why an array.
It's kind of defeats the point of using a length this time to turn it into an array.
But it's just the easiest way to print it in one line.
I could have done a string of guessing concatenated everything.
But this is just a super short thing this is not about being efficient.
It's just purely to help us see what's happening.
So with my current list here's the values in there.
If i do list print it just gives me this array and I can see the order that they're in.
So when we do let's start reverse and then print again.
We want to see the opposite order so that we know it worked.
Anyway let's get started on reverse.
So I'll add our reverse method in here.
And the first thing that all do remember we have three variables that we're going to try and keep track
of the current node.
The next variable thing that that's ahead of it and the previous variable the thing that's behind it
that we're going to connect to.
So I have to start somewhere.
I'm going to make my node variable and started at the head head then I'm going to swap the head and
the tail.
So this does head now becomes this tail this tail equals node.
I can't just say this dot tail equals the stuff head because this dot head is now changed.
So I made it.
This is just a shortcut.
Serving as a temporary variable but we're also going to use this node variable in our loop.
So what we need to do now is starter loop and instead of a while loop because I've been doing that in
all of my solutions I'm going to do a for loop just to show you that you can because we're keeping track
of the length.
So I'll do four of our equals zero.
I asked less than this length I plus plus.
So now we have the bulk of our logic where we're going to go through and we've established that this
is node to start.
This is our very beginning.
Now we're going to make a variable called next instead of equal to this node next.
And then we're also going to use a previous variable however at the beginning previous is going to be
null because there's nothing in front of it.
So we'll started at an all but we'll update it as we go.
So let's do that now I'm going to make a variable called previous and that will be null and need the
variable keyword far.
And also do next.
We can set that to no or we could just leave it like this.
The reason we want previous definitely to be know is that we need to make sure that the end of our list
the tail next is no.
We don't want it to be undefined or something else we want know because that's how Currently the tale
is set up.
If there is no next it set to No.
All right.
So now what we do is we go through the list and we save the next variable so we already have next.
Next is going to be equal to whatever we're currently looking at dot next.
So that's what we showed here.
If this is what we're currently looking at we're going to take it next and save it in our next variable
so that we can move on to it in a little bit then what we're going to do is take whatever the previous
value is and set this node next to be that previous value.
So it starts at No.
So the very first time is some very exciting.
We're going to say node next equals previous.
So equals no.
The very first time through but that will change.
Now all we do is we shift things over.
We say OK.
So this was our current node.
Well now our current node is going to be whatever the next node was in our previous node is going to
be whatever the node used to be current used to be.
So that's simple at the end we're just going to say previous now equals the current node and the current
node now equals the next node we just move one thing over and then THAT'S ACTUALLY it.
Let's return this at the end.
We'll verify that this works of course.
I know it can be conceptually confusing.
So we'll try and step through it one time but let's just make sure it works first.
When I run the code and we look at our list print right now looks good.
Let's do that reverse and printed again and let's just make sure 100 to 0 1 to fifty.
Three fifty nine nine nine.
It's totally reversed.
OK.
So what actually happened here.
If we look at the initial state of put this in comments if you understand this I'm not going to teach
anything new here but if you want to walk through and do that right now.
So we started with this and we have three variables that we're keeping track of.
We have one that we're calling node.
We have one that we're calling.
I'm going to do it just like this.
We have Noad previous and next previous starts at no index doesn't really started anything.
It doesn't matter because we assign it right at the beginning.
The very first time through node is equal to this dot head right here.
So now we're going to set next equal to dot next which is 2 0 1.
So this becomes next right here.
Then we say node dot next is actually previous which is not.
So in our new list that we're building we have 100 and we're having it.
Next we're having it point to no.
So there's nothing there.
Then we shift previous to now be 100.
So this is previous.
And then reset node to be what next to us.
So this is now Noad.
And then we start the process over OK.
So then we go next equals Noad next.
Well here's Noad so no doubt next gives us 250 node next.
It's now reset to be previous.
So that means 2 0 1 dot next is going to be 100 which is the current value previous So that's the same
as us drawing this arrow right here we're connecting to one dot next to the rest of the list.
Then we update previous to be the node.
So this becomes previous Then we set node to be next.
So 250 becomes our node and we start over again.
You can drop out of this video at any point but if you'd like to stay in for the long haul we go through
again next equals no dot next.
So this becomes next 350 does node next equals previous.
So now we're connecting to 50 Dunton next to 0 1.
So that's us drawing this arrow.
We're building it backwards one thing at a time.
Now previous equals this node is going to get rid of next for a second and just shift these over previously
called node node equals.
Next we go through again next equals node next.
So that's 9 9 9 node next equals previous or 350.
Next is 250 350 now points to 50 previous equals node.
So we shift all this over just like this.
Perfect.
Now we take next.
Which is going to be no doubt next.
So it's next over here it's it's no there is no doubt next node next ECOs previous.
So this node next is now equal to 350.
So that's our final connection.
Nine nine nine points to that then.
This doesn't really matter because we're done but previous equals node.
So we shift these all over just like this.
But we're now done in our loop has finished executing.
It doesn't keep going because we used a for loop based off of the length.
This loop runs five times.
One two three four five.
If our list is five items long and looks like we're done what am saying.
We are done.
It works.
We can just double check one more time let's do list print and then we do list that reverse the stop
print again opposite order.
Let's look at the head should be set up correctly and then look at the tail.
It should have no as it's next.
OK that was a tough one I know is a tough one for me to explain at least.
Hopefully you were able to understand what I was saying.
OK.