Welcome back to the last video on linked lists or on singly linked lists.
Excuse me.
Next we're talking about doubly linked to lists but we're done with singly linked lists and I'm getting
real tired of saying that word right now.
So let's wrap up by talking about the Big-O notation of the common operations things like insertion
deletion or removal searching and accessing data and also compare it to an array.
And then we'll do a quick recap and move on to doubling first.
And at the end of that section we'll do the same thing where we'll compare not only doubling first two
arrays but also to singly linked lists and we'll see their unique strengths and weaknesses.
All right.
So let's start with insertion in a singly linked list inserting things is really easy right.
We either push it onto the very end all that we had to do was take the current and the tail make a new
node and just set the table next to be that new node and then update the tail.
Same thing at the beginning if you want to add something at the very beginning.
We just make a new node and we said it's next to the current head and then move the head.
So it takes constant time.
It doesn't matter if our list is a million items long or 10 items long.
It takes the same amount of work same amount of time to add in a new item.
Now that's not the case with arrays.
Remember that if an array is a thousand or a million items long Let's go with a million and I add something
to the very beginning to the index 0.
I have to shift every single index over and rewrite it all the way down to 1000 or 1 million in one
or if I add to the very end of an array then yes it takes constant time but on average if we were going
to take the average it's 0.
And where is the length of the array.
So singling us win that battle as far as inserting data much faster constant time versus an array where
the average is 0 of and then we get to removal taking things out of full length list.
And this depends on where we are removing from if we're removing from the very beginning.
Super easy.
That's one constant time all that we do is we've already seen we take the current head and we just said
it's next to be the next head and then we take the old head and set it up next to be null.
We chop that tie.
But if we're removing from the very end it becomes difficult in a singly linked list.
If we're popping because we need to find the item right before the last item right before the tail and
that involves iterating the entire list.
So in our best case for removing from the beginning of one of the worst case of moving from the end
there's a million items we're going to have to go.
Well we're not going to go to the million we're going to have to go to one before the millions in order
to remove that last item.
Next up searching.
So searching through a length list if we're looking for a value let's say that we're looking to see
if the list contains ninety nine.
Worst case that's.
Oh.
And where and it's the length the list because it could be the very last thing or the second to last
thing and we would need to start at the very beginning and check every single node.
So as the list grows so does the amount of operations it takes to search for something and the same
is true of accessing getting a certain node out.
If we ask for the tenth node or the hundreds of the millionth node as that number grows as the list
grows so does the number of operations there.
When we compare that to an array an array has random access meaning that it's constant time to access
items once they're indexed so the indexing takes time and insertions can take time.
And so can removals.
But other than that if you're just accessing if you're asking for the tenth or the fiftieth or the zero
with item in an array it takes the same amount of time because of the way that arrays are structured.
So arrays win that battle.
So really to wrap it up singly linked lists excel at insertion and deletion compared to a race.
So if that's something that you're really concerned about and you don't need random access you just
need to have some data represented in a list with an order but you don't need to just access the 50th
item or the millionth item.
You just need to access it in order then a length list might be what you want if you're if you're concerned
about insertion and removal times and you don't care so much about random access.
OK.
All right so let's go let's just recap a couple of things.
So I think this single thing for us are excellent.
Now this is just what I said.
It's an alternative to arrays when insertion and deletion at the beginning are frequently required.
Remember that inserting at the end of an array is not a big deal.
We don't have to re-index anything.
Arrays contain a built in index whereas length lists do not think those are just connections are nodes
that are connected to one another with a dot next with a reference or a pointer.
There is no number there's no index or position.
We can't access things easily using an index.
And the last point that I'll make if you're wondering why would you use this.
Well remember this is a course on data structures and a lot of it is oriented sort of towards teaching
theoretical things.
But that doesn't mean that linguists never have uses or applications.
Well we'll discuss more as we go.
We're going to learn about some more specialized data structures that are built on top of linked lists
like stacks and Qs which are coming up and so we have to understand how linked lists work in order to
implement a stack in a queue.
Congratulations if you made it to this point.
I know this is a lot of content.
It's a little different than some of my other courses that are focused on building something cool or
fun or it's supposed to be fun at least this could be a bit dry.
So I highly recommend take some time take a break do whatever you need to do.
Get ice cream or go yell in a pillow and I'll see you in the next section.
Doubly linked lists.