Hey welcome back.
This section covers two new data structures that are linked together that are often taught as one chapter
in a book or one day and of course they're very simple and this will be a lot less code than something
like a linked list.
So those two structures are stacks and Qs.
We're going to start with stacks for the first couple of videos.
But like I said this will be much faster much easier than some of the length list logic we had before.
So first couple of objectives what is a stack.
We're going to talk about a definition.
We want to talk about use cases both in the real world.
They're used all over the place but also in this course we will come back and you stacks later on and
then we'll implement operations on the stack.
We're actually going to talk about two different ways to implement a stack.
But first what is a stack.
OK.
So both the stacks and Qs which we'll talk about in just a bit.
They are both data collections their data structure.
They're an abstract data structure.
And really the only rule is it's a collection of data and it needs to abide by a life principle.
Last In First Out.
So a queue follows a different principle which is first in first out.
But we're talking about stacks.
So the last element added to a stack is going to be the first one to be removed.
Think of a collection of books on your desk or if you have a messy countertop and you haven't done the
dishes because your roommate is a terrible person if you have a bunch of plates stacked up the most
recently added plate is on top.
And when you remove a plate you're going to remove from the top you're going to remove the one that
was just added.
Unless you're crazy and you want to remove the very bottom plate and you know cause a crazy mess.
So a stack again is just a collection of data.
And the first thing that you added in is the last thing to be removed.
The last thing to be added in is the first thing to be removed.
There's more than one way to implement a stack but you could use a length list and we'll get to that.
But what we have here is our first element added in our last element added in.
And we would remove from the last side of things from the left.
When you remove something you would come from here.
And then here then here and then finally seven would be removed as our last thing to be removed.
It was the first thing to be added.
So we've seen this before.
If you remember in the recursion section we talked about the call stack.
So if you're not familiar with the call stack I recommend you go check that section out.
We talk a lot about it.
The name says stack in it.
And if I head over to some code and I run this code here's factorial it's recursive.
It doesn't matter if you remember how it works or not.
When I execute this for the break point if you watch the call stack Here's the well this is the first
thing.
But here's our first function call that we wrote added into the call stack and it will be the last one
to be removed.
So things are added on top of it as you can see we're almost there.
Thank you.
Our last one.
Yes.
So we now have this stack where this was the first thing I did in this is the last thing added and this
is going to be removed first.
Imagine a stack of books here we take from the top until we get to the bottom.
And so then we pop We removed from the top although that is deceiving because it does look like we're
removing from down here.
But the length the list is just shrinking.
So if you look in this context we're looking at a return value of two x's to this one X is 3 x's 4.
So when we remove There we go we removed one.
Now we're back and we're down to X's three x's four.
So it looks sort of like we're removing from the bottom the way the animation works here but we are
indeed removing from the top of the stack.
And now we have one more.
We remove this and we get back to this original anonymous and now we're done.
OK.
So if you don't remember how the call stack works.
Definitely check out the recursion section but this is an example of a stack.
The last thing added in is the first thing removed.
So a couple of other uses.
We talked about how stacks are used to manage function invocations.
That's in many many programming languages really commonly used undo and redo functionality like in Photoshop
when you're typing Well I guess not typing but when you're editing a photo you know removing wrinkles
on your mom's face because she makes you do that because she knows you know how to photoshop things.
Well if you make a mistake you hit command Z.
It's going to undo the latest action which is at the top of the stack.
It doesn't just go you know a hundred actions back.
You have to step through it constantly so every time you do a new action you remove something or you
clone something it gets added to the top of the stack and then when you undo it you're removing from
the top of that stack.
Another example has to do with history objects in your browser.
Many front end frameworks like react will use a stack to model the history that the pages you've viewed
the routes that you've visited that makes sense.
And one final example in this course we'll actually use stacks and some of our own algorithms.
So when we get to things like trees and graphs later on some of the algorithms that we'll be writing
we actually use a stack and also Qs which we'll talk about later but in this case we'll use a stack
to store sort of the history of things things that we want to come back to.
We're going to use them as an intermediate in our algorithm.
So here's an example again.
Don't don't worry about the code itself but we make a stack and you can see here I'm calling on my stack
I'm calling on my stack inside of this algorithm and we're using it as a place to help us to store data
along the way as we go through this algorithm we're collecting things and then removing them from the
stack anyway.
Don't worry about the code itself just know that this is not a one and done thing where I'm going to
introduce a concept and say Yeah these are cool and they're used.
We're actually going to use them later.
So in the next video I want to show you that we can implement a stack without actually writing any new
code ourselves.
We don't have to create our own data structure.
There's more than one way to implement a stack.
It's an abstract concept and we're going to start by just doing one with an array using a builtin javascript
array to build a stack.
So that's coming up next.
And then we'll do a more official linked list implementation where we write some code.