All right.
Welcome back.
So if you watched the last video we talked about how a stack is a lifeso Lythgoe however you pronounce
it last in first out data structure and there's more than one way to create something like that.
In fact a stack is just a concept.
It's basically a set of rules that says OK you need to be able to store data in such a way that the
first thing added in is the last thing removed.
The last thing added in is the first thing removed.
And it doesn't really define how you do that.
It's just a concept.
So there's more than one way of doing it.
And the easiest way is to use an array.
So some data structures or sorry some programming languages come with their own stack data type.
But we can still use a built in array or list data type to create our own stack.
So all that we have to do is store data in here in a way that the first thing is the last thing removed
and the last thing and the first thing removed.
So if I hop over to my console if I make a new array I'm just going to call it stack and it starts out
empty.
Let's say that I'm storing web pages that I'm visited and I'm creating a history of where I've been.
OK.
So to add something into this stack How do we add to an array.
Well there's a couple of options but let's just use push so I'll push.
I start at Google dot com.
OK.
So we push Google in and then let's say from Google I go to I don't know Instagram.
And then one more site that I go to is YouTube.
My stack now has three things in it.
So in order for this to be a stack I need to have a way to remove from it where the most recently added
thing is what I get first.
So when I remove from here I want to start by getting you to and then next time I should get Instagram
and then Google.
So how would I do that.
Well there's a method to do it stack dot pop Well array of pop so pop is going to remove from the end.
So using push and pop in tandem on an array create to stack as long as that's how we're adding and removing.
If somebody goes and add something to the middle of the array or it's the beginning or removes from
the beginning then it's not quite functioning as a stack anymore.
But if we just push and pop like we're trying to use a stack in our code which That's actually something
we'll do later on is using the array as a stack just because it's simpler.
And if I pop I get YouTube and then Instagram if I push something else in there like let's say you go
to Amazon.
Now when I remove using POP I'll get Amazon first.
It was the last thing added in.
So it's the first thing I get out.
And then one more time I get Google.
So that's one way of using an array to create a stack structure but we could do it another way using
builtin array methods.
Can you think of how that would work.
We're working with the end of the array right now we're adding to the end and removing from the end.
There's another way.
Well there's at least one way if I make some space here if I think I still have an empty caps lock I
have this empty array.
Well if I add to the beginning of the array I could do that.
So how do we get to the beginning.
Well you can use an shift that confusingly titled method and let's say this time we're modeling.
I don't know my Photoshop history so I start with create new file and then the next thing that I did.
What did I do afterwards.
I resized file and then I removed Let's see cloned out a wrinkle or something like that in Photoshop.
OK.
So our stack has three things in there.
In order for this to work the last thing in needs to come out first.
So I can't pop anymore because people were moved from here meaning all take from the end which this
is the first thing added in we don't want the first thing in to be the first thing out.
We want the opposite.
We want the last thing in to be the first thing out.
So I use an shift to add and shift to remove which were moved from the beginning cloned out Rinkel resized
file create new file.
So both of these approaches are valid stacks.
They work.
It's all that matters is that we have a way of adding data in and removing data such that it satisfies
this last in first out principle.
The first thing in the last thing out.
The last thing is the first thing out.
But there's a distinction between these two pushing and popping was the first thing we did.
Meaning we're adding to the end and removing from the end.
And then we also talked about shift and shift adding and removing from the beginning.
So based of what we've talked about with arrays earlier on which is better what's more efficient what's
the problem with one of these.
Well if we think about how arrays work remember that adding to the beginning removing from the beginning
is not good as far as Big-O notation time complexity.
What we have to do is if we have an array with three things in here each item has an index.
And if I add something to the very beginning we have to re-index all the other items because this is
no longer going to be index 0.
This will no longer be indexed.
Everything gets shifted down.
OK so if we have this stack with these three items in here if I unship again and this time I add something
else in like I don't know and just doing dumb abbreviations all of these indices have to be shifted
down and that's very inefficient.
I mean for for items it's not really a problem at all but just it's worth considering if we have a lot
of data it's not a great way of doing it.
Instead if we use push we're adding to the end we just have to create a new spot and new index and read
an add you know index of 4 but we don't have to re index every other item in there.
It is worth mentioning that if you actually care about the efficiency then you probably don't want to
use an array for a stack.
If you're going to have a ton of data in there all you need is this last in first out capability.
We'll use our second implementation coming up where we use a linked list.
There's no reason to have these indices we're not accessing information based off of an index.
We're simply accessing information based off of when it was inserted.
The order needs to be preserved and a linked list will do that for us.
So to recap we can use an array to create a stack.
We can use push and pop in tandem so that the first thing added in is the last thing out.
The last thing added in is the first thing out.
I know I'm a broken record on that.
Or we could use shift and shift and shift to add to the beginning shift to remove from the beginning
of the array.
So it doesn't matter what direction we're doing it in.
If we're adding down here or adding over here as long as we're removing from that same direction if
that makes sense.
But in general if you are going to use an array push and pop are the better options because it doesn't
require reindexing the entire array every time you add or remove something you just have to create some
you know a new index at the end.
Or remove that index.
OK.
So next up I'll show you an implementation of a stack using a linked list.