Welcome back.
So as I mentioned a couple of years ago there's more than one way of implementing a stack.
It's just a general idea of a data structure where we can add data in and remove data using a last in
first out principle.
Lifeso.
You know the last thing that's added in is the first thing we get back and I showed you how to do that
using an array.
And that works.
We didn't have to write any new code we didn't even defined a class we just used an array and use the
built in methods we get for free.
Nothing wrong with that.
I mean it's a little heavy handed.
We don't need you know indices for example which we get for free.
We don't need all the other.
I don't know dozen plus methods that an array comes with.
We don't need any of that.
All we really need are the methods to add and remove in a last in first out fashion.
So what I'm going to show you in this video is how to build our own stack class that doesn't use an
array at all.
In fact it's built kind of following the principles of a singly linked list.
So if you didn't watch the section on singly linked lists you should go back and check that out.
You could also do it with a double dealing first but I'm not going to you know do both because it's
a lot of time and it's very similar.
And if you see how it works with a single thing I still get it with a double one.
All right.
So one note when we use and learn other algorithms later on some of them use a stack and Qs which we'll
see in a second to help them to store data sort of to keep track of what's open process and what has
yet to be processed.
And we could use an array implementation we could use her own class to keep it short.
I will be using an array implementation.
That doesn't mean it's better though it's just easier and quicker.
But this is the stacks and queue section.
So I'm going to show you how to make sort of the best possible stack from scratch and it should work
look like this.
I should be able to initialize a new stack and there's only two methods we care about stacked up push
and stacked up pop.
So I could push something like first and get a couple more seconds notice it's returning to me the size
or the length of it.
And then I do one last one and then when I pop it should of course follow Last In First Out.
So it gives me fourth and then third and second then first and then no.
So that's it.
We need a class defined called stack and it needs a way of storing data.
So we'll have a node class as well.
Looks like this just like we did with full length list instead of head and tail end and length.
I went with the first last and size head and tail is usually reserved for length list.
Even though this is a subset or a special case of a length list I like to use first and last but it's
the same idea head and tail are just pointers there variables and then we have the Node class that has
a value for each node and then a pointer to the next node in the stack.
So at this point you might be thinking well we already built a single length list.
It had a bunch of other methods but it had push and pop.
So why not just use push and pop as they are.
And that could work except for one small problem which is that in a stack push and pop are supposed
to be constant time.
And if we if you remember if you didn't watch the Stingley thing for this section this probably won't
make sense but pop in particular was not constant time because to pop something off the end of the list
the way that it works we have to iterate over the entire list and stop one node before the end.
One note before the tail.
That's what this code is doing here.
So this is not constant time because we have to loop over the entire list.
So instead it's much better to use shift and unshipped except there's supposed to be called push and
pop.
So I'm going to show you.
I'll actually write the code but hint hint.
You could basically just rename shift in and shift to push and pop and call it a day.
But I'm going to define my own stack class right now.
I do have pseudo code if you want to do this on your own but I didn't want to drag it out into multiple
videos.
So basically push is going to work a little differently than push that we wrote earlier on because we're
going to be adding to the beginning of the list and removing from the beginning of the list instead
of adding to the end and removing from the end.
Same idea.
It's just that when we add and remove from the beginning it's faster it's constant time in a singly
linked list.
If we use a doubly linked list then it wouldn't really matter.
It would be constant time to pop as well from the end anyway so well to find a function called Push
and it should accept a value.
Create a new node with that value if there are no nodes in the stack.
So the first and last property to be that new node if there is at least one node create a variable that
stores the current first and then reset the first to be the new node and then all we need to do is connect
everything together.
So set the next property on the node to be the previously created variable and then increment the size
by 1.
So I'm going to come over here and define my first I'll do my node class.
So node is really simple.
It's copied from before we have a constructor or fastforward that looks like this value pass in.
We set a value equal to whatever is passed in this next starts as null then we start with our class
called Stack which also is really basic at the beginning doesn't take anything.
And instead of head and tail I'm going to set first to no last to know.
And then also I'm going to go with size instead of length just to differentiate it and it starts at
zero.
OK.
So now to push in.
Needs to accept avowe and then we create a new node with that value.
So let's just do our new node equals new node with whatever was passed in then we check if there are
no nodes in the stack.
So the first and last property to be that new node.
So we'll just check if there's we could check if the size is zero or just if there is no first.
If there's nothing at the beginning we set this up first to be the node the new node and then do the
same thing for the last.
All right.
So that's that next if there is at least one node create a variable that stores the current first property
on the stack and we can go from there.
So we need to have an else and I'm just going to make a variable called Temp equals this stuff.
First the current first because we're adding this to the beginning.
Then we're just going to say this first is now equal to new node.
And then this first dot next equals temp.
The old beginning and then the very last thing we need to do is increment the size of the stack by 1.
And I didn't actually add this in the pseudo code but I explained this earlier that it's best to return
the size.
So I'm going to do that in one line just return.
Plus plus this dot size.
And if I run my code I should be able to do var stack equals new stack and do a push.
Let's just push some random numbers in.
Looks like well we can actually tell if it's working but at this point the order of in that stack the
first very beginning should be 2 3 0 1.
And then that should point 2 to 30 and then that should point to 23.
So now we just need to implement pop which will remove from the beginning which again we're doing it
backwards.
Sort of counter to what we did with a singly linked list because we want constant time for adding and
removing for pushing and popping.
So now to implement Pop we're going to define a function called Pop.
And we're going to check if there is or if there are no nodes in the stack.
If it's empty return no.
Otherwise we're going to take whatever the first property is on the stack and store that in a variable
to return at the very end.
Whoops.
If there's only one node set the first and last property to be no.
Meaning if the first is now equal to the last set the last and first to be no.
If there's more than one node set the first property to be the next property on the current first decrease
decided by 1 return the value of the removed node.
So you could posit if you want to implement this on your own.
But again these two are very similar to shift and an shift on our singly linked list.
We're just using first and last and size instead of head and tail and renaming them push and pop.
OK.
So pop first we're going to check.
What was it.
If the list is empty so I'm going to do.
If not this stuff first.
If that's the case return null.
That means there's nothing to overturn we're done or there's nothing in the stack to pop.
Otherwise I'm going to take a call a temp set that equaled the first.
This is what we'll return at the very end and I'll actually do that.
Now return temp Vau or value.
So we're returning the value at the end.
But along the way we need to patch things together.
So we want to check if there's only one node.
Meaning if this first equals this outlasts What do we want to do this last.
Equals no.
And that's just an edge case when there's only one thing left in there.
We need to make sure we're also updating last because on this next step we're going to update first
this first equals this first.
Next.
So we needed to do this beforehand.
If it's the last thing in this list or in this stack we need to make sure that last is null so that
when we do this stuff first equals this up first.
Next we're setting first to be no as well.
But in the case of this example where we have three things in our stack we're not going to change last
to be no.
Instead we're just updating first and then the only other thing we need to decrement size.
So this size minus minus just like that.
And we should be good to go.
Let's test it out.
So let's make a new stack var stack equals new.
It's not supposed to happen.
I thought I was going to autocomplete for me.
Stacked up.
Bush let's do first.
Like this second and third.
Sorry my cat is making a lot of noise over there what is doing.
And then will do stacked up pop.
We should get third and then second and then first and now nothing.
And we have successfully implemented a stack.
So hopefully you did watch the singly links section.
Otherwise this would be a complete whirlwind and that's not my intent.
You're not supposed to see this unless you went through that first section because there's a lot of
stuff here that I'm not explaining anyway.
So just to reiterate why we did it this way rather than using push and pop that we already wrote for
a singly linked list.
Just to reiterate.
Remember for adding to the end and removing from the end it's not constant time to remove from the end
because we had to iterate the entire list to get to the second to last item to set that to be the new
tail.
And the stack is supposed to be constant time.
So we're adding and removing from the beginning of our list.
But we're calling it push and pop because it is a stack.
All right.