All right.
So the last thing we'll do is quickly talk about the big O stacks and all that really matters are these
first two insertion and removal.
So the way that we wrote our staff class was to make sure that pushing and popping were both constant
time.
That's kind of the one thing you have to care about in this deck searching accessing individual items
using an index or position that is not important at all.
And if it is you probably want to use an array or some other data structure that's going to give you
faster access.
So a stack is really prioritizing insertion and removal and the way that we implemented ours if you
wanted to search for something you'd have to start at the beginning and just traverse the entire stack
next next next which would give us of an insertion and removal though because we're adding to the beginning
and removing from the beginning.
We don't have to iterate over the list or the stack.
We don't have to look for anything we just jump right to the start.
And that means constant time and lastly to recap stacks are a last in first out lifeso Lythgoe data
structure where the last value is always the first one out there use to handle function invocations
like the call stack.
We've seen that they're also used for operations like undo and redo.
For routing your page history where you've been in your browser and a whole bunch more and they're not
a built in data structure in Javascript in some languages they are.
But javascript is not one of those but they're pretty quick or easy to implement.
And like I said in this video or in the last video you'll see me use an array to implement a stack because
it's shorter.
We don't have to use all this code here.
Not that bad but when we're doing these more complicated algorithms later on where we need to use a
stack I probably have already recorded them so I definitely will be using an array but this is the preferred
way of creating a stack if you are using it for tons and tons of data.
You know there's no reason to use an array to store 10000 items if you're only accessing using push
and pop or shift on shift.
There's no reason to do that just to use a custom class like this.
So that's next.
Next up queue's.