All right.
So we're moving on from stacks to talk about a similar sister data structure called the CU.
These two are often talked together.
They're often grouped into one section just like they are in this very course stacks and cues.
So before we get into the details quickly define our objectives to find what a cue is understand use
cases and examples of where they are used and then implement our own data structure just like we did
with Stex.
So what is the cue.
Well it's very similar to a stack in the sense that it's a data structure that you add data in and you
remove data out and those are really the only two operations.
Adding and removing However the order is different.
Instead of last in first out for a stack lifeso this is a fivefold FIFO and data structure first in
first out.
So the name Q Just like with stacks where I said think of a stack of paper or books on your desk with
a queue.
Think of a line.
Q What a lot of people around the world would say in the US who would say we're waiting in line but
lots of places say forming a Q So a queue like at Disneyland or you're waiting for and getting on an
airplane or something.
The first person in line is the first person out.
The first piece of data in a queue is the first thing out and these have uses all over the place you
know waiting in line.
Yeah humans do that all the time.
It's a miserable experience for most people.
But in programming in our computers that are also really commonly used.
If you've ever played a video game or you're waiting to join a game like it's an online game there's
usually some queue structure keeping track of who has been waiting the longest.
Who's going to get you know added into the game first.
Also background tasks on your computer.
Time are uploading or downloading something.
If you click like you know you download one file and it takes a while and you go to download another
file.
If they're the exact same size the first thing that was added in is going to be processed first or if
you're uploading something usually the first thing that you start to upload is going to finish first.
However that's a little tricky because there's different file sizes and some things will upload or download
much faster.
So a better example is a print queue.
So if you go and print 10 different things a printer can only handle one thing at a time.
So unlike uploading or downloading where things could be happening concurrently when we're talking about
printing you print one page at a time one project.
So there's a queue like at a public library 20 people try and print their essays the last night before
they're due whoever hit print first is going to be processed first.
If we used a stack instead of a queue that would be disastrous if we did last in first out that would
reward people who waited until the very very end.
So they are used all over the place.
It's a 5 0 5 000 first in first out data structure and just like before we can implement them with an
array.
Or we could implement our own Q class and we're going to do both.
And just like before as well.
I'm going to mention that in later algorithms that we learn will be using QS.
We'll also be using stacks and we could use the classes that I'm going to show to show the stack class
but to keep it short and simple I'll be using an array but that doesn't mean that it's better to use
an array.
It might be simpler or shorter definitely doesn't require as much work on our end but it's definitely
worthwhile knowing how to implement your own queue class because it's lighter weight.
We don't have to worry about all the extra garbage we get when we use an array.
So next I am going to show you how to model a Q or I should say model is it is a cue to create a Q Using
an array and then also how to create our own Q class.
So in summation just like with a stack there is more than one way to implement a Q.
It's not you know rigid.
There are many different implementations.
The only rules governing it is that the first thing added in is the first thing removed.
So we need an interface to add something in usually called NQ E and Q And then a way to remove something
usually called dequeue D.
Q And that's really it.
So in the next few videos I'll show you two different ways of meeting those requirements.