All right.
Welcome back.
Let's quickly talk about building a q with an array.
So this is the easy way.
So we would really need to do is create a variable.
I'll just call mine.
Q Like the letter instead of Q You EUV think that you spell it.
So it's an empty array and there's multiple there's at least two ways of doing this really.
We can add to the beginning or add to the end.
So let's just pick one.
Let's say that we're going to start by adding to the end of the array so we could use push.
Right.
So let's push first and a couple more or less two seconds and surprise will do.
Third.
All right.
So the array looks like this.
So for this to work or operate as a true cue we need a way to remove first first second second and third
third.
So we want to remove from the beginning.
So pop is not what we want if we were doing a stack then that would work.
Instead we need to move from the beginning with shift.
And we get first second and then third.
So that's one way of creating a cue and it's super easy.
Right.
Of course one thing that's not great when we do this is if we had 10000 items in there that you'd have
an index and removing from the beginning means that every single item is read indexed.
So adding to the end of the array doesn't require reindexing anything just means indexing the new item
at the very end but removing from the beginning shifts everything over.
So what if we did this instead if we look at Q As empty.
So let's do and shift let's add to the beginning.
So we'll do first again and second and third.
Very exciting.
So if we look at Cue it now looks like this.
And then to remove following the rules have a cue first in first out we would need to pop from the end
so we get first second and third.
So those two pairs we could do an shift combined with pop.
Or we could do push combined with shift both are going to give us that desired cue functionality first
in first out.
However in the second case we think about how it's working.
As we grow this ten thousand items if we're adding to the beginning every time we insert that means
reindexing the entire queue which also is not good because that means shifting everything over you know
giving a new index to if we have 10000 items.
That means re-assigning every single item popping from the end works well.
So unlike when we talked about stacks you could use push and pop to make a stack and you would never
need to re-index the entire thing the entire array.
Unlike that when we do a Q There's no way around it using an array.
So it definitely makes sense to create your own Q class if you're really concerned about performance.
Like I said I will be using an array to illustrate or to create a cue for us in some of the more complicated
algorithms later on to keep my code short.
But it's not ideal in the next video I'll show you how to use a linked list based Q to define our own
Q class which will perform better than this but this technically is a cube.
We have a way of adding and removing and a first in first out method way functionality.
Anyway you can do it with an array.
Next we'll do it from scratch.