All right we'll come back.
So in this video we'll define our own Q data structure from scratch instead of using an array.
And just like we did with the stack data structure it's going to be based off of a length list.
So hopefully you made it through the singly linked list section and we go through this pretty quickly.
So if you didn't watch that if you didn't understand that code some of this might be confusing.
So I recommend to do that first step will have a q class a first and a last and a Size property.
Just like with our stack and then a node class for each element in the queue will have a value and a
next pointer.
So quickly to refresh your memory on a linked list.
What we could do just like with an array.
We have two sort of pairs of options.
We can add to the end and remove from the beginning or we could add to the beginning and removed from
the end.
Right.
So we could for example if we let's do an insert at the very end insert 80.
There we go.
And we keep inserting this insert again 54.
The first thing that should be removed is the first thing that was inserted in a cue.
So that would be over here.
So then we would remove from the beginning just like this.
So that's one option.
The other option is to switch it in at the beginning.
So we'd insert at the beginning like ninety nine right there and then remove from the end which theoretically
would be the first thing added in.
Although in this case it isn't because you know we were doing it backwards but if we kept inserting
the list it would grow or the stack grows this way.
So this should be the first thing added in.
And if I remove from there from the tail.
Oh no.
Look at how slow this is.
So this is the exact same thing we encountered in the stack video where in a singly linked list removing
from the very end using POP is slow because we have to iterate over the entire list.
Let's do it one more time.
Remove from the end.
Not good.
So what we're going to do instead of this is to add to the end and remove from the beginning.
So it looks more like this.
So our methods are going instead of push and pop which is what they are for a stack.
The terminology is and Q and dequeue.
So if this is our cue when we add.
Now well I just clicked dequeue accidentally.
So you could see it was removed from the beginning.
But when we entered cue something it's added to the end.
So it's pushed on.
If we're going with a singly linked list we would call this push.
We're adding to the end.
And when we dequeue we're removing from the beginning which we would call shift.
But because it's a cue we're going with and Q and dequeue.
So this is our idea to singly linked list or it looks like one but it has these two methods.
So we add to the end to the tail and we remove from the head.
So let's do that.
Now here's the classes that we'll go with.
I'm going to start by defining those two classes and then we'll add the two methods.
So I made a new snippet and I'll fast forward through my definition of the Node class.
All right.
So we have node takes evaluation.
We set the value to be that value and then the next is null by default.
Now quickly to find the basic skeleton of the Q class and it just has a constructor takes nothing.
And we have a first which is no.
We have a last which is no and then a size.
And now we just have to add our two simple methods.
So we'll have NQ which accepts a value.
So I'll just call it Val.
And then we have the Q which doesn't.
I hate having to type that.
I hope I say oh my gosh you see.
You see.
There you go.
And this should return the first thing that was added in.
So this should add something in.
And then this will return and remove the the first thing that was added in.
Not very good about not explaining it in a good way anyway.
So this will add to the very end of our lengthy.
This will remove from the beginning.
So let's start by queuing.
So if we look at the pseudo code our function accepts the value.
We've done that.
Create a new node using the value passed in.
And then if there are no nodes in the queue set this node to be the first and last property.
So that's not all of it but let's just start by creating the new node.
So our new node equals new node with Val that was passed in cool and then we're going to check if there's
nothing in the queue.
So we could check if size is zero or if there is no this at first.
In that case we set this up first equals new node.
This last equals new nodes.
This is our edge case.
If it's an empty queue.
So we set the first and last to be that new node.
Otherwise set the next property on the current last to be the new node and then move the last pointer
to be that new node at the end to basically add it to the end.
So that looks like this else and this is identical other than first and last in size.
You could replace that with push on our singly linked list.
We're adding to the end we just used head and tail and length.
So it's the same logic.
So otherwise this last.
So the very end next is now equal to new node.
And then we just say this last equals that new node.
So we've moved over that pointer.
So we're now looking at the end.
And then finally we're going to increment the size of the q by one and return that.
So I'll do return plus plus size.
OK.
And then we'll move on to dequeue and dequeue should remove from the beginning in order to give us the
last or excuse me to give us the first thing added in.
We're adding to the end removing from the beginning.
So Diekema looks like this.
We define the function takes no arguments if there is no first property just return no store the first
property in a variable.
This is identical to what we did in the stacked section of the stack.
Part of the section.
So it's very very similar.
And let's just get going on it honestly.
So dequeue we're going to start by checking if it's empty.
So if there is no this first return no.
That means that there's nothing in our queue Otherwise we'll make a variable called temp to store the
current stuff first.
This is what will return at the very end and then we'll just do our exact same logic.
So if this stuff first is equal to this last we're going to set this last equal to no otherwise was
actually not even otherwise.
But just this first.
So that's our edge case.
If you know there's only one thing left in there we set the last item to be no then we're going to take
this out first at the beginning and update it to be the next item.
So whatever used to be there for example if this is the current start first we're now going to say this
first next is now this stuff first and then the only other thing we need to do is decrease the size
by one and return the value of the node.
So that's going to be this size minus minus and then return temp value.
And that should be it.
And if we look at this dequeue and compare it to our stack which had it was called pop but it's the
same idea the code is identical.
They even use variable named TEMP.
Yeah.
It should be exactly the same.
And that's correct.
That's how it should be the way that we're implementing our queue.
We are removing from the beginning same thing we did with our stack.
It's just that in our stack We are also adding to the beginning in our queue.
We're adding to the end and we called it dequeue instead of pop and queue instead of push anyway.
So let's test this baby out.
So run our code.
I don't know why I just let's run the code and let's make it Q Just call it new q like that and then
we'll do an NQ first.
What's going on here.
It looks like ah I have a problem.
Up first this outsized needs to be set to zero.
So we'll do our Q equals new Q And then do Q and Q First.
Looks like it's working second and third and then we'll do a Q dots dequeue which should give me the
first thing added in which is first and then second then third and now it should always be No.
And first and last are set to no size is back to zero.
So I can now and q something else like hello.
And then I can dequeue Hello again and everything should be happy and that is our cue.
So this q can grow super large.
Theres no indexing theres no problems that will encounter its constant time for every operation which
is really just adding in and removing.
And it is first in first out FIFO fight so I don't know what the official pronunciation is and that
is in comparison to a stack which is lifeso or Laveau last in first out.
So they're very similar but also extremely different in how they actually behave.
They're similar in the fact that there's two operations adding and removing put something in.
You get something out.
It's just that the orders are totally different.
OK so in the next video I'll wrap everything up.
In queues.
Talk about Big-O notation and just summarize it all.
Hopefully this makes sense if you saw the singles links section.
This is extremely similar.
We just put a different wrapper on it called things a little bit different names but otherwise it's
the same functionality just slimmed down.
All right.