All right.
So that's it for cue's really quick.
The Big O notation should be constant time insertion and removal.
That's the only thing that matters.
Searching and accessing something that you really do with a cue Otherwise you may not want to use a
Q data structure if you need to prioritize searching.
Generally all you care about is adding things in with Q removing things with dequeue you want that to
be super fast.
So with our implementation it is constant time.
Note that when we use an array it was not constant time because in both iterations are both solutions
that we used or that we came up with.
Using the built in Array methods there was a cascade of re-indexing.
So that does not lead to constant time and linear time is not what we want.
We want constant time and this is the same for stacks stacks and queues to structures add things in
remove them different orders and how they actually work.
But both adding and removing should be constant time 0 of 1.
So to recap on queues they are first in first out just like at an airport.
First person in is the first person out.
Unless you are selected for additional screening in which case you won't be the last one out.
But usually the first person in line gets out first.
Contrast that with a stack first thing in is the last thing out.
So queues are used often.
Any time you need to keep track of an order and maintain that order so that the first thing in a print
queue that's a classic example.
The first thing that someone tries to print is the first thing actually printed and then anything else
that piles up is kept in the order that it was added in and then we remove it.
We print the things that have been waiting the longest.
OK so useful for processing tasks and also are foundational for other more complex algorithms and data
structures that we'll see later on.
As I mentioned we will be using stacks and Qs later in the course to help us implement more complicated
data structures and algorithms so they are not just a novelty to show you they will be resurfacing.
And like I said insertion and removal needs to be.
So I said it can be done in constant time in a good stack and a good queue.
It has to be otherwise it's just a waste.
Why even use a stack or queue anyway.
That's it for stacks and queues.
Very similar in a lot of ways.
Adding and removing things constant time very different in the order first in and first out for a queue.
Last In First Out for a stack.
Ok see in the next section.