Hey welcome back.
So at this point we have the ability to store data in a graph structure.
We wrote the graph class we added in methods to add and remove vertices and edges so we can store everything
we can represent a graph.
Now we get to go to the really really juicy meaty important stuff which all has to do with traversing
our graphs searching or visiting neighbors from a given node.
So we'll get into the real world uses for this.
There are many many of them just like two sides from now.
I'll talk about it.
This is also a topic that comes up a lot in computer science textbooks and final exams.
It comes up in interviews which I actually think it's a great interview question because of how many
real world applications there are.
So it's not some arbitrary you know just test of your art.
How much do you remember from from college computer science.
It's something that actually is relevant in today's world.
So we'll talk about why but when we say traversal for now at least I just mean visiting every single
node every vertex in a graph.
So there's many ways of doing this.
Usually like when we talk about the real world applications you may not be visiting every single node.
A lot of what people do has to do with finding nearest neighbors or most similar neighbors are finding
the shortest path from one vertex to another.
In the case of GPS directions.
So it's usually more special cases rather than visit every single node in this entire graph just to
say that you've done it.
But we've got to start somewhere.
And a lot of the more advanced algorithms are derived from our basic traversal approaches the procedures
we're going to talk about now.
So when we say traversal we mean visiting updating checking searching printing out whatever every vertex
in a graph.
So we start from one vertex which if we go back to trees remember trees are a special subset of a graph
where for any given node there is only one path one and only path to get to this node.
So from 17 the route to get to 25 This is our only option to get to 89.
There's one option.
Now if we compare that with some other graphs.
So the more generic graph basically this is not a tree every tree is a graph but there are many many
graphs that aren't.
So for example this one this is a directed graph which we haven't worked with very much but it just
means that those connections those edges are they have a direction associated with them.
They're one way.
So let's say I want to go from zero to six and actually even before that we have a problem of not knowing
where we start from.
There is no root.
So yeah maybe as humans we want to start at zero because it's the smallest number but there's no indication
that this is the start point.
We could start from here or from here.
So unlike a tree when we write the code to traverse a graph we need to specify our starting point.
So let's say I want to go from 0 to 6.
For example there is at least Well there's this option 0 to 1 to 6.
We can go 0 to 2 to 3 to 6 0 to 2 to 3 to 5 to 8 to 6.
And I think that's it.
If this was a undirected graph we would have some other options too.
We could go from 5 we could go from 7.
So my point here is that for any node in the graph there's no guarantee there's one unique path to get
there.
Now that doesn't mean that traversing is harder or more difficult but it does mean that sometimes while
there are certainly multiple orders but also you may end up having to do some backtracking.
You may revisit a node you've already been to almost always do and it's not much code.
But we have to write code to pay attention to that.
But first let's go back and talk about why you should care.
Before we get into the specific algorithms so any time we have a graph whether it's a network graph
for a torrent Web site or we're talking about web crawlers where we have like Google in the early days
we're just follow every link from one that still does this but would go from one web page.
Follow all links on that web page and follow them out and out and out.
And in reality it's not a tree structure because you have many web pages that linked to one another.
So to follow every link that's a graph structure.
So the actual process of traversing of crawling it's just a graph traversal.
Also when we talk about things like finding the closest matches or recommendations the shortest path
between things and when to show you a couple of examples.
These all have to do with traversing from one vertex to another.
So here's this Wikipedia visualization of a small subset of Wikipedia pages in order to create this
somebody or some code started from one web page I don't know which one they started from and let's say
here and they wrote code to visit traverse every link in this graph and draw a little dot or something
like that and then follow one of them followed a link to something over here.
And that one linked to many other things and from there you know we went on and on and on and traversed
all of these Wikipedia pages.
So just to generate this involved some graph traversal that is sort of a basic example just to draw
something.
If you go back to this example when we're talking about using a graph structure to help make recommendations
this is an illustration of a poor one of two video games where I'm trying to show that there's some
overlap between Borderlands and Halo.
Now if we had this for 10000 video games and we had thousands and thousands of data points for each
game and things like revues scores genres how many things how many copies are sold different elements
of the game play.
So if somebody said that they liked Borderlands and you wanted to figure out a game to recommend to
them or a product to recommend or on Netflix a movie to recommend to someone it involves starting here
and trying to find something that's most similar that that you have the most overlap with.
So this is a small graph so we can tell only one option Halo.
But if there were millions of other data points we might need to traverse across them and try and tabulate
what's closest What has the most has the most nodes most vertices in common with Borderlands that involves
traversing from one node to a bunch of other nodes.
Or here's one more example.
If we're talking about friends on something like Facebook this very simple example just from this we
could make a recommendation.
Let's see.
Maria is friends with an army is friends with Nan and Tim is friends with Maria and army.
So if we wanted to find a recommendation to Tim who he might know that he probably seen that on Facebook
you might.
I don't know exactly what it says anymore.
We recommend this person or do you know X person or suggestions for friends you might recommend then
based off of the fact that from Tim we can get to nn pretty easily.
Nan is one jump away.
We go to army well to Jump's I guess one and then two we go to Maria one and then two.
And so we could write some algorithms traverse outwards find friends of friends and whichever friend
a friend has the most friend a friend that's a better way of putting it.
Whoever looks closest whoever has the most friends of friends with me recommend them.
OK.
So my point is there's lots and lots of applications.
Even things like artificial intelligence.
If we talk about all the different possibilities for a board game lay out in a game like tic tac toe
is a simple example but let's say something crazy like Scrabble where there's so many options you could
use a graph to store different game moves and then traverse that graph to find the shortest path to
a winning move the shortest way to win the game.
For example GPS navigation we have millions or billions of vertices represented representing a map and
intersections and businesses.
How do we find the best way to get from one place to another.
So that doesn't involve just direct traversal that involves finding the shortest path not just blindly
traversing the entire graph but we have to start somewhere before we can talk about shortest path algorithms
before we can talk about making recommendations.
We just need to be able to visit every single node and there are many ways of doing that.
Just like with trees.
So in this section we're going to talk about depth first search or depth first traversal both recursively
and iterative flee.
And we're going to talk about breadth first traversal.
Now it's not that different from what we did with trees but remember the distinction that I showed.
There are times where you're going to have to visit a node again or realize you've already visited that
vertex and adjust accordingly.
But I'm getting ahead of myself.
Let's now talk about depth first search and how it works in the next video.