Hey welcome back.
Let's kick things off with depth first traversal of a graph.
So just like with trees which we spent a good amount of time on binary search trees or binary trees
in general there are two main options for traversing these trees.
Depth first and breadth first traversal.
Now within depth first we did talk about pre order Post order in order but the general idea behind depth
and breadth first is what we care about.
So when we say depth first for this binary search tree or any tree it means that we're focusing we're
prioritizing visiting children of a given node before we visit siblings or we deepen the traversal before
we widen it.
So what that really means whether we're going left or right first doesn't really matter but let's say
that we go left.
So we start at 41.
We're going to visit 20 and rather than going to the sibling we're now going to finish out the children
of 20.
So that gets us to 11 and didn't go back to 20.
Finish Out the children.
Now we had a dead end.
Now we go back and visit 20's sibling.
And then we keep doing that.
So we prioritize deepening of the traversal rather than broad broadening whether weather rather than
widening So that's depth first.
But in this section we're talking about graphs that are not trees and they're not necessarily harder
to traverse but sometimes they can be a little trickier to understand what depth means versus breath
because it's easy on a tree where we have a clear direction down or it depends you know how it's drawn
sometimes you see trees drawn upwards from the root.
But however it's drawn there's a clear path through that tree.
There's one root.
And then you descend away or you ascend away whatever it is you're moving away from that root.
So depth first means moving away from the root.
When we talk about a graph a more general graph like this and this is a directed graph.
Unfortunately this website doesn't let me do undirected graphs and traverse them.
But anyway let's say that we pick one of these vertices.
There is no root node.
There isn't a tree but let's say we're going to start at zero.
What does it mean to do depth first traversal from here.
Well really all that it means is finding one neighbor following one neighbor.
Let's say one but there's actually three neighbors we have six and two.
Let's say we follow one and then we continue to follow the neighbors of one before we visit its siblings
and when we say siblings it's kind of different than a tree because they're not necessarily on the same
level.
But let me just put it this way we started zero.
Let's say that we always choose the lowest number as our next item to visit.
So we go to 0 to 1.
Now in a breath first which will come back to we would then visit the other neighbors of 0 2 and 6 but
in depth first we're going to go 0 to 1 to 5 and then come back to 1 and go to six and then from 6 we
visit it's neighbors like 7 and then 9 and so on rather than the breadth first where we're going to
visit 0 1 2 6.
All of zeros neighbors first before we visit one's neighbors and twos neighbors and so on.
So let me show you a little animated diagram I put together.
Here's a simpler graph.
There is no you know root node that we start from by default but let's say we're doing a depth first
traversal starting from a.
We want to explore as far as possible down one branch before we backtrack again we have to decide the
order we're going to visit things in.
So we if we have a there's two neighbors which one do we visit first.
Well let's just go with alphabetical order to keep it consistent.
These are both neighbors and we could visit either one first but let's say we're going to visit alphabetically.
So we start from a.
And then we visit B.
Now if this were breadth first we would then go back and visit.
But depth first means we're now going to explore these neighbors.
So let's pick a neighbor alphabetically first.
We have see we could do D but let's do C to be consistent now from C..
We have two neighbors and we've already visited B.
So this is an important idea.
We have to remember where we've been.
Otherwise we could just go back to be.
So we we've done.
So that leaves us D.
Now from D We have two choices and if we're going alphabetically we're going to go to E and then to
f.
Now that order doesn't really matter as far as depth first.
These are both neighbors to D.
But it's just helpful for us to kind of be you know have a concrete order if we're just doing alphabetical.
OK.
So it's really important that we remember where every bend.
Otherwise we would go from a.
Let's say we go to be again.
Well B has two neighbors or three neighbors.
C d n.
And if we don't remember we've already been to a.
What's stopping us from just going back to a and then going back to B for always picking the earliest
alphabetical the lowest alphabet A and then B we'd get stuck.
So here's another example a slightly different graph.
I know it's the same nodes the same vertices but different edges.
If we start from a again if we're doing lowest alphabetically we would go to B and then from B we only
have one choice.
We go to D.
Now we have two choices which one do we go to.
Well we're doing alphabetically first.
We go to E.
Now we have two choices.
There are three edges but we know we've already been to D.
So do we go to C or F for doing it alphabetically we go to see now from C..
It's it's a dead end.
We visited a we visited e.
So if we go back to e..
And now we have to finish.
E We have F and then we're done.
So here is one more exact same graph actually same animation but down here I'm displaying our adjacency
list.
So you can see a is connected to B and C and that's reflected here.
And I do have things listed alphabetically first.
So the the edge from a to b comes before 8 is c.
Again it doesn't really matter.
But for me to explain it's easier to do alphabetically first.
OK so if we look at what happens from a we started a and we visited a so we're going to cross it off
meaning that any time we see a so adjacent node we're going to ignore it.
So we look at a and we see that there's two edges two vertices so we could go to a B or C and we'll
just take the first one we go to beat.
So when we visit B we now cross off from here and from here to all of its edges.
This doesn't mean deleting them it just means that we're going to remember I've already been to be so
ignore it next time we see it.
So we get to be which is right here and we see that it has two edges a and D.
But we've already Benty we cross that off.
So now we go to D and we cross off because we've been there it has three edges.
We cross d everywhere.
So now at d we look well there's three choices but we've already been to be.
So we'll go to each next and we cross off all those e's.
Now we go to E.
Where should we go from.
Well let's go to see.
OK.
So good to see.
And we cross all those seas off and now we go back to where we were last.
And we've already visited Sea.
We've already visited D.
Now we need to visit F and we're done.
OK.
So that's the basic idea of depth first traversal.
We follow a branch down.
It's harder to say we're deepening because it's a little more challenging to visually understand what
depth means in a graph because you know when you have a tree it's easier.
We're moving away from the route.
In this case it looks like a loop basically.
So depth is harder to explain what it really means is just following the neighbors and continuing to
follow neighbors before backtrack.
So we're going to implement depth first search both recursively.
I said search we're actually going to do traversal is the same idea except we're not searching for something
we're just going to visit every node every vertex.
Anyway we're going to do it recursively.
And if we just to show you both approaches it's a good thing to know.
So we'll start with recursive the recursive solution.
Well first the pseudo code in the next video and then an implementation afterwards and then we'll do
it or to flee and then we'll cover breath first.
OK.