Welcome back.
So we're going to start off by implementing depth first traversal of a graph.
Two ways recursively and intuitively.
But first we're doing the recursive version.
So I have a more detailed bit of pseudo code after this but here's sort of the basic explanation.
So define your function your method DFS.
You might want to call it DFS recursive so that you can do both iterative and recursive and it takes
a vertex to start from.
There is no you know automatic inherent start point like a tree.
So let's say you pass an A.
So we need to have a base case when we're doing something recursively.
If you haven't seen the recursive section you definitely check that out first.
Otherwise this will make no sense.
So our base case is when vertex is empty.
So the first time around that's not going to be the case because we're passing in A or B or some starting
point.
If that is the case we return something return no just get out of there.
Otherwise we're going to have a list of results.
So we're building this array to return at the very end.
So we add the vertex to the results list meaning we've visited it.
So we would add a in and then we mark Virtex as visited.
So what would we do to actually market has visited.
I'm just going to do something like this.
I have an object key value pairs and when we visit F for example we add F in here and set it to be true.
You don't have to do this you don't have to set it to be true.
You could use just another array and add a in there but I like this approach it's more explicit and
it also later on would allow you to mark something unvisited if for some reason you wanted to consider
to be false but it doesn't really matter.
But this is how I'm going to do it.
So mark it as visited then for each neighbor in that vertexes neighbors so for all of A's neighbors
if that is not visited recursively call DFS on that neighbor.
So we would call depth first search on B and on D if those are the two neighbors.
And then for each one of those we do the same thing we add it to the results list and then we market
as visited we would add into to here so that we don't visit visit it again we don't duplicate our work
but don't get stuck in a little loop which I'll show you that is possible if you don't mark thinks is
visited and then we visit each of its neighbors.
But when we do it recursively the way that these things are ordered on the call stack I'll walk through
it and the solution video we end up with a depth first traversal.
So a couple of things.
Here's the same explanation as before we just moved through this very quickly.
We see that this is the adjacency list representing this graph structure over here.
And what we'll do is as we visit a we're going to start there.
I'll add it to my visited object key value pair and any time.
Let's say we're looking at see later on we would check.
All right which of its neighbors do we have so we have see.
All right.
Well we have a and we'll look at a.
Oh it's already visited.
So we're not going to do that anyway.
So we started a market has visited.
So then we go to A's children and we look at both of them has been visited has been visited will be
hasn't.
So we're going to recursively called depth first search on B and C but because it's recursive this is
going to happen first and all of these neighbors will happen before we come back to see it will be waiting
on the call stack then we go to B we visit be we added to our list of object visited vertices and we
look at B and it has 2 neighbors.
Well for each one we're going to check.
Has it been visited it's been visited.
Yes it has.
We're not going to recursively call it D.
Has not been.
So we keep going and you can step through this on your own but this is the idea where we're going to
keep track of what's been visited and each time through.
We have this pseudo code for each neighbor in that one verdict.
Vertexes neighbors check if it's been visited if it hasn't been visited yet recursively called depth
first search on it.
So remember recursion call the exact same function again.
Now I'll show you the more detailed pseudocode in just a moment.
But first I want to show you this.
This is the code with what we've already written that generates this graph structure.
So if you do want to follow along so you can test if things are working correctly it can be a little
harder to just make up your own graph.
It can be harder to know if it's working because it's less it's less linear than a tree.
So it's harder to think through it at least for me personally.
So you could copy this code and have the same structure as me to the same graph and you should get the
same order.
So as far as the more explicit pseudo code the more detailed pseudo code for the recursive version write
a function that accepts a starting node and we'll just go with a for now but don't make it implicit
You know don't set a default.
You pass and then you're going to create an empty list in array to store the end result that will return
at the very end.
So this will store the order.
It should be you know a and then B and then D and so on.
If we're starting from may create an object to store your visited vertices so that something like this
but it should start empty.
Ok then the slightly trickier part inside of you don't you don't have to do it inside the same function
but I'm going to do it inside of it to help her function which accepts a vertex.
So what I'll probably do is name the outer function depth first search recursive and then the inside
I'll just call DFS and this is the part of our logic that matches the pseudo code I showed you before.
So this is the actual recursive function.
This function just sets up the array it sets up the results that will return at the end.
At first originally called a recursive function because I don't know if you remember from the recursive
section we talked about helper method recursion where sometimes you need some data to persist so you
can't just have one recursive function that calls itself.
You might need an outer function.
So that's the case here.
OK so your help function should return early if the vertex is empty helper function accepts vertex.
If it's empty We're done.
The whole function should place the vertex except into the visited object market has visited and push
it into the result a way away from the results array our list that we return at the end.
Then for that vertex loop over all of its children children is the wrong term.
All of its neighbors and for each one if they have not been visited recursively invoke the helper function
with that vertex.
This helper function.
So we don't recursively call the main function we recursively call the smaller helper function and then
we evolve.
You know Mark Each one has visited added to the array check that children are visited and keep doing
the same thing.
Then the important part is the very end invoke the helper function here.
So you define it then invoke it with the starting vertex.
So we set it on its way and this inner function is going to be updating that results array and its going
to be updating the visited object each time through.
It will have access to that.
And then at the very very end return the result array.
This is what will have been constructed by these recursive functions.
So we'll end up with a b d blah blah blah.
If you use the same graph that I used.
And again you can create it easily by just copying this.
All right so you give it a shot.
Recursion can be hard but I think I tried to write it out very clearly.
Step by step but if you don't want to try.
Just watch the next video.
As I step through the call stack We'll see how it works and why it actually is up first.
That's coming up next.