All right let's get started implementing depth first traversal recursively.
So first thing we need to do is to find a function that accepts a starting node.
OK so here I have the same graph we've been working with has an adjacent to you list vertex adv. text
add add remove edge Bob Bob down here is the code as shown in the last video if you want to set up the
exact same graph it's me it looks like this although it's not perfect this tiger.
Where do you have the nice slides.
So what we want to do is come down here and just define this is going to be very long.
You might just want to go with DFS are in DFS eye for recursive and intuitive but because this is my
solution code I want people people to be able to find it and understand what it is very easily.
So I prioritize legibility over like depth first recursive and it takes a vertex a start point.
I actually like calling this start to make that clearer.
OK.
So that's the easy part.
Now we have a couple of things we need to create a list to store the end result.
We need to create an object to store the visited vertices.
OK so let's do that.
We come down here and start off by making my let's go with results.
First an empty array and then we'll also do visited as an empty object.
So next up we add to the meat of it.
Create a helper function which accepts a vertex and help function should return early if the vertex
is empty.
Let's just start there.
So let's define the helper function.
I'm just going to call DFS DFS and it takes a vertex and then down at the bottom.
I'm actually going to immediately invoke it with a start because that's the first time even though there's
no logic yet the first time through.
We want to start it off with a start.
You could also you know you can define it this way function DFS blah blah and then call DFS manually
and pass and start like that.
But I prefer to do it this way.
So function DFS Virtex and that vertex we need to check if it's empty.
That's our base case.
So we'll just do.
If there's no vertex and remember that's when we hit the end of the line.
If there's nothing to pass in to DFS.
So if there's no vertex we'll just return.
I'll just return.
OK.
It's just large enough.
Hopefully.
OK so here's a helper function.
This will do the bulk of the work.
Adding data into result and visited and then at the very end of this code will return result.
When we're done.
So let's start now with the real meat which is we need to do this logic the helper function should place
the vertex except into the visited object and push that vertex into the result array.
OK so in here we're going to add the vertex into results and add it into visited and set it equal to
true is how I'm going to do it.
So we'll do heads visited first visited of Virtex equals true that saying you know visited a is true
and then also we're going to do a results up push Virtex.
The order doesn't matter.
So that's done.
What's next loop over all of the values in the adjacency list for that vertex.
If any of those values have not been visited recursively invoke the helper function.
OK.
Well I'll tell you right now there's a small problem we can write this sort of a simple way that you
might think it should work this adjacency list referring to you know the graph it's adjacency list of
Vertex so that should give us like if we did a it should give us an array B comma C..
But let's just print that out let's to cancel the log.
This adjacency list of vertex.
OK.
And I'm actually going to execute this code now and call it g.
Depth first recursive pass in a.
So we should just see that adjacency lists that array printed out but we don't we get this error cannot
read Property adjacency list of undefined.
Lovely problem with this in javascript.
The key word this.
So what I'm going to do to make this easier is appear to define our adjacency list to equal this dot
adjacency list because in here our context the meaning of this has changed.
So I'm going to preserve it up here and just call it adjacency list.
Also it makes our code shorter.
So now if I do adjacency list it knows when we say that we're referring to this data adjacency list
where this refers to the actual graph itself.
Rerun the code.
Now we get B and C.
Cool.
OK.
So now instead of printing them out we want to loop over it.
So we're going to do a for each for each neighbor and call it naver a little fat arrow.
We're going to check if that neighbor has already been visited.
So how do we do that.
Well we have this visited object which just passen neighbor.
So that will be you know B and C for the first case if we're starting it and we want to do this if it's
not been visited if it has been visited we can ignore it but if it's not been visited what are we going
to do if it hasn't been visited recursively invoke the helper function with that vertex.
OK.
So if it's not been visited then we want to do return DFS neighbor OK.
And we're basically done.
We're missing one thing at the very end.
I'm going to walk through this of course but we need to return the actual result array that we're building.
OK so if this is first of all let's before I actually explain it let me just make sure I implemented
it correctly.
It's very easy to have a typo when you're talking.
That's the moment of truth here.
OK.
So g dot adjacent No.
What am I doing.
G dot depth first recursive starting from a.
Ok it's working.
ECF I've done this one a couple times so I know the Serhiy daughter who made the slide to that order.
But let's actually walk through what's happening on the call stack.
So if you're good just to see that it works and you're done.
Fair enough it's a bit difficult to step through.
But let's actually open up the debugger and I'm going to call down here just copy this line.
So we see what we're working with.
And at a break point.
OK.
So execute the code.
Scroll back up to the exciting area and I step through this.
All right we get our first call in depth first recursive where start is equal to a.
And we initialized some of our data.
OK.
Now then we get our first call DFS with start.
So vertex is a.
So if not vertex or Turnell that's not true.
Right so we skip that line we set visited of a to be true.
We push a result.
So the result now contains a.
So you can scroll down a has two neighbors B and C.
So we're going with whatever's listed first which is B.
That's the way that I constructed it.
I added that connection before ABC.
So we going to be first.
So let's get to that part.
Can see we get this anonymous function for the for each that's been added and we're going to check heavy
visited neighbor one neighbor is B.
We have not.
So we return DFS of B and you'll see another DFS just a moment.
Here we go.
So we still have a couple of calls here on the stack.
This is DFS of a nested inner function here.
This is the for each which is waiting to also do for each of C..
OK.
So now we're at B and I'll speed this up a bit.
We check.
Is there vertex.
Yes vertexes B.
So that line is not true.
We make sure to Markby is visited we push B and 2 result.
So now result has a comma B.
Now for each child and say child for a neighbor of B which means B really was only has one which is
D and actually misspoke.
There are two neighbors.
There's a and D.
But we've already visited a.
So you can see we're checking if we visited neighbor.
Well that's already been marked It's visited.
So this does not happen.
We don't return DFS of egg but we try again with neighbors set now.
And this is true we have not visited Deitz So we've returned DFS offensive.
And you'll see it added to the stack.
There it is.
This is defensive if the Virtex is not empty it's not falsie.
So we keep going we ignore that visited vertexes troops and now we visited the push Dion and would go
to its neighbors.
Well what neighbors this does have it has B E and F C L C first time through.
We're looking at B but we've already visited it.
So we ignore.
Now we're looking at.
E which we haven't visited.
So we had defensive e mulga this call stack is growing quite a bit defensive is up here and we check
if not Virtex All right.
There is a very Texas e so we market as visited.
We push it on to result.
Then we go to each of its neighbors.
If you look at the adjacency list for e you can see c d n f.
All right.
So we're going to start with C..
It's listed first and neighbors see we have not visited c so we returned DFS of C and it gets added
on.
Oh boy.
Should've made a smaller graph.
See Virtex is truth.
So we skip this.
We visit it.
We said it to be true and visited results up push.
Now for each of its neighbors.
What neighbors to see HAVE IT HAS A and E.
Well we've already visited day so we we don't do this we skip.
We've already visited as well haven't we.
OK.
So what happens now.
This is the real moment.
Finally we've hit a dead end.
Right.
We go to see and we've been to a deep end.
It's not what happens.
Well watch the call stack over here.
Something up hopped off there was that for each that was waiting.
So that's done.
Now we're back here where we have vertexes E and we're looking at its neighbors which we see.
And now we're looking at its other neighbor which is D which we've already visited and now we're looking
at its last neighbor ef which we have not visited.
So we're going to add defensive effort to the call stack.
There you go.
Now we're looking at F and there is an f. we ate we visited it we added to the results.
OK.
Now we look at each of its neighbors.
Is there anything that has not been visited at this point.
We've seen everything.
We visited everything on this entire graph.
So all of them are marked visited which means we're not returning anything here.
So we keep going and you'll see things get popped off eventually
and finally we end up out of our main out of our inner helper function and we're returning a result
at the very end which looks like this.
And then it should just a moment almost there.
There you go.
ABDC f.
OK.
So there's a lot to walk through.
I totally understand if you didn't make it through that I barely survived.
So the recursion can be a little difficult to follow but so just think of it as visit a node and visit
one neighbor and then revisit one of its neighbors and visit one of its neighbors.
Anyway it's a lot.
Totally understand.
I hope though that it at least makes a little bit of sense how it works how the recursion works.
Remember I had to do this adjacency list.
This is the one gotcha.
Because the context the meaning of this change in our inner function.
So to preserve it appear also shortens our code just a tiny bit.
I expect there to be a healthy amount of questions on this one.
This is a bit tricky but I think it might also help in the next video.
I'm going to do the same thing iterative.
So actually the order will be slightly different.
It will still be depth first.
There's not just one depth first order but the actual result that we get will look a little bit different
and you'll see why in just a bit.