Welcome back.
All right.
So if he made it through the recursive version or if you just watch the solution which in itself was
a bit of a battle to make it through We're now going to do the same thing iterative.
And I do recommend doing both of these because I think it helps solidify for a lot of people.
One graph traversal.
But two recursion and iterative solutions in general and sort of how they relate and how they're connected.
So what we do instead of using the call stack to help manage our state to keep track of you know where
we're going and where we've come from.
We're going to just use a stack itself.
So in javascript I'm going to just use an array to do that.
You could write your own stack class again and take advantage of that.
But for us conceptually and just to make it short we'll just use an array.
So DFS iterative Here's the basic pseudo code and then they have a more in-depth version so we'll make
a stack called S which will be an array which starts empty and we push the starting node the vertex
will start from a probably onto the stack.
That's the first thing to do then we have a loop while S is not empty while there's something in the
stack are going to pop something off of it.
Call that vertex and then we're going to check if it's not discovered meaning if we haven't visited
yet visited added to our list label it as discovered and then for each of its neighbors push them onto
the stack.
So the first time through with a well it hasn't been visited because we just started.
So we visit it and then we market and visited and then we look at a neighbor's which if we're using
the same graph are B and D.
And once again I do recommend you set up the exact same graph just to make it easier to follow along.
All right so that's the basics of it.
I'll show you the more in-depth version in just a moment.
Use this stack that stack to maintain sort of the order of things that you've been to but also where
you need to go back to and visit other neighbors because of the way depth first works are going to go
all the way down one path and then we need to go back and visit the other siblings not quite siblings
but the other branches.
All right.
So here's the more detailed pseudo code.
Write your function in a coal mine.
Depth first iterative and it should accept a starting node.
Just call it start.
Then create a stack and empty array is what I'm going to use.
But again it's up to you how you want to implement that just to keep track of vertices.
Create a list or an array to store the end result.
I'll call mine result should begin as an empty array then create an empty object to store visited vertices.
Or you could do it with an array but we need a way to keep track of what we've already visited so that
we don't try and do visit them again and get stuck in a loop and then we need to add the starting vertex
to the stack in market as visited.
So we need to have something in there so that we can add this loop while the stack has something in
it.
Otherwise if we tried to just wait to add it inside the loop it would never run because the stack starts
is empty.
So you want to put the start at the beginning.
We want to put that in the stack.
Ok so as long as the stack is not empty I would just check as long as it has a length.
Pop the next vertex from it if it's.
If it hasn't been visited yet market has visited added to the results list and push all of its neighbors
onto the stack.
So I'm just going to use another for each but rather than recursively calling you know another function
we're just going to push them onto the stack and use that stack rather than the call stack to keep track
of where we are going to use just an array to do it.
And then the very end need to return the result array.
So quick note you actually end up with a different order than what we did in the recursive solution
it still will be depth first.
But it's a different order and we'll talk about why that is in just a bit.
In the solution video.