Welcome back.
So we're going to implement the iterative solution now.
And the first thing I need to do of course is define the function itself.
So what I call this depth first recursive depth first iterative you could definitely do something simpler.
OK.
So it accepts a starting node and there's a couple things you have to get out of the way if we have
to make our stack.
We have to make our result right and our visited list or not a list object so visited we could actually
just copy this from a pure result and visited.
But I also need to make my stack.
I said this stack is going to be let's call a stack an array as well but we need to put the start in
there.
Remember this line here at the starting vertex to the stack and market visited well and was going to
do this rather than pushing it just have it initialized there.
Then after that we need to market as visited.
Let's just make sure we did everything else made the function I made the stack create a list at the
out.
Yeah.
This is all good.
We need to add the starting vortex we did that marketing's visited and then we'll add our loop.
So I'm going into sets visited make this just a separate line just so we can see these are our variables
our declarations visited of start equals true.
Again you could just use an array to to manage what's been visited and closed this.
By the way but I like doing it this way with an object it's just more explicit.
OK.
Now we need to do our Wildblue.
So while there's something in our stack so I'm just going to do while stack length.
You could do greater than zero but stacked at length that's easy because soon as we hit zero we're done
it will be false.
While the stack has something in it pop the next vertex from the stack if that vertex hasn't been visited
yet marked as visited.
So let's start with that.
I'm going to make a variable first to store what we're popping off so I'm just going to call it I don't
know current vertex equals stacked up top just like that.
Then we need to actually add current vertex to our result array.
So a result of push current vertex.
So that's what we'll return at the very end.
And then we're going to go to each of its neighbors.
And before I do that rather than redefining current vertex each time through in this loop I'm going
to come up here just to let current vertex and then down here give it a value.
Minor thing but I just don't like you know constantly re initializing current vertex inside a loop.
Now we need to add each of its neighbors to the stack.
Well if they haven't been visited yet and let's just start by accessing the neighbors so this dot adjacency
list of current vertex.
So that's going to give us if we're talking about a it would give us an array that contains B and C..
OK.
So this started Jason's the list current vertex data for each kind of a long line.
I'm going to call it neighbor could call it.
I don't know connection now.
I wouldn't call it pal.
Probably not.
So what do we do.
Well if it has not been visited.
So if inside a visited there is nothing for neighbor.
If that's the case we need to make sure that it has been visited.
OK so we're going to visit the neighbor and then we'll set it to be visited then stack push naver just
like that.
OK.
And we're basically done.
We just have to at the very end return our correct results.
And as we're going through this how about right here because the log of the stack so we can see what
we're working with.
OK.
So to execute our code and so called G.
Depth first iterative with a.
And what do we get.
I can make this larger.
OK.
So first of all the order we get is different.
And we can talk about wind just a bit but it still is depth first.
If you don't remember let me do the same thing for recursive.
We got a B.
ECF.
So the recursive version was a B D E C F which is still depth first.
The iterative version instead of going a and then B we actually end up going a and then C but as long
as we're following this path down and following one of C's neighbors and its neighbors and its neighbors
it's still depth first.
It's just we started with C rather than B because of the way that our code works and you'll see why.
So a see where we go to see Neighbors.
We've already been to a.
So if we go to eat then from it we have three choices.
We've already been to see.
So we have D or we have F and our code goes to F next and then f we can go to E.
We've already been there.
So we go to D.
And then from D E F or B.
Well we've already done this.
We've done this.
So if we go to B but it still is depth first we go here here here here here here.
So think of it this way.
This is our adjacency list.
It's the same for both versions.
What we are doing in the recursive version we started that way.
We go to be alphabetically first or whatever is first in this adjacency list is visited first.
So a to b versus in the iterative version we went to a to c and then from C we look at c we go to E
and from E.
You've already been to C and we go to F..
We're taking whatever is at the end where we're working from this direction.
If that makes sense from the end of the adjacency list rather than from the beginning.
So now let's walk through why this works.
Let me clear this and let's do iterative a.
This is what our stack looks like.
The very first time through we have a.
OK.
So we visit a bit go up through our code a bit more we're going to visit it add it to the result.
So our result now contains a then for each neighbor where we have to b and c we add them both and we
popped off and became empty.
And we add B and C.
So then what we're going to do is visit C because we are popping off the end.
So we're going to see next.
And then we're going to add it to the result.
So our result looks like a C and then we go to C's neighbors and we push those in.
So we end up with B and B because we've already visited a we don't add it in.
So the next we pop off the stack we go to E.
So we visit e a c.
OK.
So you can see that B is just patiently waiting here.
This if we are doing breadth first we would go immediately a to c and then back to B but its depth first.
So poor b is waiting.
Or in the recursive version we go a to b and then C is waiting anyway.
So we keep going and you can see that we end up with is children or neighbors F and D are both added
in and D is first and then F..
But we pop off the end.
So then we visit f next and then from f we don't have anything to add because we've already been to
E and to D.
Well we haven't been to D but we've already added it into our stack and we've already visited it meaning
we've said it to be visited true.
Otherwise you would get pushed in there again.
OK so then we pop f off.
Now we have B and D.
We start with D.
Pop off the end and then finally we get to be it's the last thing added.
So we're using a stack an array to keep track of sort of where we need to go back to.
Right.
We're going here we know we need to visit B at some point but we start with C and then from C we go
to eat and at B we're going to go to f.
But we also need to remember to go to D.
So we add D in as well but poor b has been waiting this whole time.
It's depth first.
So I do think for some people the well I think the iterative version is easier to understand but I think
that the recursive version is important to understand why it works.
It's a classic use case for recursion graft versal that is.
And I think if you can get one of these if you can understand walk through it you're good.
So this is the iterative version.
We saw the recursive version.
They both are depth first.
We do get a slightly different order.
There's not one exact precise depth first order for any given graph.
So there are different orders but they are depth first.
OK.
Next up breadth first.
We're all missing one solution.