Welcome back.
So now moving on to breadth first traversal of a graph.
So breadth first prioritises visiting all of the neighbors at a given depth before moving downwards
or visiting neighbors of neighbors.
So let's take a look at an example first with a tree.
It's you know it's always easier to talk about because we can just say horizontal before vertical before
descending down with a graph though it's a little more complicated but we can still talk about depth.
There are layers there's levels it's actually called height.
So if we look at if we start from zero there are three neighbors of zero.
So we could call each one of them one two and nine.
Each one of those have a height of 1 so we could put a little one next to them.
Then if we go from one there are three neighbors of one 11 3 and 6.
Those would have a height of 2.
If we look at nine there's eight.
And for those have a height of 2 They are two jumps away from 0 1 to something like 10 would have a
height of three.
So when I say height just imagine a little number here a 1 1 and a 1 and we have a 2 2 and a 2 and we're
going to visit all of the things on the same height horizontally.
In this case sort of diagonally across before we visit their neighbors.
So here I'll play it for you again the order we go in.
In this case it's going to be one to nine on this website.
They use the lowest number first I believe.
But we could also go 9 2 and then one.
Either way we're prioritizing visiting neighbors all neighbors for a given node or vertex before visiting
neighbors neighbors.
OK here we go.
You can see it actually draws those little numbers.
And then for one we visit all of its children shouldn't children all of its neighbors.
And we keep going.
Now of course we have to keep track of what weve already visited because like Here I pause weve already
visited five so we dont want to continually visited again
we go almost there.
OK.
So the actual order that we go in doesnt matter that much.
Like I said if were going to start 9 two and then 1 or 2 1 in the 9.
Its just that we're flushing out the entire all of the neighbors were given Virtex first.
So on our more simplified graph if we start from a we could go.
And then B or we could go B and then e.
And thats what I coded in Heres a B B.
Then go back to B and visit all of its neighbors.
So weve already done.
So we have C and D then we go back to eat and visit all of its neighbors but weve already done a we've
already done d.
So it's only neighbor that's left is F and then from F we've already visited everything else and we're
done.
So in the next video I'll have the pseudo code.