All right.
So here's the pseudo code to implement breadth first search.
It's very similar to what we did for depth first search except we actually use a different data structure
rather than using a stack.
We use a Q but I'm just going to use an array which we did for the stack but we just used different
methods rather than push and pop we'll use push and then shift so that we are adding to the end.
But we're moving from the beginning so that the first thing is also the first thing out unlike what
we had with the depth first version where the first thing had to wait until the very very end.
OK so your function except to start we'll just do a create a Q Just use an array and make a variable
called Q and place the starting vertex in it.
So there's something to start.
Then just like before.
Create our result array to store.
You know what we return to the end with our order.
Make an object to store the visited nodes like we've been doing just call it visited and then mark the
starting vertex as visited then the bulk for logic.
As long as there's anything in the queue.
So while loop while there's something in there we're going to shift the first vertex from the queue
and push it on to the array that stores what we visited that stores our result.
So take the first item out and push it to the result.
And then for each neighbor in that Virtex all of its neighbors and the adjacency list if we haven't
visited yet mark it as visited.
And then add it to that queue push it into the end.
OK.
So we have our queue.
It's the exact same process.
Well almost the same process as depth first search or depth first traversal.
The iterative version but we're using a q instead of a stack.
So we're still pushing to the end but we're now shifting from the beginning.
Otherwise it's pretty much the same.
I'm going to write the code again.
The next video.
But you could just take your code if you wrote it or take my solution and just slightly tweak it.
And at the very end we do need to return the array of all the nodes we visited.
OK.
So make this queue to store everything put the first node in there where we're starting out.
And then while there's something in that queue we're going to remove the first item we're going to add
it to our result then we're going to look at each of its neighbors.
And if they're not visited yet they're not marked as visited Mark that Mr. visited and then pushed them
to the queue and keep going and then return the entire result.
At the very end.
OK.
So let's do that in the next video.