All right.
Welcome back.
So if I made a new snippet otherwise basically doing everything the same I have my same code.
You can get that from the slides a couple of videos ago we talked about this if you want to follow with
the same graph.
So I'll start by defining breath first down here which takes a start vertex.
Just call it start and then we need to define a couple of variables so we can make my Q As an empty
array and I'm just going to add start in right out right out of the gate.
We need to make our result we could just copy this from up top any of these.
If you watch the previous videos and my variable visited to keep track of what we can do then we're
going to loop while the q has a length and the first thing that we do is remove the first node in the
queue from the beginning.
So instead of Pop we're going to do shift.
So qued shift and stored in a variable and we could define the variable here I'm going to call it current
vertex just like we did in the last video.
But I'm actually not going to redefine it in a loop going to move it up here and then set it here so
initialize it once set it over and over update it.
OK.
And then we're going to visit that node which means results push current vertex.
So if we take the first item out and then we push it into our array that we return at the end.
Now the slightly trickier part we need to go to all of its neighbors.
So that's a this adjacency list of current Virtex.
And then for each for each Naver.
But we're going to do well we're going to check if it's been visited or actually we're going to check
if it's not been visited.
That's what we care about.
Because if it hasn't been visited then we need to market has visited
just set it to true and we need to push it on to the queue
and we're actually done.
So at the end we do need to return it it's kind of a lie.
We're not quite done now are.
So the way that this one works if we step through it before we even run it here's our sort of visited
result that we're going to have at the very end.
And then here's our Q Let's do it like this.
Okay.
Perfect We start by adding a to the queue and then we remove it first thing and add it to result and
then we go to its neighbors.
This adjacency list of A for each.
So there's two things in that list there's B and there's C and we're taking the first thing.
If we if we actually looked at the list B does come but before C because I added that connection first.
So we're going to add B into our Q And we're also going to add c into the Q And then the loop starts
over and we take from the beginning we shift.
So we remove B and we add it here.
If I can type and then we add its neighbors.
So we loop through its neighbors or A&amp;E will a has already been visited so we ignore it.
So we add d to the end right here and then we remove from the beginning which gives us c so we add c
into the result.
And now we go to its neighbors what weve already been to a.
So now we have to go to eat.
So we had the after D in the queue.
Remember first in first out.
So we take out and revisit D and we go to DS neighbors weve already been to be so we don't add that
in.
We've already been to e.
Well it's in the queue at least and that's when we market.
Remember we added in after remarket visited.
OK.
So then all we have left is f..
So we add F and now we go to take that from the beginning with shift we put it here and then we're going
to go to its neighbors.
We've been to all of them so we don't actually add anything in.
And we were moved finally.
And that's what we've lost.
Now let's see if I'm making that entire thing up or if it actually works and a comment that out run
our code and we have graph dot breadth first starting from ABC.
Oh looks like we have a little issue here.
Let's see.
I found the problem.
Maybe you saw this performing.
But what we're not doing here is marking a as visited at the beginning which actually is in my pseudo
code.
And I ignored it.
You can see here marked the starting vertex as visited.
So what's happening there.
We just print out let's do it at the beginning here constantly log the queue and run my code G dot breadth
first from a 0 3 running.
OK here we go.
We start with a in there but I don't market as visited in my visited object.
So then we go take it out.
We added to our result we had the children of the neighbors B and C then we take B.
But B actually has two neighbors right.
A indeed.
But we didn't mark a as visited the first time.
So we add it back in and then we add D and then we keep going from there.
That's not right because we started that way.
So if we market visited you'll see at the very end we have a in there twice.
It's not good.
So we market visited right up here.
Well just two visited of start equals true perfect.
You could also just set that here visited the D and now if we keep that constant log rerun the code
we end up with a b c d f at the very end because a never gets added back in and it's all working.
All right.
So let's get rid of that constant log.
If we go one more time to read the first search of a a b c d e f which means going a to b to c d e f
that Brett first.
OK so we're going sort of left to right.
You can think of it whatever order they are in the edges or in the adjacency list we're going from the
beginning of the list to the end.
So I added a B before a c so we visit B C and then D before E and then f you could change it if you
really wanted to.
There's no easy as far as I know there's no shortcut to reverse.
For each some languages you can you know just specify I want to loop over this array backwards.
But the sort of easy way just to show you if we do this.
So I start reverse and I run the code.
Now you'll see we start from a but now go to a C and then B and then E and then D and then f.
So rather than a b c like left to right left or right we're going right to left.
Still breath first.
Just like with depth first.
We had different orders.
Same thing here.
And I want to be clear there's not only two orders this could be a much larger graph and we can have
you know five neighbors for a in which case it's not just b c or C B.
There would be five other two or three other neighbors to worry about.
OK.
So that's breadth first.
Hopefully you can see it's very similar to what we did with the depth first iterative solution.
Now that we have all this out of the way we're able to visit every single vertex in the graph.
We get to go to the fun stuff which has to do with mainly shortest path algorithms.
This is a really important use or really important thing to be able to do with graphs and one of the
most commonly done things in all sorts of applications whether we're talking about Uber we're talking
about Google Maps or we're talking about Google search results.
It's not just maps stuff and GPS.
So we'll talk about that in just a bit.