Hey welcome back.
We have a brand new section here.
We're still working with trees but we're doing something a little different.
So tree traversal is what we're going to focus on.
And this is the idea of basically given any tree whether it's a binary search tree or just a plain binary
tree that's unsorted or a ternary tree or some other tree that has any number of nodes.
There's no special order just any tree.
All right generic tree how do we visit every node one time.
So this is a classic computer science problem.
There are many many ways of doing it.
Contrast it with a linked list to traverse this tree to visit every node one time.
It's very easy right.
There's one linear pathway from here to there.
There is no order that you have to decide there's no decision it's just go from here to here.
So this is unsorted.
Imagine you know we're searching for value.
We want to know if 43 is in this list.
Well we start here and we go here here here.
OK.
We found it.
Or if you're looking for ninety nine we would traverse every node.
We hit the end.
Ninety nine is not in here.
Now when we talk about a tree it's very different.
So this is not a binary search tree.
It is a binary tree.
Each node has at most two children but it's not ordered in any way these values on the right are not
less than are or they're not necessarily less or greater than excuse me 10 and the values on the left
are not necessarily less than so no order we can't use our little shortcuts if we wanted to find a node
if I wanted to know if 29 was in this tree.
We would need to visit every single node in order to figure out that it's not there.
So do we start here.
Well it's probably a good place do we go left and then sort of work our way horizontally and go horizontal
again and keep going down.
Do we go all the way down to the end and then come up and then go down and then go back up go all the
way down to the right and then you know keep going down any further branches.
It's really difficult to know.
There's so many ways of doing it.
It's not like a linked list where there's one linear approach.
So that's why we have a section on this.
We wouldn't do it for a length list because there's only one way.
But with trees there are many many ways and we're going to focus on four very commonly known approaches.
They have names.
These orders.
One thing I'll say this section will take advantage of recursion more than any of the other sections
so far.
So if you skip the recursion section I highly recommend you go back and watch that because this will
be a little bit mine.
Mind blowing might be putting it nicely.
It also might just be really confusing and not fun.
So I would really make sure you understand recursion you don't have to be an expert but just know the
basics so that when I talk about it to make sense hopefully if I did a good job in the recursion section
there are two main approaches to traversing a tree something called breadth first and another called
depth first.
So these refer to the general directions.
So when we talk about breadth first search if this is our tree imagine just starting at the beginning
and then basically working across the tree first.
So 10 6 15 then continue across breath refers to the breadth of the tree.
So the worst sentence ever.
Then there's also depth first search and there's actually three main orders for DFS depth first search
that we're going to talk about.
So the idea of depth first is that you're just going down like your primary direction is going to the
end of the tree vertically and then coming back up versus breath versus going across.
So one version is something called in order and that would mean basically starting down here and then.
Well we can spend more time I don't want to just explain how every single one works.
Just want to show you there are different ways.
So this is in order.
There's also a depth first search called preorder where we work from 10 6 down to three to eight.
And then we go down the other side and go down 15 to 20.
Then there's also post order that looks like this.
So we go down to the bottom and we work our way back up like that.
So these are all different approaches different ways of searching or at the very least not even searching
just visiting every single node.
If I just asked you to print out entire tree.
There's not one easy way or one given solution right.
These are these values that we're seeing here are the order that we're visiting them.
So this would be the order they would be printed out in.
And it really depends on what you're trying to do and I'll have a video where I address that.
There are certain situations where you might want to use one versus the other.
But for now let's just leave it at the fact that there are many ways of visiting every single node in
a tree.
In fact there are so many ways that we have a whole section on it.
And this is really independent of binary search trees.
It's really just trees in general.
But we will be working with our best class just so that we don't have to duplicate code and create a
new tree class.