All right.
Welcome back.
So in the last video I mentioned there are two main strategies for traversing a tree breadth first search
for FS and depth first search DFS and these just refer to sort of the general order that we that we
visit things are we going to prioritize visiting all nodes on the same level before we move down or
do we want to work in a more vertical way which is what depth first is so fast.
What we're starting with breadth first search just means we want to visit every node on the same level
every sibling node before we look at a child.
So for us the order of this tree would look like 10 6 15 3 8 20 and then we would keep going if there
were more from left to right in our case.
But that that part is not as important to left to right.
What's more important is just that we're working horizontally.
Now I'm sure you're wondering why would you use this versus another one.
Why are there all these different orders why are we learning this.
I will talk about in a separate standalone video once we've gone over the different approaches.
Why you would use one versus the other because it's a little hard to talk about it before you have the
context of the other algorithms and how they work.
So for now I'm just going to punt on that and say I'm going to teach them if you have questions about
why.
Let's just wait I guess.
You know technically it's a video so we you kind of have to wait.
But just hang in there.
The one thing I would mention is keep in mind this is a small binary tree but we might be working with
a tree that is super super deep and narrow or something it's really wide.
It doesn't have to be a binary tree.
We could be talking about each node has 100 children.
And so these different approaches these different strategies actually have an impact depending on what
the tree looks like how the data is distributed.
Anyway that's enough about the general approach to be fast.
Let's get into specifics.
How do we implement this to do that.
We're going to take advantage of.
Q So I don't recommend creating your own Q class and going through all of that.
Just use a list or an array to model a Q Which if you didn't watch the section or you don't remember.
It's a first in first out structure.
So if we used a simple array or a list you could just use push to add things in and then shift to remove
from the beginning so that whatever was added in first is always the first thing out.
So here's our basic approach.
We're going to have two variables.
We're going to have the Q to help us keep track of things and then we're going to build up a list of
data to return at the end to our end goal.
If this was our tree and we're doing a b fs on this breath first search we want to return this at the
end of our queue at the end will be empty.
So the queue is just to help us out.
So our main idea we take the route we added to the queue.
Then we loop as long as there's anything in the queue and we dequeue a node from the cube which if you're
using an array just means shifting from the beginning of federate.
Take that node and we add it to our return value the list that we're going to return at the end.
And then we check if there's a left on that node and we added to the queue if there is then we check
if there's a rate and we added to the queue if there is and then we return at the very end after the
loop returned the variable that stores all of our values.
So if that sounds confusing it is if we don't look at it visually.
So let's walk through this briefly.
So I have to.
This is not really in a programming language but I have a cue that I'm keeping track of and then this
visited thing the structure that at the very end I'll return this list or this array of data and our
will be empty.
So we start within the root and we add 10 to our queue.
This is like our list of okay things we need to do is start to do list and then we start our loop which
just says while there is something in the queue so our queue has something we're going to take it out.
We're going to add it to our visited list and then we're going to check if there's a left.
Is there a left.
Yes.
So we add that to the queue.
Then we check.
Is there right.
Yes.
15 so we add that to the queue then the loop starts over and we remove the first thing from the queue
first thing and first thing out.
So we take six and now we add it to our list that we visited we have visited six.
Now we check is there left.
Yes.
So we're going to add it in.
So that gives us three.
Is there a right.
Yes.
So we add an 8 and then we're done.
We start over.
We're not done done.
We're done with six.
And now we take 15 out.
So hopefully you can see already this pattern right we're going this level finished than this level
this level and we're creating this queue to help us remember the things that need to come next.
But we're not visiting them next or waiting to visit them until we've finished a horizontal level the
breadth first search.
So we take 15 out and we add it to our list that we visited and would check if there's a left is there
no.
Is there a right.
Yes.
So we add Ian and then start over we take three hours and we keep going so there's no left no right.
We don't add anything to the queue.
Same thing with eight.
We take eight out.
There's no left no right.
So we had that in.
Then we get to 20.
Now the queue is empty which is how we know we're done and we return this value at the end.
This is our breath first search 10 6 15 3 8 and 20.
This is how we traversed it.
This is the order we visited things.
So we take advantage of a cue to just store it's like a To Do list.
Don't forget this comeback but we take things from the beginning and we add to the end to the first
thing it is the first thing out.
Hopefully that explanation makes sense.
The pseudo code is pretty clear I think.
So try and follow this and give it your best shot in the next video.
I have a solution.