All right.
Welcome back.
Let's implement our breath first search.
So I'm going to go over and the very first thing is I'm going to find a method we could call it be EF-S
or breath for search.
It really doesn't matter.
I mean to do be a Fester's because it's really annoying to type and it doesn't need to take any arguments.
We're just trying to visit every single node.
OK.
And right off the bat we need two things.
First we need our data which is what will return at the end.
So I'll just make an empty array.
We also have a couple of other variables so I'll just declare them all together.
We have our Q Which will also be an empty array and we can just start with that.
And the first thing that will do is place the root node in the queue.
OK so that's easy enough.
Q Dot push this dot Rube's.
So that puts.
If this is the tree we're working with that puts 10 in there and then we're just going to loop as long
as there's anything in the queue.
We're going to take dequeue from.
Q So let's just start with that loop while there's anything in the queue.
So if we just did while Q In javascript if we have an empty array and we negate it this tells us that
we get false which means that an empty array is truthy.
So that's not what we want.
It's not like an empty string or some languages an empty array is falsie because it's empty.
Not the case.
So what we're going to do instead is wild queue length.
So 0 is falsie as we can see there are the we can get back to false anyway.
It didn't make any sense.
I'm sorry if I did a bad job explaining that.
But we can't just say while.
Q When you say while Q Dot length.
So while there is something in the Q We're going to remove something from the beginning of that Q So
when do Q shift and let's put this in a variable.
But rather than inside this loop continuing to make a new variable over and over and over and redeclare
it.
Let's actually go up here and make another variable just call the node and let's start it as one we
actually do this route like this.
OK I'm going to.
This is just me being sort of ridiculous but I like all this to line up.
OK let's just do that.
It really doesn't matter.
You could just do three different vars anyway.
We have nodes start as root then we can use to push node.
It doesn't really matter but now I don't have to do this var node equals and just have this var key
word in a loop.
It's not a good idea.
So I'm just going to now assign node to b q shift.
Now of course I could just started note as nothing could just made it undefined or no.
But this works fine for me.
So we take from the beginning of the queue.
So if we're pushing at the end we're going to shift from the beginning in order to get that first in
first out.
Then we need to take that note and add it to the list that we're going to return.
Then we check if there's a left.
We add that to the queue we end it.
If there's a write we add that to the queue as well.
So we know it was queued up shift.
Now we're going to do data push node so that's adding into our list that we're going to return to if
this is our queue empty and this is our data empty.
The very very first thing that happened is that we pushed.
Sorry about that Syren if you could hear that queued up push 10 given this tree.
Then while queued up length node equals take this out and added into our data.
Now we're going to check if there's a left if node left.
Then we'll do a Q push node left and will do the same thing.
If there's a right so we add that in to that.
Q And that's actually it for our loop then at the end.
We just need to return this data variable where we're building up everything we've visited.
So just to reiterate that if we take 10 from the beginning which was in our queue we added data then
we're going to check is there left for 10.
Well given our structure yes it's six.
So we had six in 10.
We do know right.
Is there are no doubt right.
Yes it's 15.
So cued up push 15 and then the loop starts over.
There's still length to the queue.
So now node is equal to 6 it would take 6 out and we push it on to data which is what we visited.
And we return at the end and then we check if there's a left there is.
So we add that in.
Which is three.
And would do the same thing with the right.
We add that in.
Which is eight.
And we keep going and I did this in the last video so I won't step through every single moment.
But let's just see if it works if it does work.
We expect to get this.
So I'll copy this over.
This is what we want.
Let's try running it.
So down here I have the code to actually build the tree.
And now I'm going to do a tree.
B fs.
Wow that's annoying.
Maybe I should just push the value in to make this easier to see what's happening.
So let's do push no doubt value.
It really doesn't matter.
But just to make this easier to see
OK.
So we got 10 6 15 3 8 20 and we're supposed to get 10 615 3:08 20 that are breadth first all the way
across all the way across all the way across.
So horizontal before we go vertical breath before depth.
So that's be EF-S it's relatively straightforward if you take advantage of a queue.
Remember first in first out just a list of things that we need to visit.
We're keeping track of it and it grows and it doesn't really matter.
Yes this is hard coded for left and right.
But if this was a ternary tree we could add you know first second and third child.
Or we could do it dynamically and have a loop and loop over all the children.
So it doesn't have to be a binary tree.
It's the same basic principle.
You use a.
Q All right.
So that be EF-S.