Hey welcome back.
We're pushing on with tree traversal.
Now we start depth first search.
So there are three different orders within depth first search that we're going to talk about.
But all of them are DFS algorithms meaning that they pursue all nodes they visit or traverse nodes vertically
down to the end of the tree before visiting sibling nodes.
So that's maybe not the most technical explanation but it means that we're going to traverse down until
we hit the end of the tree at some point and then from there there's a couple of options as far as the
order that we do things.
But we're working down first depth first rather than horizontally breath first so we can break down
tree traversal into three main steps.
So for any node we need to at some point visit the actual node itself like building a list or printing
it out.
We need to add it to the list or we need to print it out whatever we're doing.
So we have to actually do the visit.
Then we also need to explore the entire left side and the entire right side at least when we're talking
about a binary tree.
If we have you know a turn every tree then we need to do the first the second and third children.
But let's just stick with binary trees for now.
So we have to at some point explore the node and then traverse the left and traverse the right.
And those three things just by changing the order that we do them in in our code literally copying a
line pasting it above the line removing it below another line will change the output that we get.
So with our DFS algorithms our end goal just like with the breadth first search is to just build an
array or a list or if you prefer just print them out.
But basically we want to visit them in this order in pre order which is what we're starting with.
Basically means you're going to visit the node first then we look at the entire left side.
We traverse the left then we traverse the right and that's true for any node.
So we start off at 10.
We visited.
Meaning we added to our list or we printed out.
Then we explore the left side.
So that means starting off at 6.
And so we visit six meeting meaning we add it to our list or printed out.
Then we traversed the entire left side then the entire right side.
So that means three and then eight.
There's nothing to traverse after them.
So they get visited.
Now we go back to 10 because remember we visited 10.
Then we looked at the left side.
Now we have to look at the right side of 10 10 we're still waiting to have its right side visited.
And so we've got 15 and then 20.
So we have those three operations.
We visit the node we look at the left and we look at the right just by changing the order that we do
those in we'll have a large very drastic impact on the output order the actual traversal order.
And so we're we're going to talk about preorder in this video.
Then there's also post order and in order they are all depth first search algorithms but there are different
orders and we just have to shift one or two lines of code.
So here are the basic steps that I recommend you can do this iterative.
It's definitely shorter and easier to do it recursively.
So again if you haven't done the Rickerson recursion section where you don't know recursion I def. recommend
you review that section.
OK.
So we're going to create a variable just like we did before to store the values that we visited.
So at the end we'll just return that call it data or visited or whatever then we're going to create
a variable called Current and just store the root of the tree in there.
So that's where we start off.
Now the slightly tricky part we're going to write a second helper function so we're going to have our
preorder function takes no arguments in our second function which takes a node and it accepts and notice
an argument and all that it does is we push the value of the node to the variable that stores our values
that we return to the end so we visit the node by adding it to the array or to the list.
Then we check if it has a left if it has no doubt left property we're going to recursively call the
helper function again.
And then do the same thing on the right if it has a write property call the function on the right.
So basically we have this helper function where for a given node we start with the route.
We push that node to the list that we're looking at to our end result our data.
So we visit the room and then move recursively to the same thing for the left and the same thing for
the right.
So we'll walk through how this works in the solution will look at a call stack.
It can be a little bit crazy to try and visualize but if you can just write a helper function that accepts
a node it takes the value of that node pushes it to our or our array that we return at the end.
Then we check if there's a left we call the same helper function.
I would just call it traverse we called traverse on the left side of the node and then we also the next
line below.
If there is a write property called traverse on the right side then we're going to invoke that helper
function with the current variable which is started at the root.
Where is that right here.
And then at the very end return the array of values or the list of values that we've visited.
So I know it seems intimidating.
If you're not comfortable with recursion I totally get that this is relatively.
This is pretty much word for word.
Well not word for word.
Line for line what you need to do.
You can do this solution in just a couple of lines maybe eight lines seven lines.
And once you get this one it's very very similar to the other two that the two other depth first search
orders.
So try it out.
Don't get discouraged if you can't do it because in the next video I'm going to have a pretty thorough
solution where we actually walk through step by step how it works.