All right.
So let's try implementing this depth first search pre order.
So we're going to go over here to define the function.
I'll just call it DFS pre order like this.
And then inside of here I'm going to start by making our variable data that will return at the very
end.
So I could actually go down to the very end and return data.
This is just the order that we're visiting the nodes then we'll make a variable called Current and set
it to be the root
just like that.
Now for the tricky part write a helper function we'll call it traverse that accepts a node.
So I'm just going to do that actually nested inside of your function traverse accepts a node and the
first thing that we do is push the value of the node to our variable data.
So we'll do data push node.
Then we check if there's a left property if there is we call the helper function with the Left property
and we do the same for the right.
So we could just do if node left.
What are we going to do.
We're going to call traverse no doubt left.
So this is traverse we're recursively calling it and we do the same thing.
No doubt right traverse node dot right.
And that's actually it for our solution.
Well that's a lie.
We have to actually invoke traverse which is what I talked about done here.
Invoke the helper function with the current variable.
So that's traverse current which is the root.
And actually he honestly don't even need this current variable.
You could just do traverse this route.
But what.
Sending a current variable allows you to do a user could specify a starting node to start from.
They may not want to traverse from the root if you have a massive tree.
I'll just do this though this route.
OK.
So if we actually run this right now with this tree 10:6 15 3:08 20.
Let me just save this.
Executed.
Let's see if it works.
Oh you know what I'm realizing it's easier again to push the value instead of the entire node.
So let's try rerunning one more time tree.
DFS pre order.
Here's what we end up with 10 6 3 8 15 20.
And that is the correct depth first search pre order.
So now let's get to the harder part which is explaining how the heck that works.
So I'm going to come down here and do a tree dot DFS preorder and add a breakpoint there.
Now let's step through what happened to execute this code.
OK.
So I'm going to order the call stack and step through this very first thing and make our array called
data we call traverse on the roots.
OK now if we look at the call stack we now have a traverse call and we're pushing 10 into our array
that we're returning called data.
So 10 is in there.
Then we check if there's a left and there is.
So we call traverse on the left and that left node is 6.
So we end up with another call added to the stack this time on 6.
And so we now push 6 into our array.
So our data array has 10 and then 6 and we check is there left on 6.
Yes there is.
So then we traverse no dot left which is three.
And so we end up with another call added on top.
Now we're working with three day to push node value.
So we add three into our list so we have 10 6.
Now three is in that data and we check.
Is there no doubt left.
No there is not.
So we don't traverse no debt left.
Is there no dot right.
Nope there's not.
So we don't traverse that either which means we're done with this call with three.
So you'll watch it actually pop off here.
There we go.
And now we go back to where we were on six because six we stopped at this line.
Right.
We're waiting for this traverse to finish.
Now we get to the right.
Is there a right side.
Yes there is.
So that is eight.
So now we traverse eight.
So we add one more call right there to traverse day to push node value which is 8.
So now we have 10 6 3 8.
Then we check is there left.
There's not is there right.
There's not.
So we're done like a few times and it gets popped off.
There we go.
Now we're back to six at the end because this finished we traverse the right side of 6.
We did the left than the right.
There's nothing there.
So we're done with six.
Now we're back to 10.
So we did the entire left side of 10.
Now we're going to do the right side.
So the way that this works is that we visit a node and then we traverse the entire left side and then
traverse the entire right side.
That's sort of the high level overview but the way recursively it works.
It can be a little tricky to step through.
So now we're on 10.
We finished pushing in for 10.
It was very easy.
We've traversed the entire left.
Now we have to traverse the right.
So is there a right.
Yes 15.
So we traverse 15.
So we get a call added to our call stack for 15.
We push 15 into our list.
Now the list is 10 6 3 8 15 and recheck.
Is there a left there is not a left for 15.
So we go to the next line.
Is there a right and there is.
Which is 20.
So we traverse 20 and traversing 20 really just involves you can see the call being added over here
day to push 20.
So we had 20 in and we've now visited every node.
We don't actually know that Intel no doubt left so this is going to be false.
There's no left there's no right.
So 20 gets popped off the call stack and then the call for 15 gets popped off and then the call for
10.
The original one is popped off and we finished all traverses So this is the line that caused all that
trouble.
And this is what data now looks like.
Now we just returned data and we're done.
Well there we go now.
And that's the order revisit things.
So to recap what we do is recursively we visit a node then we visit the entire left side and then the
entire right side.
So this order is really significant.
And you'll see in the next two videos or next two solutions for different orders.
All we have to do is tweak the order that this happens.
OK.
So that's coming up next.