All right.
Welcome back.
Next up we're going to take a look at post order.
So just a slight tweak or a variation on what we wrote in the last video where we're basically going
to change the order of one line that we're going to move which will make a significant difference to
the actual output order.
So if you watch the two videos ago when I introduced the depth first search I talked about there's three
main operations or things that we do for any node we need to at some point visit the node itself like
10.
Then we also need to traverse the entire left half and the entire right side.
I shouldn't say half because it's not necessarily half but the entire left side and the right branch.
And then do the same thing on this node.
So do we visit it first then look at the left then the right.
That's what we did in pre order.
If we go back here we start off by visiting 10 adding it to our list then looking at the left side then
once the entire Left is done then we go to the right.
So then we get to six.
We visit six.
We look at the left then the right.
There's nothing after she would just visit three and eight and then we finish out the right side of
10.
So that's pretty order.
We visit the node first then left then right.
Post order works differently.
You might be able to tell by the name post after we visit a node after we have looked at the left and
the right.
So we explore everything first we traversed the entire tree or the entire branch from a given node the
left and the right.
Then we visit the node.
So in post order we started 10 but we're not going to visit it.
We're going to look at the left and go all the way down to the left then all the way down to the right
and then we visit a node.
So we start at 10.
We go all the way to the left traverse.
So then we get to six.
We're going to go all the way to the left than the right and then add six in.
So that means adding three in first then we add the right.
We visit eight.
Now we visit six because we explored the left and the right of six then we don't visit 10 yet.
We've only done the left side of 10.
Now we do the right side.
So we go to the right of 15 which is 15 and from there there's no left.
So we explore the right.
We get to 20.
There's nothing after that so we add 20 and we explore and revisit 20 and we work our way back to 15
then finally 10.
So in this example in post order the route is the last thing that's visited for any node.
We explore all children before we we actually visit the node.
Now practically what this means is you just need to change the order of your code.
So if you wrote the solution or you're looking at my solution from the last video for preorder everything's
pretty much the same.
We're going to write a function.
It doesn't take any arguments.
We're going to make an array or a list to store the values of the things we visited so that we can return
it at the end.
We are then going to write a helper function that accepts a node and recursively.
We're going to do these three steps.
If there's a left property call the helper function on the left property if there's a right property
traverse the right property and then push the value of the node to our variable that stores our visited
values and then invoke the helper function with the current variable.
And then finally return the array of values.
So this is copy and pasted from the last two videos that go the same pseudo code except the order is
different.
Rather than pushing first and then doing the left and right we're going to explore the left explore
the right and then push the value in.
So that's Post order.
Give it a shot.
Just you know alter the code if you'd like.
It's good practice to write from scratch but if you're short for time or you're bored then just copy
and paste the line change the order and make sure that you get the expected output.
So if you use the exact same tree this is the output you should get for post order compared to do this
order here for preorder.
So give it a shot and see if you can get it to work.