Welcome back.
Let's get to work on post order.
So we're going to take any node.
We're going to explore the entire left side then the right side.
And then finally visit the node itself.
Add it to our list.
Let's hop over to my code and I'm just going to define depth first search post order like this will
make our data array to store our data and at the end will return data.
Then I'm going to define my function traverse the helper function that takes a node but rather than
pushing in the data first and then looking at the left and looking at the right we're going to do if
node left traverse nodes out left if node right traverse no doubt right.
And then afterwards data up push node value.
And then we need to invoke traverse at the end traverse with the route this dot route.
And that's it.
So it's the exact same code except we move this line where we actually visit the node by adding it to
the array we moved it after we explore the left and the right.
So would you left then right then we push it in and if we just verify that it works first.
Let's do both a tree dot DFS preorder tree dot DFS posts.
Nope that tree again.
And let's make sure it works.
So execute my code and it's a should have known better something giving me the last return value.
OK here we go.
So this was what we just did.
This is from the last video.
So you can see this is working we're getting the expected order.
So if this is our tree here it's the same that I had in the slides.
The order would be three and then eight then six not ten.
We still have to go down the right side.
So that means 20 15.
And then finally you get back to 10 until this work correctly.
Compare that with preorder where we visit and then look at the left and then the right.
So we visit 10.
Then we go down to the left.
We visit six.
We visit three.
Then we go to the right.
We visit eight.
Then we're back at 10.
We visit the right side 15 and 20 and that's all there is to changing the order to doing a post order
depth first search or depth first traversal.