Welcome back.
So we have one more depth first search order to talk about.
It's called in order.
So if we go back to those three pieces three puzzle pieces we change the order of them.
Then it changes the output entirely.
So those three things are at some point.
We actually visit the node then we traverse the entire left and we traverse the entire right.
So within order we're going to traverse the entire left side then visit the node and then traverse the
entire right side.
So what that means is if we start with 10 we traversed the entire left.
So that means going to 6.
OK.
So we traverse the entire Left or 6 meaning we hit 3.
We visit three first.
There's nothing to traverse.
It's a leaf.
Then we go to six and we visit six and then we traverse it right.
We get to eight.
There's nothing to traverse so we visit eight and it's added to the list.
We go back to 10 so we did the entire left side of 10 traversed traverse.
Now we visit 10.
Now we traverse the right side and that adds 15 and then we visit 20.
So this is the same pseudo code except that in our help or function we do the left side we traverse
the left side recursively then we push the value of the node to a variable then we traverse the right.
So the end goal just like all of our other traversal methods is to build a list or an array containing
the values in the order that they were visited.
Or you could just print them out.
But I would do this so that you can see exactly what's happening it's easier to compare.
If you just build an array or a list.
So with this sample tree our output would be 3 6 8 10 15 20.
So we do the left side visit the node then the right side just need to change a single line of code.
And contrast that with preorder.
Remember here we visit the node then the left then the right with post order we traverse all the way
to the left all the way to the right and then we visit a node OK.
So give us a shot if you have the code from the last two videos then just change that one line and you
should be good to go.