Welcome back.
So we have our final implementation of DFS depth first search.
It's going to be really fast.
We just need to change a line from our last solution.
So to recap on every node we traverse the left then we visit the node then we traverse the right.
So if we go over here and I add in a solution.
So DFS in order I'm not even going to bother typing the entire thing again.
I'm just going to copy it over and change this so that when we traverse we traverse the left then we
visit by pushing a data into or pushing the node value into our data array.
And then we do the right side.
So if we start here we're going to traverse the left and we get to hear what we still need to traverse
the left.
Then there's nowhere else to go.
So we push no de-value 3 then we're back to this one which is waiting.
And we did the left.
So now we visit six and we do the right.
Then we're back to 10.
We did the left side.
Now we visit 10 and then we go to the right side and so on.
OK.
So let's see if it works.
Treat it.
DFS in order we get 3 6 8 10 15 20.
And that's what we expect.
3 6 8 10 15 20.
So those are the three orders that we were going to talk about a small change if you prefer.
You can actually rewrite this code like this.
You can do rather than a conditional do no doubt left and traverse node and do the same thing down here.
No doubt right.
And traverse node it's just a small change if you don't want to do the conditional.
We're just checking if it if it's truthy.
If it's non-zero this will do the same thing.
I personally I think I actually prefer this slightly more verbose because I like putting that in there
but I know some students are sticklers for making things as succinct as possible.
So you could do this and this applies to all three the solution so it's not just this one but I'll leave
it in here and I'll leave this one.
And if just so that we have some variety in our solutions.
All right.
So that's depth first search.
Three different ways three different flavors in every approach we're working vertically first.
If that makes sense rather than horizontally going back and forth breadth first search Well I'd like
to do next is add a quick video where I talk about the merits of these approaches and why you would
use one or for the other.