All right.
So now that we've implemented a couple of ways of traversing a tree spend a lot of time on it.
Let's talk about which one is better.
Which one should you use.
And SPOILER ALERT The answer is that it depends.
And there's pros and cons to all of them and it's really just dependent on your situation which is always
an annoying answer I know.
So let's start by just talking about breadth first search in general compared to depth first search
in general.
So ignoring the order Post order preorder in order put that aside.
Breath versus depth.
Which one would you use in a given scenario.
Well I think it depends on the tree.
If you have a tree that is fully fleshed out like this tree it's as wide as it can be the entire way
down.
If we're working with a breath first search remember that we have this cue that we're storing all of
the nodes we have yet to visit all of the children.
So let's say we're here we're going to visit this node and then add left and right to a queue and then
go to this node at left and right here left right.
So our queue grows and it stores a bunch of pieces of data a bunch of nodes.
So by the time we're down here or imagine we have something with a height of like 100 levels down we're
going to have to store a ton of data in our queue just in memory.
By the end that queue will be empty.
But I'm talking about space complexity the time complexity of depth versus breadth first Doesn't matter
though the same.
We're visiting every node one time so that's irrelevant.
But the space that's used up in this scenario could be a lot more.
If you're if you're talking a breath first on a wide tree versus on depth first we're not storing all
of those nodes across the tree.
We only have to keep track of the nodes in a in a given branch all the way down to the end.
And the way that we implemented it earlier in the section was using recursion.
So each one of these is a frame and the call stack where we're waiting for something else to happen.
So in this sort of tree where it's a lot wider than it is deep then depth first search would use less
space.
It's again not about time we're visiting every node once it's the same amount of work it's just how
much space we take up in the process of doing that work.
If we contrast that with this somewhat more depressing binary search tree if we traverse this entire
thing breadth first the space that we take up in memory is basically nothing.
Our Q is never going to have more than one item in it.
We start here.
We visit this.
We add it's right node to our queue and then we move to this.
And we popped off the queue or we actually shift it and then we take this and we added a child to the
queue.
So we have one thing in memory at any given time really in our queue.
But if we're traversing it depth first if this tree is really really long then that means a ton of level
so we have to go down and keep every other level above it in memory.
So that's something to consider.
Most of the time your trees will look something like well I shouldn't say most of the time but but most
of my experience is with trees that looks something like this rather than a super super long one sided
tree which doesn't make much sense to keep as a tree.
OK.
So to summarize that time complexity is the same.
We're visiting every node once.
It doesn't matter.
You know if we have 100 nodes we're going to visit every single one breath first in depth first same
amount of time space though it really depends on the structure of the tree if it's a really wide tree
breadth breadth first could store or take up a lot more space for that.
Q If it's a really deep long story then depth first could end up taking up more space.
Okay.
The last thing I'd like to do is quickly talk about when or potential use cases for the different variants
of depth first search.
So preorder post order in in and in order there all depth first variants.
Why would you potentially use one over the other and there's not really a great answer.
I'm going to give you a couple of examples.
This is actually a question I put to some of my teacher friends to see what their input was what they
tell their classes.
And pretty much the only feedback I got back was I just teach them and tell them they need to know it
because it's good for them and I don't really have any great examples about when you would use one versus
the other.
Well I'm just doing a little bit more than that.
I have a couple of examples but this isn't going to be super comprehensive but here's one example.
When you use in order on a binary search tree like we have here if we look at the data we get back it
is in order.
We get all the nodes in the tree in their underlying order.
So it goes from lowest to highest.
So if you want to take an entire large binary search tree where everything to the right is greater than
a node its parent node everything to the left is less than the parent node.
If you use a depth first traversal in order you will end up with the set of all the nodes in their order
depending on what you're doing.
That could be useful if you wanted to you know grab them in a list or put them in a database or do something
with them in that order.
It's kind of a stretch but that is worth knowing that that's a side effect of how this works on a binary
search tree.
Now I want to talk about preorder.
Just to recap how that one works.
We visit a node first and then do the left and then the right.
And what we end up with in this case is a list that looks like 10 6 3 8 15 20.
And this can be useful if you're trying to clone or duplicate a tree or you want to store it you want
to like flatten it out so you can store it in a file or a database or something and then recreate it
from that serialized structure.
Basically you freeze dry it you suspended in time and then when you're ready to rehydrated you could
go and make this the route and then navigate and iterate through this list and you make this a child
and you make that a child and it's given to you in an order where you could reconstruct the tree versus
if we look at something like this.
In order you start off with three at the beginning of the list you don't know what the root of the tree
is.
Versus here you immediately know this is the root.
This is the left and so on.
So those are just two situations where one of those variants might make more sense but remember at the
end of the day they're very very easy to switch between.
It's not like you're making some massive decision that you can't undo.
Right.
You just change one line you move it to the beginning or the end of that function call and then you
have the other order.
So really the bigger concern is breath versus depth first.
All right.
So let's quickly recap trees here.
There are nonlinear data structure.
They contain a bunch of nodes.
There's a single root and then a bunch of are usually a bunch of child nodes.
Binary trees are a special case where we can have values of any type but each node can have at most
two children for a parent binary search trees.
On the other hand are a more specific version of a binary tree.
So we have trees and then binary trees and then binary search trees and binary search trees have to
fulfill a special condition or a form of an ordered or a sorted tree.
So every node to the left for Paran is a less than its value and every node to the right of a parent
is greater.
So you can only have a binary search tree with data with data that is comparable pieces of data where
you can say this is definitely less than this is definitely greater than.
Okay.
And then also what we just spend a lot of time talking about we can search or traverse trees using breadth
first search and depth first search and within depth first.
There are three variants we discussed three orders in order Post order and pre order.
OK there's a lot about trees.
I think I've said this had every section at the very end.
I recommend you take a break.
Do not try and powered through all of this because I'm afraid you're going to lose your mind.
OK.