Hey welcome back.
So we have a brand new section with a new data structure called the hash table also known pretty commonly
as a hash map.
So these are used so frequently you've probably used them all the time.
I certainly have because they're built in to pretty much every programming language out there whether
we're talking about javascript or Python or Ruby or Java.
Scala pretty much every language has a variation of a hash table or hash map built in as a default type.
So you don't have to do anything just like with an array.
Most languages have a built in array or list type and you can just use it out of the box.
So we will be implementing our own version.
We will make our own.
But just like with an array you're probably in ninety nine point ninety nine percent of those cases
going to want to use the built in array class or list class or whatever similar structure there is.
There's no reason to reinvent the wheel.
Same with the hash table.
But there's a lot of really cool stuff for us to talk about as to how they work what hashing is I should
actually just talk about that on this slide.
So in this section we're going to explain what a hash table is.
That will be in this video then.
Oh two for one there.
Well defined with a hashing algorithm is define what a hashing algorithm.
Boy these slides.
That's not a deal.
So define what a hashing algorithm is.
Discuss what makes a good hashing algorithm.
There are certain characteristics we're looking for.
Then we'll talk about what happens when collisions occur and a hash table.
What that means for there to be a collision and then two strategies for handling them something called
Separate chaining.
And another thing called linear probing.
Those sound like two different methods of torture.
So we'll get there.
But let's start by just discussing what a hash table is.
So as I already mentioned these are all over the place.
You've probably used them in whatever programming language you prefer.
Hash tables are used to store key value pairs and yes so are arrays arrays associate a key like 0 or
1 or 2 or 3 to a value which could be anything else.
But those are strictly numeric hash tables are not.
And on top of that the keys in a hash table are not ordered.
So in an array of course the index indices start from zero and they go up to some number that keep going.
There is a specific implicit order hash tables.
That's not the case.
And another cool thing about hash tables is that they are fast for finding values for adding new values
for removing values.
It's all fast.
So we'll talk about why that is and how it works.
But first let's go into more detail on just why you should care.
So as I mentioned pretty much every language out there has some sort of hash table structure because
of their speed.
They're used really commonly and they're also just data itself lends often lent itself to being stored
this way.
Yeah if you have sequential data great you could use an array if everything you know has an order and
there's a number that makes sense to associate it with a position.
Use an array.
But a lot of the time our data may not fit that pattern.
So we could use a hash map or a hash table.
So here's just a quick overview from certain languages.
These are what their implementations of hash maps are hash tables are known as so Python has a dictionary
or dict Javascript has objects and maps.
And I did put an asterisk here because in objects you actually are only allowed to use strings as keys
but it's the same idea behind the scenes.
It's implemented basically as a hash table.
Java go in Skala have something called a map or map ask Ruby.
They don't even bother.
It's just called a hash.
So these are all our key value data stores and they implement hash tables so hash tables are sort of
a generic idea and you can implement them in many ways.
Dictionaries and Python maps and objects and Javascript maps and Java go probably.
OK.
So let's pretend that those disappear we're not able to use the basic builtin javascript objects or
Python dictionaries if we still want a key value data store.
We need to implement our own.
So that's what we're going to do.
I imagine they just mysteriously disappear.
How would we do.
How do we write our own version of a key value pair hash table a data store.
So imagine we want to store some colors where we're making a Web site we have color codes hexadecimal
which are really difficult to keep track of or to differentiate between.
So we could just store mentalists like this.
But this you know there's no there's an order here that's implicit but there's no reason that we'd want
to store them in a particular order.
It doesn't matter.
I don't know which color this is what color that is.
You get the point hopefully this is not a great way of storing colors unless we just need a random color
at any point that would work if we're just picking something random out of here.
Great but if we need particular colors at a particular moment it's not great it's not readable.
What do these colors correspond to.
So rather than using indices or numbers to access the colors it would be much better to use you know
human readable keys like pink which is pink or a version of one type of pink orange red might be it
is this color cyan color this would be much better if I could just say you know give me colors of pink
or colors of Scion which Here we go colors of Cyan is much better than colors too.
So we're going to try and implement this structure on our own even though of course in javascript and
Python you would be able to do this out of the box.
But if we didn't have access to dictionaries or objects or maps how would we do this.
So that's what the section is focused on.
I think it's kind of fun because we get to go into some some fun detail onto what hashing is what hashing
functions are going to talk a little bit about some math get into prime number land discuss how prime
numbers play a role in this.
It's all sort of fun stuff.
So that's our goal.
Reinvent this basic mapping key value pairs.