All right.
So in the last video we talked about wanting to store information using a key like Suyin or pink or
H any string.
And by the way in a data and data table and a hash table it doesn't have to be a string but we're just
going to focus on strings just to narrow down some of the complexity.
But either way whatever we use it's not a number.
So let's say we're using a string like cyan rather than a number like 0 or 2 or 1 million.
This is a lot clearer.
So we want human readability.
But of course it needs to also work.
It needs to be a real thing on our computer.
And unfortunately computers don't know how to find something or insert something at index pink or index
hello world are out damn spot or h it just computers don't know how to do that.
Thankfully we have hash tables to the rescue.
OK.
So quickly just a little preface here.
Remember that every language at least every language I've worked with has a built in implementation
of a hash table.
We are actually reinventing the wheel here which is usually something I try and avoid in these courses
but it's just to help us understand how this works.
It's important to understand what's happening behind the scenes.
I like to think of it as I don't know we're building a little model like a toy model of a car engine
on our desk to help us understand how real car engines work.
If you actually had to use one you would probably pick the Ferrari engine that you magically have laying
around in your house rather than the toy model you built out of cardboard.
But either way you understand how they work now.
I don't know if it's a good analogy honestly.
So that's what we're doing we're trying to build a model to understand how it works and to do that.
We're going to use an array or a list a way of storing information where we have to use numbers.
So what we do in a hash table is we take an input.
Again we're narrowing it down to say strings like hello or pink We need a way to take pink and turn
it into a number that we can store in the array.
So if our array goes from 0 to 99 it has 100 slots 0 to 99 we need a way to convert pink to a number
between 0 and 99 and then we store the data at that number.
So there are functions that help us do that and they're called hash functions or hashing functions.
They actually have a separate video after this one where I talk about the complications of writing a
good hash function.
Why it's difficult.
We'll talk about some examples of existing famous hash functions.
They are used all over the place.
There are very intense teams of people like multi-country efforts of people working on hash functions
because they have a lot of applications in security and cryptography.
But what we're talking about are going to be very simple and limited in scope hash functions.
The idea is we pass in a string.
If this is our array where we are storing our data we have 10 slots we pass in a number to our hash
function.
There are many many implementations just some mysterious hash function over here.
I guess you can't see where I'm pointing to my right.
It's a box.
If I pass in the string pink it needs to give me some number between 0 and 9.
And every time I pass and pink it should give me the same number.
So it happened to give me zero.
The way this hash function is worked is worked the way this hash function is built.
It gives me zero.
So I store pink as the key and then this as the value at index 0 then I go to the same hash function
and I say hey here is orange red.
What does that convert to.
Well it happens to convert to 7.
So I start at 7.
I do the same thing for Psion and I get three.
So I start at three.
So that's how we go about storing things.
Now if somebody asked me hey what's an index.
I don't know index Suyin.
Well our code still doesn't know what index Suyin is but I can take Suyin and pass it to the hash function
again and say hey what was the number you gave me earlier and it gives me 3 and then I go to index 3.
Same thing for pink.
So this is why it's important we always get the same number back if it's not.
If that doesn't happen then this whole thing is broken.
Because if I ask for what's the index of Suyin and it gives me nine.
There's nothing here.
It always has to be the same thing.
Once we've inserted something we need it to be consistent.
So reading a hash function that works that takes a string or any piece of data an image a PTF a video
and somehow spits out a number.
It's not easy and that's what we'll talk about in the next video.