All right.
Welcome back.
Let's talk a bit more about the hash function part of our hash table.
So we'll be using hash functions to convert keys like the string pink or what was the cyan and turn
that into a valid array index.
A small number but hash functions have uses all over the world of the Internet and privacy and just
computing in general.
So on Wikipedia the first use that is listed is indeed hash tables.
What we're talking about.
But they're also used to help protect your data to store your data to authenticate you when you log
in on a Web site they're used in crypto currencies and cryptography in general.
There's there's many many types of hash functions including a subgroup called cryptographic hash functions
which are crazy.
The math and the science behind them.
This is the stuff where I said there's like teams of researchers working on them cryptographic hash
functions are a crazy branch of cryptography which is already a crazy branch of science.
It's fun stuff.
I have of course.
Am I allowed to say that I may or may not have a course on this topic and on crypto currencies and how
it all fits together.
OK I hope I don't get in trouble for that.
Anyway what we're talking about are just basic hash functions and the definition of a basic hash function
is just a function that takes data of arbitrary size whether it's a thousand characters or a million
characters and it's going to spit out data of a fixed size.
It's going to map an input to an output of a fixed size.
So for us we just show you an example.
This is in Python which I know a lot of you probably don't know this is not a Python specific course
that's not important.
Languages like javascript actually don't expose a built in hash function but Python does and some others
do.
So I'm just going to use this here to demonstrate this is one type of hash function there's many many
implementations but this one allows us to pass in some data like let's say hello with an exclamation
point when I hit enter.
I get a number.
I'm not going to count the characters or the bits but of this size and I can do it again and just change
something slightly like make a capital H.
And I get a number of the same size.
It's shifted over because of this negative sign was there.
But if we look at the same time it is the same number of characters but it's totally different just
from changing that H.
But I could do a single character like a.
And I still get this really wrong number or I could do a super long string that is much larger than
that number and it's going to be condensed down to this.
Now a couple of things that we should talk about.
1.
So this is a fixed size.
This is similarly sized data no matter what the input is.
And that's important.
The other thing that I don't talk about is in most cases of a hash function we can't work backwards.
This is actually meaningless on its own.
If all we have is the output.
This is usually a one way function meaning that I can't just take this and figure out exactly what generated
this number.
So this hash function is generating pretty large relatively small in the grand scheme of things compared
to other hash functions.
But for us it's too large we don't want to store numbers.
You know what this index in an array.
Because then we're going to have a ton of empty space in our array.
We want to store stuff in an array of like 200 or 20 or even ten spot 10 elements.
And this is like what trillions.
I don't even know more than trillions probably.
So we're not going to use this hash function we're going to write our own simple one both talk about
what makes a good hash function.
So first up it needs to be fast.
We don't want to spend forever hashing something because when we insert something into our hash table
it needs to be hashed.
But also when we go and fetch it or update it or remove it every time we try to access it afterwards
we still have to run that hash function again.
Right.
I have to say hey what's the hash of pink that's going to give me a number and then I'm going to go
to that number in the array and then if I'm trying to update paint and when I say here's pink What's
the hash.
So we want it to be fast.
We want to make sure that it's relatively random or random serang term we want to make sure that it
distributes things uniformly so that things don't cluster we don't want to sit like a dumb hash function
that's always going to just give us the middle of an array or position zero.
It's useless if if every element is stored at the same spot.
Now we might have collisions and we'll talk about how to handle what we might have if we're only storing
things in a hundred spots in an array.
If we're storing like 500 things we're going to have to share some cubbyholes some elements there and
that's OK.
But we want it to be pretty evenly spread out.
And then lastly we want it to be deterministic and this is really important.
It means that every time we pass in one input we always get the same output it's determined that we're
going to get the same output.
We don't want to have to we don't want there to be any uncertainty or multiple answers or output per
one given input.
So we want the same input to always give the same output.
So let's just quickly run through those Here's an example.
This is a bad example which is why I wrote an example of a slow hash function.
We don't want this.
All it does is at the beginning it loops a thousand times 10000 times and just print something out and
then it does the hashing.
All right.
That's silly.
But we want to try and keep things quick and fast.
We don't want to have to you know loop a ton of times.
We want something that is constant time.
So we're going to write some of our own hash functions in just a bit.
Keep that in mind.
We want it to be fast.
We want it to distribute values uniformly.
So not like this which just gives zero.
This is a valid hash function if it meets our definition.
It takes an input of any size and it maps it to an output of fixed size.
It just maps every input to zero which is not what we want and then deterministic so it also is not
a good one because it is non-deterministic.
It involves a random number multiplied by 1000 and then floor that that's not good because that's not
going to give us the same output every time for the same input.
So in the next video I'm going to show you a simple hash function that we could write that will work
with strings only.
But it meets some of these criteria and then we'll try and tweak it and make it better.