All right let's try and write our own basic hash function for now just with strings.
So the goal is to write a function.
Let's just say it's called hash and we pass in a string like I don't know pink.
But on top of that we also pass in a length of an array.
So if we're trying to store our hash table in an array that is 100 items long we would pass in 100.
So this will map pink to be a number between 0 and 99 for a valid index in that array.
If we did Pink come nine this hopefully should give us a number between 0 and 8 so that we can store
it in the array and in a valid position.
So to write this let's ignore this last thing to start.
How would we just convert pink to a number.
There's many many ways.
But remember it needs to be reliable deterministic meaning that it you know is reproducible.
Every time we get the same output so we could just take the length of pink and just call it a day and
just used for.
The problem with that is that a lot of strings have the exact same length.
So if we're working with you know the English dictionary and we're trying to store words I don't know
what the most common length is but they're definitely small strings that you know traditional words
they're not very long.
So we're going to have very very clustered data.
If we had an array that was a 1000 character or a thousand positions long they'd all be less than.
I don't know what the longest word in English is but it's are all less than 50 characters probably and
most of them are less than 10 characters so that's not really great but there's another thing we can
do which is to use the underlying UTF 16 character codes for each character.
So every character has a numeric value associated with it and you can actually access that.
If we do a there's a method called Char code at or a car character code at and we have to pass in an
index like zero and that corresponds to the zero index of this string there's only one character and
it gives us a number.
Or if I had high and I did zero it's going to give me the number for H if I did it for one.
It gives me the number for I.
So these numbers we could use we could basically add them together for a given string.
Also to make it a little simpler if you subtract 96.
This will give us the alphabetic ranking or position.
So for example a is now 1.
If we did d it should be four.
And if we did Z that should be 26 perfect.
So that works.
It gives us you know the position in the alphabet starting from 1 up to 26.
So we can use this.
And on top of that we'll add them together.
So we'll continue to do this for every character in a string.
So let's say I have a variable called total to store everything in.
And then we're working with the string Hello.
So we would do total plus equals the character at position zero.
So car code at zero and then subtract 96 so that we just this is just to make it easier for us.
You don't have to subtract 96 it's still valid.
So that adds eight then we're going to do character code 1.
So that's for E.
We do this in a loop of course.
This is for oh this is for the other L then we get to 0.
Right.
Is that it.
One two three four five.
Yes.
So that's our total value in there.
So we get 52 but then we also need to consider that we talked about calling our hash function like this
or you'd pass in a string and then a length let's say 11 is our length of our array we need an index
that is going to be valid and 52 is not.
It's too large.
So how do we keep it within these bounds.
The simplest way is to use modulo if you don't know or don't remember modulo it's the percent sign operator
in javascript and in pretty much every language programming language at least think of it as you know
you divide something by a certain number and then you take the remainder.
That's what we store that's what we return.
So 13 mod 3 for example 3 goes into 13 how many times evenly four times.
Right.
Four times three is 12.
The remainder is 1.
We have one left over.
So if we take the length of the array that we're trying to store if I say 11 we take total which is
52 and I modulo Ahmad 11.
We end up with a number that is valid to store our data in which is 8.
So whatever the number was I mean we could take a giant number like this.
If I made by 11 we're going to get a valid array index now between zero and 10.
Just to prove that one more time.
Keep adding something you can see we're getting these numbers that are valid array indices.
So I have the function already written in the slide every go it looks like this function hash takes
a key like Pink an array length like 10 and then we make a total variable.
We loop through the characters in the key P and then I then and then K and then we add the character
code for each character to that total.
And actually the way that I decided to do it here is to use the maade array length as we build the string
as we are as we total up the string.
So instead of doing a mod at the very end we add each thing in we modulus by the array length and then
we start over again.
The way the hash function works is not the focus here but I just wanted to show you this is a basic
hash function.
It's not perfect but if we called hash with pink and we want to index less than 10 this one gives us
zero.
We do it with orange red.
We get 7.
We do it Ixion we get three.
So it appears to work.
I do have it over here as well.
We run it let's call a hash on pink just to make sure and we call 10 so that we get an index between
0 and 9.
I always get zero no matter what.
If I quit my browser I restarted.
I'm always going to get zero when I call pink with 10.
Now if I did instead of do let's do I don't know orange.
I also get zero so that's something we have to consider what we'll evaluate whether this is a good or
bad one in just a moment.
Let's try.
Blue zero also.
No.
How about saying.
OK.
So if you get three.
How about purple.
We get a.
And maroon.
All right.
So you see we do get these numbers and they're all less than 10.
So that works and every time I call it I get the exact same output according to the rules that I laid
out in the last video if there are a couple of problems with this current hash function.
First we're going to ignore this one but it only hashes strings right.
If you tried to give it a number or a boolean value or something like an array it's not going to work
because we're using a string method.
So that's a problem in general if we're trying to actually implement something legitimate but we're
not going to worry about that because that's not that's beyond the scope of this.
We're only carrying about strings but a bigger problem is that it's not constant time the time that
it takes the number of operations that we do depends on the length of the string or the size of the
data.
So if we pass in a larger string it takes longer to hash it.
It scales along with the size of the input.
So that's not good if we want to fix that.
And also this one is important.
It's not very random.
Our data can be clustered relatively easily.
And so we're going to talk about in the next video ways of improving number two and three here.
We of course we're going to end up with cluster data when we're working with numbers you know between
0 and 10.
There's only what 10 options for our values so of course we're going to have some duplicates.
But still this is not perfect.
We have ways of making it slightly more scattered.
And I'll give you a hint it involves using our friend the prime numbers our friends the prime numbers.
OK.
So in the next video will improve this so that we don't end up with this loop so that we can have a
constant time for our time complexity and then also add some prime numbers in to make this a little
more random or distributed evenly.