Welcome back.
So let's try and refine or revise our hash function from the last video just a little bit.
So it's still not going to be revolutionary it's not going to you know blow the minds of computer scientists
around the world.
It's going to be pretty bad.
But it's at least a little better than what we had in the last video.
So we're going to focus on improving its performance a little bit so that it runs closer to constant
time.
And then also we're going to try to increase the randomness of the distribution of things throughout
our buckets in our hash table.
So here's the code.
This is the original one that we had.
And the first thing we'll do to make it a little bit faster.
So if our key length you know our key approaches like 200 characters or 500 characters although there
is a maximum length to a string but let's just ignore that and say as our key becomes you know a million
characters.
We're not going to loop over every single character.
All that will do is add in a minimum.
So we're going to take math men between the length of the key and one hundred.
So whichever one of those is smaller is what we're going to actually loop.
So if our key is 30 characters then we're going to just loop 30 times.
But if our key is a million characters we'll just do the first 100.
So this is not a perfect solution but this will work for us for now just as a slight improvement.
And it's really honestly the reason I even put this here because we're not going to work with any characters
or any strings that are greater than 100 characters anyway.
I just included this to really hit on the point that you want your hash function to be as fast as possible.
But we're going to work with small strings that are like 10 characters anyway so this doesn't honestly
matter.
Now the second thing that we're going to do is add in prime numbers.
So I'm not going to go into a ton of math here because frankly I don't understand half of it.
There's a lot of I actually asked one of my friends is a math Ph.D. and I talked to him about this and
he wasn't totally clear on exactly how it works either but hashes hash functions almost always take
advantage of prime numbers and there's a couple of reasons but it comes down to reducing collisions.
Meaning that we don't want data to be stored in you know in the same buckets if we can avoid it.
We want to make sure that we are spreading data out as much as possible so that it's faster to retrieve.
So anyway I'm not going to go into a ton of detail or really any detail because it's complicated but
just know that prime numbers when you use them especially at the end if you are if the length of your
table itself the array that you're storing data in is a prime number like 31 items long or 13 items
long generally the larger the better the less likely it is for you to have collisions.
And just to illustrate this point did a little research.
There's this question ancora that has a really good answer.
There's a lot of really bad answers to this question on stack overflow.
People don't really explain it but this apparently is from some guest lecturer at MIT a while back and
this person ran a little experiment where they hashed 10 million pairs of data key value pairs using
different hash functions in different sizes of the actual list or the table they started in some of
them are prime.
And some of them were not.
And you can see let's just take a look at these first two hash functions for 10 million pairs of data.
This is the base.
It's called the search costs that basically the measurement of how many collisions there were.
So if we take a look between a prime number 8 1 9 1 that's a prime number 1.9 to collisions.
Now if we look over here we use an even number now.
Look at all these collisions.
This is bad.
We don't want more collisions.
So just using a different table length just one number smaller to make it prime lead to it's huge.
I mean multiple orders of magnitude decrease in the number of collisions so this is much much better
here.
Same thing with this different hash function.
We have 90 is our measurement of the collisions.
I don't really know how it's you know establish what 90 actually means but we can compare that to 4000
196 collisions when we use a non-prime length for our list.
So the hash table that we're storing things and it's always good to make it prime even if we don't go
into a ton of detail on exactly why you can see here just from this table.
Changing a prime number so it's just one number smaller but a prime number the length of the table versus
an even number.
Huge increase or decrease depending on how you look and look at it in the number of collisions.
So we're going to use a prime number for our length.
OK.
So here's our new hash function where we have our key in our array length.
This time we should use an array length that is prime.
So let's try hashing.
I don't know.
Hello.
And using 13 and we get 7.
Let's try doing it by 13 we get 9.
Let's try high 10.
I don't know Suyin we get five.
OK.
So we're not really going to be able to see if our distribution is any better in such a small dataset
right now and the length is only 13.
You want to use a larger prime number ideally.
But we're also only storing trivial pieces of data because this is just a a learning exercise so it
doesn't honestly matter.
But the improvements we made in principle at least are to speed this up so that we set a maximum.
We're only going to loop at most 100 characters so if you pass in a huge piece of data we're just going
to look at the first 100 and if at that point if we have two strings or two pieces of data that are
identical for the first 100 characters that's OK they'll collide.
We'll store them in the same place if you know that all of your data follows that pattern and you are
storing a thousand character strings in the first 100 is always the same.
And it was the last couple that were different.
Well then we'd probably tweak our out for them to start at the end of the string for example or we do
something.
But just for this sort of all purpose example we're going to cut it off at 100 characters really just
to show you that you should consider that even if it's not practical for us then also we're adding in
a prime number and we want our array length to be a prime number as well just to decrease the number
of collisions to make our data more distributed more random even though random is not really the correct
term because prime numbers aren't actually truly random in their distribution.
Not my wheelhouse at all.
But anyway whether this is a great hash function or not and it's definitely not it still works well
enough for us to implement a basic hash table.
So that's what we're going to work towards next.
What we have to talk about first is how we handle collisions because we will see if I can reproduce
to a mid-stride doing like what does pink give us point.
OK.
That gives us five as well.
So what happens when cyan and pink have the same index.
What do we do.
Do we store them both there.
Do we make the list longer.
How do we handle it.
That's what we've talked about in the next video.
There are two solutions.
And then we'll actually go and implement one of them create a full hash table.
So that's coming up next.
This is our basic hash function only works for strings.
We improved a little bit.
It's sort of constant time and also we add to prime numbers in so that it's slightly better distributed.
OK.