I'll come back.
So in this video let's talk about how we handle collisions.
So when we have a hash function whatever it is and we have a lot of data it's pretty likely or very
common that we will have some collisions even if we're working with huge data sets.
We have a great hash function we'll still have some collisions but we're doing none of that.
We're working with a small hash table and a bad hash function so we are definitely going to have collisions.
So how do we handle that.
There are many strategies for this but I'm going to talk about two of them here separate chaining and
linear probing.
So let's start by talking about separate chaining.
What happens here is basically we just store the pieces of data at the same spot using another nested
data structure.
So it could be another array or a length list or something else.
But we just store them in tandem or in tandem only applied to.
We store them all together.
Joint store them so we can store things multiple key value pairs at the same position.
So for example if this is our hash table let's say it's empty we each hash dark blue and we get four.
So we're going to put that right here.
But then we also hash salmon and we also get four.
And we also put that right there.
Notice that it's in a nested data structure where we have the array bracket.
Here goes all the way down to here so they are stored together.
This is the first item.
This is the second item.
So if we were trying to I don't know if someone asked me what's the value for salmon.
Well we've had hash salmon.
We get four.
So if we go to index four and then we just loop through we look for salmon in this list.
We know it's here somewhere.
But there could be 10 things here.
So we find salmon and once we find it then we get the corresponding value out and return that.
So that's one strategy we store things together.
If we're using an array it's easy to just use what we'll do a nested array.
The second strategy that we're going to talk about at least is called venir probing.
So many probing is a bit different.
We only store one piece of data at each position add to the rule that we'd try and live by and what
we do when there is a collision is we look forward ahead for the next empty slot.
It is a little more complicated but it does allow us to not have data stored at the same index you don't
have to store things in a nested structure.
So for example if you have an empty table again we do dark blue we get for what we put that for.
But then we do Sam and we get four again.
Well we're going to look at four.
There's something there.
So then we just look for the next empty slot which happens to be five.
So we could store it there.
Then we do tomato.
We get four again.
So we look.
Is there something there.
Yes.
So we're not going to store it there.
Look for the next one is that empty.
Nope.
Yes.
So we store it there.
So that's how linear probing works.
So just to recap linear probing involves storing one thing at each position and it means looking ahead.
Or you can look backwards as well but it's easier usually to look ahead to find an empty space to store
something.
And that's different than how we handle it with separate chaining or we store things together in sort
of in a nested data structure.
So we're going to implement separate chaining in our hash table.
It allows us to have you know more data than the length of our table.
We can store more than 10 things in this table.
When we talk about the we are probing though this only allows us to store 10 things because we're only
storing one thing at each position.
Soon we're going to run out of space and then what do we do.
Do we remove things or do we combine it in some way with separate chaining.
Once the whole table is filled do we grow the table.
There's so many options but we're going to go with separate chaining.
But I just wanted to show you there's also linear probing.
OK.
So two strategies for handling collisions.
Now that we've got all this basic stuff out of the way explaining what hash tables are writing hash
function we have that done.
We've talked about how we're going to implement or how we're going to approach collisions.
Let's now implement our class and actually write the code to make this work.