All right.
So let's get started.
Let's actually build out our hash table class.
I remember not going to be you know revolutionary were doing this really to understand how this all
works.
OK.
So here's the starter code.
Just copy this or type it out.
I'll include it as a file that's also in the slides.
We have our basic hash table class.
We have our constructor which accepts a size for how large the hash table should be.
And there's a default value of 53 because we want it to be a prime number.
So if we don't include a size it will just be 53 then what we do is make a new array of that size and
store that as key map.
This is where it will store all of the data.
This dumb key map then I just copied over the hash function.
I changed it slightly because now we don't have to pass in the size of the hash table because it's in
a class so we can access key map and you can see here we're modulo modulo ing modulus ing modding by
this that key mapped out length.
So here's the hash function.
We will be adding methods like set and get.
Which will then be calling underscore hash passing in the key and getting a value.
OK so here's where we're going to start.
First two methods are set and get so set accepts a value and a key.
I should say that the other way around a key and a value like pink corresponds to the value whatever
that hexadecimal code was 0 0 F F something something key and a value.
And what we're going to need to do is hash the key that's the first thing.
Figure out where to store it and then the second part.
We're doing this with separate chaining.
So it's a little more complicated than just storing the data there because we're going to store it in
a nested structure.
So just to remind you rewind here what that really means is when we hash something we get four.
We're going to go to index of four and check.
Is there anything here.
If not we're going to store it there.
But we store it in an array.
So a nested burst already.
So that next time through it we can just push onto this list if we have something else.
It's really easy to add it in.
So basically you're never going to just store the data here alone on its own.
If it's a single item you're still going to put it in a nested structure.
So your logic will be slightly different.
You need to hash the key and get that number go to that position and check if there's already data there.
If it is or if there is just push this on to the array that's already there.
If not put an array there first and then put the data inside that array.
So that's the pseudo code for set you except a key value you hash the key.
Then you store the key value pair in the hash table via a separate chaining meaning in a nested structure.
OK.
Now the way that get works is similar.
It accepts a key like salmon for example.
We're going to hash salmon and get that number back using our underscore hash function that's already
defined for you.
And once we get that value we go to the position that index in our array.
The key map array and we retrieve the value.
But of course what that actually means using separate chaining all more time winding here.
For example with salmon we hash that we get four.
We go to four.
There's there's possibly more than one item there.
So we need to check based off of the key salmon we're going to loop through these and try and find salmon.
And once we do we return this whole thing.
So there's no guaranteed order within.
So we don't know if salmon will be the first one the second one the fifth one we're just going to check.
Once we get to index for where salmon is we're just going to look for salmon in that nested list.
And then finally if it's not in our hash table at all return undefined.
Just make sure it works if someone tries to retrieve a value that's not there.
We don't want a break or code should return undefined.
OK.
So add these set and get to this code or use your own hash function if you'd like but just make sure
that it you know is it meets the important criteria is deterministic always the same output for a given
input and give it a shot.
Let's implement this in the next video.