OK.
So let's start with set.
It's pretty short.
Basically we've already done this part except to key and a value we need to hash the key and then take
the result when we hash the key.
Store the key value pair in the hash table at that location via separate chaining.
So that's the only caveat that makes it a little harder is we need to store things potentially nested
within that index.
So let's start with the basic part.
So let's hash Arkie all we have to do is call this dot underscore hash and we pass in the key and save
that to a variable.
So let's just call that index.
So that's going to go give us the index.
For example let's just return index.
OK.
So let's come down here and let's make a variable called H.T. just so that we can test everything out.
And let's try to do H.T. DOT says let's do hello world and the value will be goodbye.
OK.
Doesn't matter.
Now if we run that all right we're getting index 40 and the default is 53 is our size.
If we change that to be and are 17 try again we now get 11 something within the bounds and every time
we run this code we should get 11.
OK.
So that's giving us the index but we don't want to just return the index.
What we want to do now is insert the value at that index the key and the value together.
But there's a problem which is that we need to do the whole separate chaining thing which if this is
our key map if it looks like this and it's empty everywhere let's just visualize that with the spaces.
If this is what it looks like we need to insert an index.
Let's say right here whatever this is indexed to.
If there's nothing there we're going to put an empty array and then add our list our key comma value
like this.
If there's already something there we're going to need to do a check either way.
Is there something here if there is then we just add in our next set of key and value and we nest them.
So I'm just going to do a little check after we have the index.
I'm going to do if there is not this dot key map of our index meaning take the index we got back like
11 and check this that key map at index of 11.
Is there anything there but not.
Is there nothing there.
If that's the case that means that we set it to an empty array.
So that's the first thing we need to do.
This key map of index equals empty array and then Either way we're going to do this key map of that
index push a new array with key and value and that's it.
OK.
So there's two scenarios.
If we insert something we do a set with a key and a value that gives us an index that is currently unused.
There's nothing there it's unoccupied We're first going to check if it's unoccupied and then set the
index of that array of our key map to be an empty array and then we add in we do a push with our key
and value pair.
However if there's already something in there like if we had already run this and then we ran something
else that gave us 11 again then this part is not true it doesn't run.
So we just push key and value a new array into the parent array of that index.
So let's just test that it works.
And how could I best test this.
Let's make our size pretty small like four.
And then I'm going to do a couple of sets of fastforward.
Ok I added a couple of things in just random strings and if I execute this now remember I changed the
size the default to be 4.
So it's going to be tiny.
And when I run it we look at our hash table.
What do we have.
OK so our key map has an array.
So there's something at index 0 1 and 3 there's nothing in index 2 and there's four things inserted
and we can see that they are sharing index of 1 to index if one contains an array with cats are fine.
And I love pizza more keys and values.
So there's a key value pair and another key value pair both which were hashed to index of one appear.
We have a single entry.
Same thing down here index of three is single entry.
So if I were to add something else in let's do each set.
I don't know.
I'm just going to do hi fi.
Where did it go.
Let's look.
Looks like it was also inserted there.
So we pushed it into this existing array inside of index of one tried again something else.
Where is it go this time.
OK.
So I did french fries and that was inserted at index too.
There was nothing there.
Before we go back up here we only had index 0 1 and 3.
There was nothing at index 2.
Now there is and our logic works we're adding the array the empty array first and then pushing in our
data.
OK.
So that is set.
And what we need to do next is get this video is getting a bit long so I'll do get in a separate video
after this one.