All right in the last video we implemented set.
Now let's work on get so get needs to accept a key like pink and then go and look in our hash table
and use the hash that key.
Right.
And we need to get an index.
Then we look to see if it's if there's something in the hash table at that index.
And if not then we return undefined or false or something.
Otherwise we need to return the value itself which depending on how many things are in there.
Because with the way we're doing this with separate chaining there could be five or ten values or more
doesn't really matter inside of this one index.
So we need to find the correct key and value inside of that index in a nested list.
So retrieve the key value pair and then return it and return undefined if you can't find it.
OK so I've updated my example stuff example stuff that's not a good way of putting it.
I've updated our demo hash table here with some real colors and color codes.
These are all Chimo or CSSA built in named colors medium Violet red.
And this is the hexadecimal color code.
OK.
I've also updated the sides appear to be 17 although honestly I probably should have just specified
here and then put this back at what was it that 53 was it doesn't matter that much.
OK.
So we have get written here the skeleton takes the key and the first thing we need to do is hash that
key.
So I'm just going to copy this here.
Get an index.
Let index equals this underscore a hash of our key.
So whatever is passed in OK then we need to first check.
Is there something at that index.
So let's just do a.
If this dunky map of that index index like that.
So if there's not if there's nothing there at that index then we know for sure we can return undefined.
Right.
So if we do find an index or if we find something at the index let's say that we get index of 8.
Well there is something there but what do we need to do.
Well we can't just return to the first thing.
We can't return the entire context of that index.
If we did that let's just to turn this key map of index first of all let's run our code again.
Let's do h t get.
What color do I have in there.
Yellow.
What does he give me.
Well it gives me the entire element in our hash table at that index which happens to contain two items.
What we want is to return this sub array the child.
So we need to loop over potentially any values in there and then find what we're looking for and return
that entire suburb.
So rather than that we're going to do a for loop start at zero.
Just loop over an array.
So while it is less than this key map index length plus plus.
So this occurs once we've found the correct spot.
Like if I look at the hash table I suppose you know we hash the key yellow it comes back as the index
8.
So we found the data at 8.
So now we need to loop over this which is an array of two items but we could have 10 things here and
we might be looking for the last thing or the middle thing or the first thing.
But we're going to start a variable at zero just a standard loop.
While it's less than the length of the item at this index which in our case is a subgroup of two items
we are going to add one to I.
And then we're just going to check if this dot key map and what we're actually looking for is to see
if the key that was passed in equals the first item in this array and the first item in this array until
we find what we were looking for.
So if this key math index of I that's going to give us this summary here or this subquery here.
Then we want the 0 item where restoring the key because we're storing our key first and then the value
if that equals the key that we're looking for then we're going to I'm going to do it on a separate line
because it's kind of a long statement but returned this key map and we want to return index of the entire
subarray.
So let's test it out.
Can it run this.
We've got our hash table.
And let's do a get first of something that is in there like yellow.
OK.
So we get the correct array.
Yellow is our key and our value is that color code.
If we try and do something that's not in there we get undefined.
Let's just double check let's try doing plumbe.
What else was stored alongside the index 8 we had maroon.
So let's just check it works and we try and get maroon because that's really the harder case.
It looks like it's working to try and get plum I already did pull them didn't I.
About salmon.
All right well it looks good to me.
Except for the fact that when we do get like if I do all of we get the entire array we just want the
value.
So if we come back to get right here don't return the entire array return the value which is the second
item index of 1 0 1.
All right.
Try it again.
Let's do H.T. don't get all of.
All right.
It's working right.
We get the corresponding value not the entire thing.
And if we try and add something new that's set.
Are we done to be.
Yes.
If we do get are we done we get.
All right.
So that's working.
And that is the basics of get.
So we hash the key that's provided to get an index.
Then we check if the key map even contains anything at that index.
If not we just return undefined.
Right.
If I try and do this we get undefined.
Otherwise we're going to check over every single item that is contained at that index.
There might be one there might be 50.
We loop over and we check for each one.
Are you the thing we're looking for is your key index of 0 equal to my key that I'm looking for.
If it is return the value.
So this Taqi Mac key map index I of one not the most intuitive looking code that beautiful but the shortest
way of doing it or at least one of the shorter ways.
All right.
So let's get.