All right.
Welcome back.
Next up we have two more methods to add to our hash table.
Are very similar just to them in one video.
Extremely similar.
There's one method called keys which returns an array a list of all the keys in our table.
So you need to collect all of the keys and then another one called values that does the same thing but
for values so it collects all the values in a single array and returns that array.
So if you've done much programming before and pretty much any language there is a way to iterate over
a hash table a dictionary javascript object and it often involves looking at the keys or looking at
the values as an array or some sort of iterable list and then looping over that.
So we're just going to implement similar functionality using our two method keys and values.
One thing that I didn't write here but I would pay attention to is how you handle duplicate data.
For example values it's very likely that we might have multiple values that are exactly the same.
For example for keeping track of grades inside of our like if I'm a teacher and I'm going to map you
know Colts got to see Dave got an A.
Liane Lizanne.
Has it got a C.
That sort of thing.
Well there were two c's as the values do we return both of them.
Or do we return one and most of the time it's just the unique values that you return and the unique
keys that you return and kids are supposed to be unique anyway but values aren't so feel free to implement
it.
Either way I will show both.
So you can see how it works but implement two methods keys and values that are very very similar.
You can copy and paste the code from one to the other and just slightly tweak it.
Have a solution.
Up next.