All right.
So let's implement our methods keys and values.
I'm going to start with values actually because that's the one where we really have to worry about duplicate
data.
So let's start there and all we need to do really is make an array to store all of our data.
So I'll call it values r r r like that.
And then we need to loop over the entire key map this key map.
So let's just write a for loop for equals zero.
Oh I hate typing these when I'm not using my usual editor this key map.
And we want to go Lanc and then I.
Plus plus.
So this is just going to loop over the entire key map like executer this.
I haven't run it yet.
If we look at H.T. here we're going to loop over all 17 items here.
And the first thing we'll check is there anything there.
So if this key map of I if that's the case then let's just start by constantly logging this key map.
And if I run this and then I do H.T. values.
It's printing out all the arrays that have stuff it's skipping over all of the empty ones because we're
working with something that has 17 slots and we're only using what five six of them six different slots.
So there are 11 empty things we're not printing out.
So that's good.
So what we want to do instead is loop over this key map of I because we now need to loop through that
and collect all the values and push them into our values array.
So we need to go over each one of these and find this item.
The second piece.
So this is index 0.
This is Index index of 1.
OK.
So let's do another for loop.
This time will do let's call it J 4 let J equal 0.
J is less than this key map of I got length.
So this key map of I is referring to each cell array at that index.
J plus plus.
OK.
So for each item in there now what.
All we need to do is values array up push.
And we only want to push the value.
So that is this key map of I of J that gives just the entire thing.
So if I did this and I run this values over not returning anything so that's useless.
That was a very dumb example.
Let me add the return to the very end.
Let's come down.
Words are correct.
Bracket let's do return values array.
OK rerun the code age values.
If we look at it we are still returning an array that contains both the key and the value.
So we only want index of 1 for each one of those items.
And if I run it again would you H.T. the values.
We're now getting all of the values.
So if you call it a day here.
But then there's also this problem of duplicate data.
And like I said the way a lot of languages handle it is when you do dot values or whatever the equivalent
is you only get the unique values.
You often don't.
You don't get all the duplicates because there's usually no order that's guaranteed.
And it can be confusing if you have duplicate data.
Usually it's just the uniques.
So how would we implement that.
Well the simplest way is before we push it into the values array we just check.
Does this key map already or does the values array already include this item.
First let's get some duplicate data in there.
So I'm going to add a purple with this DD a 0 0 DD.
And let's also add in something else called Violet like this.
And so if I rerun this and we look at our values you can see that we have what was that DDA 0.
DD is in there one time two times three times.
So to prevent that we'll come over here and before we push let's add a conditional we'll say if the
values array that includes And we'll use the built in includes method.
This key map I J 1 this mean this is the value itself.
So each time through.
Well check does it include DDA 0.
DD these color codes are not the most intuitive thing for me to be talking about but if it includes
this we don't want to push so let's do the opposite say if not if it does not include then we'll push
this in like that.
And let's just test it out now.
So I'm using the built in includes method.
So if we try H.T. dot values.
Now we only get one of these Deedy a zero d d.
All right so that's one way of hand handling duplicate values so that we only end up with unique values
in our dataset that we're returning.
Then we return it at the end.
We just check each time through for each value.
Does that already include that value if it doesn't push it in.
So we could just duplicate the exact same thing and do these.
So change the name of this to be kids and we'll will call this kid's array even though it doesn't actually
make a difference.
Functionally this will be the same.
This is the same this here it's also the same.
But then this changes so this is going to be kids value are kids Auray includes that key map I J of
zero because our key each key is stored at index 0 rather than 1.
OK.
And then this also needs to be zero.
And this needs to be KIIS array up push.
And then we return keys array.
So if we test it out.
Now let's do H.T. duckies we get however many values there how many kids that is.
And if we do the same thing for values there we go.
We get fewer of course because we had duplicate values.
Now we didn't address what to do with duplicate keys.
If somebody inserts something right now if I actually go and insert plumbe again which is already in
there so H.T. set plumbe which is going to be double like that.
If we look at our hash table you can see that they're both stored nested next to each other inside of
index 0.
So they plumpest hash to the exact same thing zero each time that's how it should work.
But we end up with two children there.
And so when I do an h t get plumb our logic right now is just going to give me whatever was inserted
first and it should always stay that way.
Based off of how it's set up right now.
Now it's probably a better solution to alert your user to that so here you know we could add some logic
to check if it's already in there.
You know when we're setting something we would check if it's empty.
OK.
It's not empty.
Then you could iterate over the entire thing and check to see if it already contains that key.
We're just going to go with this simple implementation for now.
Right now it allows you to insert many things at the same key and you're only going to get the first
one that was inserted and that's fine for now.
It's not supposed to be very useable anyway but just keep that in mind that most languages if you tried
to you know insert something multiple times it would overwrite what you already had.
So if we did not set plumbe to be double That's what plumbe would be from now on.
But either way we've implemented keys and values.
There really aren't supposed to be duplicate keys but this code here ensures that we're not getting
duplicates.
Same thing down here with values.
So that's keys and values.
Now we could call you know dot keys or down values and iterate over the entire hash table if that's
what we wanted to sort of print out every single color that we have.
We could do something like T Dot keys and do a dot.
I don't know a dot for each maybe and call each phone.
Let's go with key and then just to cancel the log H.T. don't get key.
And if we tried running it we get every single value printed out and we do have two there because we're
using the keys and just getting the value based off of that.
And it looks good.
So we're officially getting the keys and the values with our separate methods and we can iterate over
them now.
All right.
So that is the basics of hash tables.
Again not sophisticated.
Not something you should really use in this implementation but hopefully it makes sense how it works.