All right.
So we've implemented the basics of a hash table.
We have a way of inserting we have a way for treating a value.
We also did the keys and values methods which aren't as important to be honest.
Now let's talk about the big-O the time complexity in particular of these basic operations.
So insertion deletion and accessing data on average and also best case are both one constant time which
is fantastic That's great.
And this really comes down to how how good your hash function is one how fast the hash function itself
is into how evenly it distributes things.
Minimize the number of collisions.
Remember that big O is a simplification of things.
We remove constants we simplify whenever possible.
So saying that you know our time complexity is low one for insertion doesn't mean that there's only
one operation that it takes to insert.
It just means the general trend.
So it is possible to write a good hash function that is constant time and pretty much every programming
language that has an implementation of a hash table has a constant time hash function.
Now that's different than a cryptographic hash function which does need to actually run for every single
bit of data as it as input grows.
Let's say a file grows from one megabyte to 200 megabytes.
The hash function needs to actually traverse or parse every piece of that data.
If it's a cryptographically secure hash function but when we're talking about hash tables it's OK if
we only look at part of the data only part of the string in our case which is what we did.
So it's possible to write in general a constant time hash function so insertion deletion and an access
in general average case best case are constant.
So if we had a good hash function and this is our dataset visualized where this is showing you know
one piece of data stored here this is talking about separate chaining.
So we have you know certain indices have two pieces even if it takes us one operation to hash our data
lets say we're retrieving accessing something like we're accessing this value here.
So I have to first hash the key.
Then it tells me index 9.
I go to index 9.
Well there's two pieces here.
So I have to go look at the first one and then the second one.
And overall we would still say that is constant time because it's three operations every time.
Or five operations every time.
But if we grew this to be 10000 items or 20000 positions elements in our hash table we would expect
it to with a good hash function be evenly distributed.
It is possible that we could have a really bad hash function that distributes everything really unnervingly
everything into one index which would be pretty useless.
But if this was the case if I wanted to retrieve or if I wanted to insert I wanted to delete something
from the end it's going to be 0 of end time because even if my hash function itself is constant time
if it's distributing everything into one spot then it's basically just a list and to insert at the end
of a list is o event and it's linear time.
So it really comes down to how good your hash function is how fast it is itself but also how evenly
distributes things.
And this is why I don't recommend writing your own hash functions use ones that are known that are implemented
by other languages.
There's lots of libraries on line so if you do have to do that I recommend you using something that
someone else has already done.
So in general when we talk about hash tables they're very very fast.
One constant time for insertion deletion and accessing and when I say access that means using a given
key finding the corresponding value.
When we talk about searching well for searching for a key it can still be very fast.
It can be constant time but if we are searching for a value then we need to go through every single
thing every item and check so that would be OK.
And all right so that's a big no.
In general time complexity for hash tables.
Now let's do a quick recap.
So hash tables are collections of key value pairs.
Cool.
They exist in many languages are already implemented dictionaries in Python.
They're similar to objects are actually closer to maps in javascript.
Pretty much every language has an implementation so hash tables can find values very quickly using a
key.
They can add key value pairs very quickly as well.
And the way that we implemented our hash table was using an array where we hash the keys to get an array
index and then we store the data at that position.
So our hash function is really important.
So a good hash function.
Also a lot of people will just say good hash should be fast ideally constant time and this is talking
about hash table hash map hash functions not cryptographically secure hash functions.
Those have some different rules but they should be fast.
They should distribute keys relatively uniformly.
We don't want any sort of conflicts if possible.
We want things to be stored as spread out as possible and we want it to be deterministic.
We need to get the exact same output every time with the same input and then strategies for when we
have two kids with the same index when we hash something we get the same index in our array there's
at least two that we talked about separate chaining and linear probing separate chaining involves storing
them together in a nested structure in the same array index linear probing involves looking forward
for the next empty slot.
And we focused on separate chaining.
All right so that was hash tables.
Again our hash function was very simple.
It was not written with the intent to be very useful.
Really more as educational demo but overall hash tables hash maps are super super useful.
We use them all the time pretty much any time you need to store key value data.
It makes sense to use a hash table.
All right.